<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The memory of that faithful servant of the Lord Thomas Carleton, reviv'd. Being a collection of several of his vvritings in the ensuing volume as a testimony of his zeal for promoting the blessed truth and establishing of Friends therein. : Also some testimonies concerning his faithfulness and perseverance in the way of the Lord, unto the finishing of his course here with joy, which was the 18th day of the ninth month, 1684.</title>
            <author>Carleton, Thomas, 1636?-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 105 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80359</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C589A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170899</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578211</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172162</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80359)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172162)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2616:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The memory of that faithful servant of the Lord Thomas Carleton, reviv'd. Being a collection of several of his vvritings in the ensuing volume as a testimony of his zeal for promoting the blessed truth and establishing of Friends therein. : Also some testimonies concerning his faithfulness and perseverance in the way of the Lord, unto the finishing of his course here with joy, which was the 18th day of the ninth month, 1684.</title>
                  <author>Carleton, Thomas, 1636?-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 184 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Carleton, Thomas, 1636?-1684.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  England --  Biography.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172162:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MEMORY OF That Faithful Servant of the Lord <hi>Thomas Carleton,</hi> Reviv'd.</p>
            <p>BEING A COLLECTION
<list>
                  <item>Of ſeveral of his VVritings in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Volume as a Teſtimony of his Zeal for promoting the bleſſed Truth and Eſtabliſhing of Friends therein.</item>
                  <item>Alſo ſome TESTIMONIES Concerning his Faithfulneſs and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance in the Way of the Lord, unto the Finiſhing of his Courſe here with joy, which was the 18th day of the Ninth Month, 1684.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>The Memory of the juſt is bleſſed,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 10.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The Righteous ſhall be had in Everlaſting Remembrance,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 112.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:172162:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172162:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Teſtimony of</hi> Thomas Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, <hi>concerning his Friend and Brother, in the Truth,</hi> Thomas Carleton.</head>
            <p>THere is a Teſtimony in my Heart at this time, to bear for dear <hi>Thomas Carleton,</hi> Notwithſtanding it is long ſince he was Removed from us, as to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, yet his Memorial lives with me, and in the Revivings of it; can do no leſs then ſay ſomething of the Experience &amp; Knowledg I had of him.</p>
            <p>My firſt acquaintance with him was by the Spirit of Truth in a Meeting, for as ſoon as I ſaw his Face, as he was coming into the Meeting, I felt my heart united, or knit to him, as <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s was to <hi>David;</hi> and it was ſealed to me, That he had a Teſtimony to bear
<pb facs="tcp:172162:3"/>for the Lord's Truth, in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of his People, which was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to me that Meeting: For after ſome time ſitting in the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, there came an Exerciſe upon his Spirit, and he ſtood up in great Fear and Dread, which was his uſual man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner when he was ſo Exerciſed under the powerfull Word of Life; not being a Man forward in entring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſervice, but rather backward, until neceſſitated thereunto by the conſtraining Power of God.</p>
            <p>And while he was delivering his Teſtimony, I had dear unity with him, and my Soul was refreſhed by his Miniſtry, although he was but ſhort, and my love reached ſo to him, that I could not be ſatisfied untill I went to ſee him at his Lodging; after which time we grew into a more near acquaintance one with another, both inwardly and outwardly, ſo that we became near and dear one unto another, and thereby came to have a
<pb facs="tcp:172162:3"/>true ſenſe and knowledge of one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers Mind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Spirits; and truly my heart and ſpirit is broken at this time, in the remembrance of that ſweet and brotherly love, that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued between us to the laſt; for he was a true Yoke-fellow in the Labour of the Goſpel, for the good and wel-fare of the Church; and I muſt needs ſay, I have found the want of him (with ſome others who were true ſenſible Members in the Body or Church of Chriſt,) whom the Lord hath been pleaſed to remove from us, and take to himſelf, which I muſt be content with, reſting in the Faith that he can and will raiſe up others in his time to ſupply their places.</p>
            <p>And although this my Friend and Brother, was a Man attended with many Infirmities of Body, which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled him from Travelling much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, yet I can ſay he was ſeldom, if ever, without a Concern, Care, or Exerciſe upon his Spirit, that all
<pb facs="tcp:172162:4"/>things might be well in the Church, and that thoſe who were Convinced of the Truth, might live anſwerable to what they did profeſs, and was many a time Conſtrained to bear Teſtimony in a holy Zeal againſt ſuch as were dry Formiliſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of it, and did not come up into a Living Experimental Exerciſe of the power of Truth, and ſuch who walked looſe in their Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; as will appear by the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Epiſtles that he Writ; and God who tempers the Body as he Sees meet, had indued him with a large and clear underſtanding, both in Divine Spiritual things, and alſo Natural Parts, beyond many; which did very much adorn him, and ſo much the more, in that he did not think ſo of himſelf, but would appear as ſimple as any, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoke him to be one of Chriſts Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, who had Learned to be Meek and Lowly in heart.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:172162:4"/>
            <p>I Write what I know, and it is not to attribute any thing to Man, but to acknowledge the great Work of God, in and for Man, who as Veſſels in his Hand he hath honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; therefore we who have been made partakers of their Work and Service, can do no leſs. And indeed all his Parts and Gifts were Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied unto him, for he was a Man of of a ſweet temper, mild in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting things, and could govern his Spirit with gravity, either with ſuch as did oppoſe Truth and contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, or at other times in Church Diſcipline, or with unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirits, that he might have to do with.</p>
            <p>Oh the Remembrance of him, makes the loſs of him more to be Lamented! But having this anſwer returned &amp; ſealed unto me, that our loſs is his gain therefore am Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the will of the Lord; and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his Parts did exceed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb facs="tcp:172162:5"/>yet he was ready to prefer others before himſelf, which was an Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him, and did very much become his Holy Profeſſion, he was a Man that Loved the Truth, and all ſuch that lived in it, and he was of a tender Spirit, deſiring nothing more then the Unity of the Brethren, and to hear of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of Truth, and Peace in the Church.</p>
            <p>So that I have cauſe to believe he is one of that Number to whom it is ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed are the Dead which Die in the Lord, from henceforth,</hi> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſaid the Spirit <hi>that they may reſt from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Labours, and their Works do follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written </hi> 
                  <date>this 15th day of the 6. <hi>Month</hi> 1693.</date> 
                  <hi>At</hi> Wicklow <hi>by one that loves the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thomas Trafford<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:172162:5"/>
            <head>THE TESTIMONY OF <hi>GEORGE ROOKE</hi> Concerning <hi>Thomas Carleton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis I have to ſay concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this our dear Friend, and Brother in the Truth, that is removed from us by Death, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God's appointment for all
<pb facs="tcp:172162:6"/>Men once to Die) he was a Man that was tender of Gods glory in his Day, and laboured for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of his Truth; into the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of which the Lord was pleaſed to Call him when he was but young in years, and made known unto him the riches of the Miſtery which had been hid from Ages paſt, even Chriſt Revealed within the ſure Hope of Eternal Glory; by which he was preſerved both ſure and ſtedfaſt in his Teſtimony-bearing for God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Lord was pleaſed to Order him; whether it was in a Priſon-houſe, or at Liberty, he was not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to ſubmit to his Will, even to do and ſuffer, whereby he might honour and glorifie his Maker in his day and generation.</p>
            <p>And he had not long been Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the bleſſed Truth, till <hi>Lewis Weſt</hi> the Prieſt of the Pariſh where
<pb facs="tcp:172162:6"/>he lived, began to perſecute him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe for Conſcience-ſake he could not pay Tythes, and caſt him into Priſon at <hi>Carliſle</hi> in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> for at <hi>Little-Salkeld</hi> in that County, was the place of his abode then, though ſome years after his Enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he removed himſelf and family into this Nation of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>mark,</hi> he being put in Priſon was kept Priſoner ſeveral years, by reaſon of the hard-hearted cruelty, of the Prieſt that ſought for his Goods more then for the good of his Soul as plainly appears by thoſe his unchriſtian-like Actions; even like thoſe of old that would cry <hi>Peace, Peace</hi> while People put into their Mouths, but when for Conſcience-ſake they could not do it, then thoſe falſe Teachers prepar'd War againſt them; and thus he that is born af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:172162:7"/>the fleſh, perſecutes him that is born after the ſpirit from one Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to another: But after this his ſo long Impriſonment, it pleaſed God to make way for his delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of thoſe Bonds, by the Death of the ſaid Prieſt his perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who on a journey, broke his Legg, whereof he Died, without ever Returning home, but his Wiſe fulfilling her Husband's Cruelty, would not condeſcend to his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement which was in her power to do, but conſtrained him to go to <hi>London</hi> being above Two hundred Miles, which he Travelled on Foot, and ſo obtained his full Liberty by a <hi>Habias Corpus,</hi> the Lord having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued him with Chriſtian patience all this time, to undergo what he permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his perſecutor to Inflict upon him.</p>
            <p>And after this it was ſome time my lot to travel with him in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb facs="tcp:172162:7"/>of Truth, in whoſe Company I had great ſatisfaction, for he did not only Preach in <hi>Word</hi> &amp; <hi>Doctrine,</hi> but in <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Converſation</hi> alſo, and ſo was A rightly qualifi'd Miniſter of the Goſpel; and was a ſerviceable Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in the Church of Chriſt, both for the Propagating of Truth, and a Support to Friends where he Lived and Travelled; the Lord having endued him with a good Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which did ſo ſanctifie his Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral acquirements, that he was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by qualified to anſwer his Call into the Miniſtry, which he delivered in Meekneſs, according to his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment in his Converſation, which which was Mild &amp; Courteous, little in his own Eye, or in outward ſhew or appearance; <hi>Yet would not turn his back off an Enemy to Truth, in Truth's defence; and he was qualfi'd for Truth's ſervice in his open and plain Teſtimony, which was both ſweet and
<pb facs="tcp:172162:8"/>lively to the Comforting the Faithful, ſtirring up the Careleſs, and reaching the Witneſs in thoſe who were unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Way of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For indeed his Labour in the Work of the Goſpel was refreſhing to the honeſt-hearted, who as a faithful Steward over the manifold Grace's of God (a meaſure of which was committed to his Charge) did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruly Labour in the Service thereof, not by conſtraint but willingly, not for filthy Lucre, but with a ready Mind; neither as being Lord over God's Heretage, but being an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample unto the Flock; for which I doubt not, he hath his <hi>Reward</hi> at the Hand of the great Shepheard, <hi>even a Crown of Glory that fadeth not away.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:172162:8"/>
            <p>And now I ſhall ſpeak a little of his manner of Life towards his lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter End, for as he had been an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent carriag'd Man, and a lover of Truth and Righteouſneſs from a Child, ſo it pleaſed God to preſerve him all along even to his Lifes end; although attended many times with great Weakneſs of Body, by reaſon of ſome Diſtempers occaſioned part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the aforeſaid Impriſonment, which he underwent for his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony's ſake, which God had given him to bear againſt the Anti-chriſtian Miniſtry of the Age; Yet that ſaying was fulfilled in him, as in the Apoſtles time, although the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man periſhed, and grew weaker and weaker, the Inward Man was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed day by day; for theſe light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions which laſt but for a moment, work in us a far more Exceeding and Eternal weight of Glory; while we look not at thoſe things that are ſeen,
<pb facs="tcp:172162:9"/>but at the things that are not ſeen, for the things that are ſeen are Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, but the things that are not ſeen are Eternal: So we need not fear any of theſe things that we may ſuffer for a good Cauſe; if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil be permitted to caſt ſome into Priſon, and we may have Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for a time, yet the promiſe is to thoſe that are <hi>Faithful unto Death, they ſhall receive a Crown of Life;</hi> So although many be the Tryals and Exerciſes of the Righteous, yet the Lord in his own appointed time, can and will deliver out of them all; and although for a time the Back be given to the ſmiter, yet the Rod of the Wicked ſhall not always be upon the Backs of the Righteous, but God will Reſcue them out of their hands, that they ſhall not be a prey to them any longer.</p>
            <p>But too few Conſider when Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and Good Men are taken away,
<pb facs="tcp:172162:9"/>that it's God's Pleaſure and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to them, to take them from the Evil to come, as he hath done our dear Friend of whom I am writing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And though he be removed from us, yet the remembrance of his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Life, doth remain with us, and although it be our loſs, yet it is his gain.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>In that Eternal Joy &amp; Reſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where his Soul's for ever bleſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>And when he was upon his Death-bead, he was ſweetly preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in a ſenſe of that Life that flowed from the Fountain of pure Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which made him to utter ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſavoury Expreſſions, even to the Edifying of thoſe that ſtood by him: ſome of which that could be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred are here inſerted: For when I with ſome other Friends went to ſee him, we had a Meeting at his
<pb facs="tcp:172162:10"/>Houſe at <hi>Ballany Carrick</hi> in the County of <hi>Wicklow,</hi> on the firſt day of the Week, before he departed this Life, being the 16th day of the Ninth Month 1684. where he ſat up in the Meeting all the time, and we had a Heavenly ſeaſon, and the Lord's refreſhing Preſence was with us, which he having a ſenſe of, did often expreſs his great Joy and Satisfaction therein, and in the enjoyment of Friends company; and ſaid he could wiſh (if it were the Will of God) that he might be taken away when we were there; So I with ſome other Friends ſtay'd all Night, and lodged in the Chamber where he lay, and he was very quiet, and patiently bore his Affliction.</p>
            <p>The next Morning one of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants coming to him, ask'd him how he did, his anſwer was to her, naming her by her Name; thou
<pb facs="tcp:172162:10"/>haſt had much trouble in attending of me, but now the time is ſhort that I have to ſtay; for he was not unſenſible that the time of his Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution drew near; his ſervant being reached with his words, began to weep, he ſaid I know there will be Mourning for me, but (bleſſed be God) it is not as thoſe that have no hope; for he knew that hope which was grounded upon the Foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles Jeſus Chriſt being the Chief Corner-ſtone, the ſame that all the Faithful did bear Witneſs too in former Ages:</p>
            <p>And ſo that day was chiefly ſpent in preparing for the time of his Change, in ſetting his Houſe in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſetling his outward Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns; and when he came to Sign his Will, his Hand ſhoke by reaſon of weakneſs of Body; He looking up with a chearful Countenance, ſaid, O, is it ſo! that I who have written
<pb facs="tcp:172162:11"/>ſo much, can ſcarce now write my Name, well, it muſt be ſo, and the Will of the Lord be done, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; and thus was his precious time ſpent, in giving and reſigning himſelf up unto the Will of the Lord, ſaying, come Lord Jeſus receive my Spirit: And ſo about the ſixth hour at Night, as he was in a ſlumber fell into a Fit or Trance, <hi>Jonathan Nichol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> his Brother in Law being with him in Bed, heard him ſay as he fell into a fit, Farewell, Farewel, Farewell, three times, as if he had been wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the time of his change, but in about half an hour he again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, and came to his perfect ſenſes as before: Three of his Children being brought to him, he called to them by their Names, ſaying, dear Babes, I am glad to ſee you, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing it with much joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, adviſing them to live in the fear of God, and to be good Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb facs="tcp:172162:11"/>and to keep amongſt Friends; and ſaid I have not much Gold and Silver to leave you, but I hope the bleſſing of the Lord will attend you; and ſo Kiſſing and Embracing them he took leave of them; his dear Wife coming to him weeping, he ſaid to her, Weep not, thy care and tenderneſs hath been much over me; and often ſeemed to lament and pitty his dear Wife, that had been a true Help-meet unto him from the time of their firſt coming together unto that day, in his Exerciſes and Weakneſs, which were not a few.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſo after he had taken his leave of thoſe about him, he fell into another fit, and in leſs then half an hour was taken away with little or no pain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the</hi> 18th <hi>Day of the aforeſaid ninth Month</hi> 1684.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:172162:12"/>
            <p>This is to be noted, that he often in his Life time, when in great pain and affliction by reaſon of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper of his Body, did deſire the Lord to mitigate his pain upon his Death-bed, and not take him away in thoſe Tortering fits; which the Lord in great Mercy did Anſwer; for he did ſay that he was not Sick, and felt little pain, but a great weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and decay of outward ſtrength; yet ſtill was well Preſerved in a ſweet Frame of Spirit, to the great Satisfaction and Comfort of thoſe that were with him at his laſt End.</p>
            <p>Thus they are bleſſed that Die in the Lord, from henceforth they reſt from their Labours, and their Works follow them; where the voice of the oppreſſor is no more heard, the Wicked ceaſe from
<pb facs="tcp:172162:12"/>Troubling, and the weary are at Reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Rooke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <head>The TESTIMONY OF <hi>ANTHONY SHARP.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>DEar <hi>Thomas Carleton,</hi> was a True, and Sound, Meek, and Faithful Friend, that Loved the Bleſſed Truth, and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:172162:13"/>Brethren, and was ſo much in the ſelf denial, and a Lover of the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that he Preferr'd them before himſelf.</p>
            <p>And having the marks of a True Deſciple, was a good Example, and left a good Savour behind him; and I am ſatisfied he is at Reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Anthony Sharp.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group xml:lang="eng">
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:172162:13"/>
                  <p>The Captives COMPLAINT, OR THE Priſoners PLEA;
<list>
                        <item>Againſt the Burthenſom and Contentious Title of TYTHES.</item>
                        <item>With a True Relation of the Priſoners Spiritual Progreſs, and Travel towards the New and Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Together, with the ſad and grievous Sufferings he ſuſtained by a Perſecuting and Covetous High Prieſt, in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> for his Goſpel Teſtimony againſt Tythes,</item>
                        <item>Here is alſo laid down ſeveral Grounds, and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt the Propriety &amp; Payment of Tythes in this Evangelical Day, and Diſpenſation.</item>
                        <item>As alſo ſeveral <hi>Papers</hi> and <hi>Queries</hi> ſent to the Prieſt, which to this Day remains Unanſwered.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>All which is now referred to the view, judgment and underſtanding of every Conſcientious impartial Reader, of what Profeſſion ſoever; wherein the Priſoner doth recommend himſelf, his Sufferings, and the empty, groundleſs Cauſe thereof, to every Mans Conſcience in the ſight of God, as was the Practice of the Apoſtles and Saints of old in the primitive Times.</hi>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>4.2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>Re-printed in the Year, 1604</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:172162:14"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172162:14"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Captives Complaint, or the Priſoners Plea,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>FOraſmuch as it hath pleaſed the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible wiſe God (who made Heaven and Earth, and all that is therein) to create Man, and ſet him apart for his own Service, Worſhip and Glory, as the moſt competent Creature, whereby to advance his glorious, dreadful Name over all his Creatures upon the Earth, over whom He gave Man dominion; and for the better Ruling and Governing His Creatures, and Worſhipping and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying Himſelf, (the Author and Creator of all) He hath indued Man with Reaſon and Underſtanding, and infuſed into him a Principle of his own Life, and ſtamped, or ſet His own Image in him, thereby to beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie His creature Man, giving him domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, power, and liberty, over all that He had made, both the Fruits of the Earth, and every Creature moving thereon; the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172162:15"/>Fiſhes of the Sea, and the Fowls of the Air, and every Creature moving therein; ſave only of the Tree of Knowledg of Good and Evil, he was not to Eat: Now the Serpent being more ſubtil, then all the Beaſts of the field did inſinuate it ſelf into the affections of the Woman, and having got room in the weaker Veſſel, did induce both the Man and the Woman through feigned ſmooth words, (and not by direct oppoſition, mark that) into diſobedience to the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, whoſe Image they then loſt, by the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents Transformation; who raiſed the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, aſpiring, ſelf-ſeeking Principle, that deſired to be equal with God, which they ſoon received, and obeyed; thereby loſing the happy, bleſſed, and good eſtate in which he was placed, and thereby fell into the knowledg of Evil, and naked mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable eſtate with God, being Transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into the image of the Serpent, was captivated in the Curſe, and ſo came to be driven out of the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> (in which he was placed) and to be fenced out from the Tree of Life, and from the Preſence of the Lord in that State for ever.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172162:15"/>
                  <p>And becauſe the Serpent had done this, the Lord curſed it above all Cattel, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Beaſt of the Field, and put enmity between its ſeed and the Seed of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſaying, <hi>The Womans Seed ſhall break its Head, and it ſhould Bruiſe his Heel;</hi> ſo the Enmity being placed between the Seeds, the warfare was begun, which ever ſince hath continued through the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Mankind; and hence the ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving between the Twins in the Womb comes to be known; and the Elected and Reprobated Seed is known; and the Seed of the Bond woman, and the Seed of the Free-woman is known; and the Fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Birth perſecuting that which is born of the Spirit is known; and the Promiſe of the Lord to the Seed of the Woman is known and fulfilled in thoſe that witneſs the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> the Lord from Heaven to be come; and the Seed of the Covenant is known to ſuch, in which all the Nations of the Earth is bleſſed; and bleſſed and happy are they that are apprehended, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes in this Seed, for they ſhall again come to eat of the Tree of Life, that is in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172162:16"/>their names ſhall be written in the Book of the Life of the Lamb, from henceforth and for ever.</p>
                  <p>It being my aim and intent at this time to preſent unto publick view, and to the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted Light, and Judgment of all pious and ſober Men, not only my diſcent, ſtate and condition from my Childhood, but rather my eſtate and condition in Spirit, in all the gentle leadings, drawing, and carryings on of my Soul, by the Lord, from the day of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the tender Mercy and Love of God, (by his light diſpenſed and made known in me) unto this preſent day of my Sufferings for his Name and Goſpel; and alſo to give a Relation of the ground and cauſe of my S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fferings, the Perſon by whom and the manner how, with a breviate of my Teſtimony, and Judgment in the matters of this Treatiſe, in as much brevity as poſſible, whereby to clear my Conſcience (and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the witneſs in others) in the ſight of God.</p>
                  <p>AS for my diſcent (to ſpeak after the manner of Men) I ſprang of mean (though honeſt) Parents according to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172162:16"/>Fleſh, my Father being a Husbandman in the County of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> I (according to his pleaſure) was educated ſometimes at School, ſometime with Herding, and tending of Sheep, or Cattel, ſometime with the Plow, Cart or Threſhing Inſtrument, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lawfull Labours, according to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of that part of the County in which I lived; yet ſuch was the love and tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Lord, (who always had reſpect unto the meek and lowly in heart, and dwells with the the contrite and humble in Spirit, and ſhews kindneſs and mercy to them of low degree) that he was pleaſed to viſit me with his everlaſting Love, which often preſented unto me my ſtate and manner of Life, and by the ſame Love and Light he made known unto me, that his Way and Worſhip was a purer, holier Way, and cleaner Life, then yet I had attained unto, and withall gave me to ſee the evils, and miſerable effects of that ſtate and condition in which I lived according to the Faſhions, Cuſtoms, Ways and Worſhips of the formal World, which ſecret drawings I felt time after time as a ſmall ſtill Voice inwardly calling for Righteouſneſs, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of Life, and as it were, ſaying, <hi>This is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172162:17"/>the Way, walk in it,</hi> Read your own States, for thus I was induced to ſeek after the Lord, and to make further enq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iry into the Way of God; (out of which I perceived my ſelf) and then not knowing where the Lord was to be found, nor that it was he that ſtirred, and drew by his Love in me; I gave my ſelf to Reading and ſearching of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which was then Preached (by the Man made Miniſters, and alſo generally believed by the People they taught) to be the Word of God, and the alon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> way to the Kingdom, and to the knowledge of God, his Way, and Worſhip; and believing their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, I did with much diligence and zeal preſs after the knowledge of the Scriptures, giving up my ſelf to Hear Sermons, learn Catechiſms, and the like, after the manner and general Practiſe Taught by the then Preachers, ſometime more Strickt then the reſt, whoſe comlineſs ſeemed to Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend the precedent Generation of Prieſts, and their way of Worſhip; yet it pleaſed the Lord not only inwardly to break my reſt in ſpirit, but alſo outwardly to afflict me with Bodily afflictions, for I was afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from my youth up, and from my Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172162:17"/>the rod of Correction was upon me inwardly and outwardly; inwardly known to my ſelf alone, and outwardly apparent to moſt, or all that knew me after the fleſh; ſome concluding I was in a Conſumption, ſome in one Diſeaſe, ſome in another; and then by the advice and will of my Father (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh) I ſought to (and proved) many Doctors and Phyſitians, for the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the health of my Body; but they (like the Prieſts) were all Phyſitians of no value, for none did remove the cauſe, nor take away the effect, which ſtill remained with me and upon me, as a motive ſpur, or whip, to drive me forward to get an intereſt in the Lord, who through the riches of his Love did ſpiritually apply my Bodily af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions for the Health and Salvation of my Soul, inwardly drawing my affections and deſires after Him, ſtill preſenting to my view, and raiſing in my unerſtanding a way more Holy, and Pure, and more agreeable to his Will, then the way I was in, drawing me from one degree of Grace to another, and from one Diſpenſation to another, according to his good Pleaſure and W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll; then I began to affect thoſe (that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172162:18"/>ſeparated from the formal Worſhips, and pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ick People) who ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emed to be a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of more reformed lives, and judgments, and of more circumſpect Converſations, and chuſed rather to ſettle and joyn with thoſe called <hi>Independants,</hi> who at that day were beautiful and glorious to that glimmering Twilight eſtate that I was in, they being then pretty tender and low; I often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged my ſelf inferiour, unworthy, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerving the Fellowſhip and Society of ſuch a People; yet ſtill I preſſed forward deſiring to attain unto that ſtate which was before me, (which by the eye of Faith I ſaw) and to apprehend that for which I was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the Love of God; yet was I often toſſed in my ſelf, like reſtleſs waves in a troubled Sea; not feeling peace nor ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility with the Lord, I often beſought the Lord in ſecret, in the brokenneſs, and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpirit, to clear my underſtanding and judgment, and make me to know his own Living Way, Truth and People; Sects and Opinions then abounding, one ſaying, this is the way, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er ſaying that is the way; one ſaying, lo, Chriſt is in this, or here; another ſaying He is in that, or there; thus
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172162:18"/>every Denomination and Judgment conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wreſting, and interpreting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to their ſundry Tenents, and forcing meanings from them to anſwer their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and to maintain every of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations as authentick Truths; in all which I was as one without Foundation, toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with every of their windy Doctrines; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll reſted with me, Man was created for Gods glory; I being ever and anon judged and condemned in my ſelf for Sin and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, for the Law was come, by which is the knowledge of Sin; and the Commandment being come, Sin revived, and I died, and having as it were wrought Death in me by that which was good, then S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n by the Commandment became exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sinful, and then was I driven to ſeek for Peace night and day, early and late, in publick and private Faſtings, or Feaſtings, or Family Devotions, whatſoever running from one Houſe to another, and from one Town to another, from one Aſſembly and Worſhip to another, even as it were from Sea to Sea, ſeeking the Word of the Lord, as <hi>Amos</hi> ſaid, <hi>Amos</hi> 8.12. in all their Sabboths, Lectures, Humiliations or Thank givings,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172162:19"/>diligently obſerving every Ordinance (ſo called) in which the Miniſter ſaid God was to be found, and all to obtain Peace with my Maker, but it, as it were, fled from me, and was not to be found amongſt them; and and then this cry was great in me, <hi>O, that I knew the Truth! Oh, that I knew the True and Living Way to the Kingdom of God! O, that I could feel that Teſtimony of Spirit which they ſo much ſpoke of, bearing witneſs with my Spirit, that I was in the Sonſhip!</hi> though I felt and knew, I was in the way ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Judgment, and had the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal tokens of a Chriſtian, as they produced from that ſpiritual progreſs and operation the Saints and Servants of God went through in Ages paſt, which was as Way-marks, ſet up by Patriarchs, the Prophets and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their Travel to <hi>Canaan,</hi> and by the Apoſtles, and Servants of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in their Spiritual Travel to the Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> through the Regeneration and New Birth.</p>
                  <p>But being as I ſaid before, often deeply humbled before the Lord, and tendred and broken in my Spirit, diſtreſſed in my Soul, afflicted in my Body, day and night
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172162:19"/>panting and breathing after the Lord, as the Hart panteth after the water Brooks, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many times deprived of my natural reſt and ſuſtenance, mine eyes preventing the night Watches, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, watering my Bed with my Tears, being almoſt overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Floods, multitudes of Afflictions compaſſing me about, Wars and Commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on every ſide, Famine and Peſtilence, and Earthquakes, fearful Sights, and great Signs appearing from Heaven, theſe were the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Sorrows, and Days of great Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; then did the ſign of the coming of the Son of Man appear in the Clouds of Heaven, with Power and great Glory, whoſe appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance was as the Lightning, that appeared from the Eaſt, and ſhined unto the Weſt; by which it pleaſed the Father to manifeſt the way of Life, and to reveal his Son in me, and by his Light that gives the Knowledge of the glory of God in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. He was pleaſed to give me a glimpſe of that heavenly Land, and of the Way to the Kingdom of God, which I ſaw to be in and through the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, which Lighteth every Man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the World, as it was then Preached
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172162:20"/>and teſtified by the Servants of the Lord, a meaſure of which I felt in my ſelf, which told me all that ever I did, ſecretly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning every work in me, with every word and action that was againſt, or contrary to the mind and will of the Father, and alſo juſtifying every good word and work that was according to his Will; Thus the Lord having opened my underſtanding, and given me in meaſure a feeling of himſelf, I was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to conclude (as the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> did) that this was the Chriſt, this was the Way, this was the Truth, as by daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience I found by the operation of the Light in my own heart, compared with the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony that the Saints and Servants of God had given in Ages paſt, and thus in the mouths of two or three Witneſſes this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony was eſtabliſhed and confirmed in me, but how to receive and give obedience I knew not, the Enemy often raiſing Doubts and Fears in me, often diſſwading me from em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing the Light, with much queſtioning whether it were the Truth yea or nay: Then as ſoon as the Seed, the Man-child appeared, the Dragon appeared alſo ready to Devour the Man-child; then the <hi>Read-Sea</hi> was as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172162:20"/>it were, before, and <hi>Pharoh</hi> and his Hoſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and fear fell on every ſide; then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared Father againſt Son, and Son againſt Father, one Nation againſt another, and ſtill the greateſt Enemies were in mine own Houſe; and then was I in great diſtreſs; then was the Dayes of great Tribulation, perceiving the Way ſtrait and narrow, being to forſake Father or Mother, Houſe or Lands, Friends and Relations, and all old ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintances, and caſt down all Crowns, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, Wiſdom, Riches, or what other Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatſoever, and deny my ſelf; and become a Fool, and a Reproach, a Scorn, a By-word, and a Hiſſing to the Men of the World, and take up the Croſs daily, and follow the Lord through great Tribulation, through the Red-Sea, through the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, yea, even through Death it ſelf; then was I ready to faint, and to ſay with them, This was a hard ſaying, who can bear it; then the Dragon caſt out Floods after the Manchild, but God prepared a place in the Wilderneſs, and the Child was preſerved; then was the warfare great between the Fleſh and the Spirit, the Law in my Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers waring againſt the Law in my Mind;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172162:21"/>doing that which I allowed not, and leaving undone that which I allowed; with my mind I ſerved the Law of God, but with my Fleſh the Law of Sin; the Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was willing to Drink that bitter Cup, but the Fleſh was weak; then when I would have done good, Evil being preſent, prevented me; then I became as one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitude of all ſuccour, comfort and ſupport, not knowing whither to fly, or how to eſcape from the dreadfull wrath of God that was then impending over me if I diſobeyed; then was I forced in the fulneſs of time, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſtand ſtill and ſee the Salvation of God, but alſo to reſign my ſelf into his Bleſſed Will and ſweetly to Drink that bitter Cup that was given me to D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k, allowing that the Will of the Lord, and not my will ſhould be done, being willing to undergo any thing, ſo the Lord be glorified, and my Soul might reſt in Peace, being that for which I had long travelled in ſpirit, having been often as it were at the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts brink, and as it were at the mouth of the Furnace, having Drunk deep of the Cup of Judgment, and of Indignation, and of the Wrath of the Lord for Sin, and for Iniquity, often travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172162:21"/>as with my Hands upon my loyns pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and crying outin my Soul, as a Woman in Travel, that longeth for the appointed hour of her Deliverance, often in that ſtate bleſſing the Lord for the Miniſtration of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, which at that Day was glorious to me, often doubting, and fearing in my ſelf leaſt the Lord ſhould ceaſe ſtriving with me, and have left me, and given me up to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate Mind, and to heardneſs of Heart, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing often ready to Diſpair of obtaining the promiſed Land, that was before me, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the many lets, impediments, obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, hazards, dangers, which like Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of oppoſition appeared as high as the top of <hi>Carmel.</hi> And thus being aſſaulted by the Enemy, reaſoning in my ſelf, I was at a point what to do; to turn back to <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Land of Darkneſs, or Houſe of Bondage again, I durſt not, knowing the Light in me, the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of fire that appeared for my Guide, and Lead<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r; led me <hi>Canaan</hi> ward, and knowing the Terrors and Judgments of the Lord, that had not only paſſed upon me, but was ſtill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending over me for ſin &amp; diſobedience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I offered not up freely, nor ſacrificed freely, nor did not for ſake all freely, but like
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172162:22"/>
                     <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> (though I had parted with much yet) would have kept a part back; and if the Lord had cut me off, as they were, I muſt have juſtified the juſtice of the Lord in my Soul and Conſcience which daily wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed againſt me, as it were ſealing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming this Teſtimony to me, and in me, that I ſhould never find Peace nor Reconſilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Lord, untill I gave obedience to the Light, and came into ſociety with the Children of Light, (<hi>viz.</hi> the People by the World called Quakers) and came to the Worſhip that ſtood in Spirit, contrary to all the Wayes, Worſhips and Services of the World, ſet up in the wills and limitations of Men, which I ſaw to be only Formal and Traditional, and no leſs then Idolatry, as they then ſtood in the Will-Worſhip, being preſcribed, and ſet forth at the Wills and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Men, and eſtabliſhed by the then preſent Powers, Government and Authority; as by the <hi>Independant Church Faith,</hi> the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Directory,</hi> the <hi>Epiſcopals Common-Prayer Book,</hi> and ſuch like, may more fully Teſtifie, none being to queſtion, or object a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any thing that was, or is believed by their ſeveral Churches and Aſſemblies, or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172162:22"/>preſcribed in their Rules or Canons, Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or Service-Books (though never ſo much diſſatisfied in Conſcience) without un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing the Cenſures, or Abjudications of their particular Societies, and Churches, ſo called: But they that are come to the Light and Liberty of the Sons of God, and to live and walk in the Spirit, and by the Spirit they know the Anointing which abideth in them, which is truth, and no lye, which Teacheth them in all things to follow the Lamb only, whitherſoever he goes, and the leadings of his Spirit, and not the formal traſh and tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional precepts of Men; and ſo they are cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from Man, and his teachings, knowing the Lord is come to Teach his People himſelf; whereof I being perſwaded in my own heart, and this Teſtimony aforeſaid ſtanding in me, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that I ſhould never know Peace with God in my Soul, untill I obeyed and followed the Light (which I daily felt ſtriving in me, and with me in my Meditations and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications with my own Heart, ſecretly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning me for my diſobedience and works of darkneſs) I was (in the fulneſs of time) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to yeild, and reſign my ſelf into the Will and Lap of the Lord, as <hi>Eſther</hi> did,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172162:23"/>either to Live or Periſh; reſolving as I ſaid before, freely to drink that Cup, which had ſo long appeared bitter, but was then made ſweet and wholſom, as the Waters of <hi>Jericho,</hi> being ſeaſoned with that power that makes every bitter thing ſweet, and hard things eaſie; then was the Arm of the Lord made bare, and ſtretched forth for my deliverance, and his ſtrength was perfected in weakneſs, being brought into ſubjection, and made willing to bear his Croſs, then his Yoke was made eaſie, and his Burden be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Light; then he that ſat in Darkneſs ſaw great Light, and he that dwelt in the Land of the ſhaddow of Death, upon him did the Light ſhine; in that Day did he cauſe the Deaf to hear, the Blind to ſee out of obſcurity, the Lame to walk, the Dumb to ſpeak, and the Tongue of the ſtammerer to ſpeak plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; even then when mine Ears hearkned to the Word that was near, in the mouth and heart, the righteouſneſs of Faith which the Apoſtle Preached, <hi>Rom.</hi> 108. Even then when I caſt away my Jewels, Ornaments, Images, &amp;c. Menſtruous cloaths, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.21, 22. and my own Righteouſneſs, Faith, and beſt Performances, which was but as fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172162:23"/>rags, in compariſon of the excellency of that Glory revealed in and through the Son of righteouſneſs which aroſe with healing in his Wings, then did he give rain unto his Seed, even the former and the latter in his Seaſon, and upon every Mountain and Hill made he Rivers and Streams to run; then was the light of the Moon as the light of the Sun, and the light of the Sun was ſevenfold, even in that Day when he bound up the breach of his Servant, and healed the ſtroke of his wounded; he opened the Priſon doors alſo, and ſet the Captive at liberty, and let the Oppreſſed go free; then he made the Lame to leap as an Heart, and the tongue of the Dumb to ſing for joy; the crooked paths did he make ſtraight, and the rough ways plain and ſmooth; he brought down the mighty from their Seats, and exalted them of low degree; then he filled the Hungry with good things, and the Rich he ſent empty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; then did joy ſpring forth as the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and gladneſs did ariſe as the Sun, even then when Peace did run down like a River, and Salvation as a mighty Stream; then was the time of refreſhing from the preſence of the Lord, even then when the Bridegroom
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172162:24"/>came out of his Chamber, and the Bride out of her Cloſet; then was the Marriage Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lamb at hand; then was the Day of joy and gladneſs, when ſorrow and ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fled away; then was the Day of mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſing, when my Maker became my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.19, 20, 23. and the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom and Biſhop of my Soul; when I was betrothed unto the Lord, then was the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee</hi> known, <hi>John</hi> 2. which was the only Marriage Chriſt and his Diſciples were called to, where all the Water in the Veſſels was turned into Wine, which maketh glad the heart of Man, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth the Living, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.15. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.19. ſuch did <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old Drink in the Land of Promiſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.14. here was the firſt, and beginning of Miracles that Jeſus wrought, ſhewing forth his Glory; it was here alſo he Healed the Rulers Son which was ready to Die, his ſecond Miracle wrought in <hi>Galilee, John</hi> 4.50, 54. here alſo was his firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance to his Diſciples after he was riſen from the Grave, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.7.10.16, 17. here alſo was his firſt appearance, and working of Wonders in me, and to me, which when I ſaw I believed, as his Diſciples and the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172162:24"/>
                     <hi>Galileans</hi> did, <hi>John</hi> 2.11. and 4.45. then he whipped out the Buyers and Sellers out of the Temple, and overthrew the Tables of the Money-changers; then I knew the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of the Lord, was with Men, and that he was come to Teach his People Himſelf, and great was the Peace of His Children, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>chap.</hi> 54.13. then did I witneſs the Covenant changed, the Law changed, the Prieſthood changed, the Offerings, Oblations, Sacrifices and Ordinances changed, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and the Worſhip changed, and all the Shadows, Types, and Figures aboliſhed, which was but a Shadow of good Things to come, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.1. and the Tabernacle and Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary changed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.20. and the Vail removed, and the New and Living Way to be Revealed (which he hath prepared for us) through the Vail, that is to ſay his Fleſh; for even to this Day, while <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Old-Teſtament and the Law is read, the ſame Vail remains over, and untaken away, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.14, 15. as is evident, and clearly ſeen to he the very State and Condition of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and People of <hi>England,</hi> to whom the Way of Life (of Regeneration of Light, of Righteouſneſs, of Peace, of having
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172162:25"/>their Hearts ſprinkled from an evil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and of witneſſing Redemption and Remiſſion of ſins) is hid, and to them the covering is not yet taken away; for the Vail is over their Hearts, and what they ſee and know of God is but by the ſeeing or hearing of the outward Eye or Ear, as <hi>Job</hi> ſaid, <hi>chap.</hi> 42.5. knowing nothing but what they know Naturally, in a literal hiſtorical, notional, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Senſe, and in theſe Things they foyl and corrupt themſelves, never owning or obeying the Light that leads out of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Diſcovers all the works thereof, which makes all things manifeſt, and gives the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt (which till then is Vailed) through which we draw nigh unto God, and makes bold to enter into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Sanctuary, even the holy Place, being pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified through his Blood, having our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences purged from dead works, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.14. which is not yet made manifeſt, where the Tabernacle is ſtanding, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.8. neither do they know the Power which through his death hath rent the Vail; but we that are come to believe in the Light, and to witneſs the New Covenant which God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172162:25"/>to his People, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31.23, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.27. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.8.10, &amp;c. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.16, 17. they whoſe Hearts are turned to the Lord know the Vail taken away, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his promiſe, 2 <hi>Cor,</hi> 3.16, 17, 18. and we all with open face behold the glory of the Lord, and are changed into the ſame Image from glory to glory, as by the Spirit of the Lord; now the Lord is that Spirit, and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is Liberty. Now being born of the ſame Seed, and not another, and regenerated by the ſame Life and Power, and becauſe we have the ſame Spirit of Faith which the Apoſtles and Servants of the Lord had, as it is written, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 116.10. <hi>I believed, therefore have I ſpoken,</hi> we alſo have Believed, and therefore ſpeak; now <hi>we have this Treaſure in earthen Veſſels, that the Excellency of the Power may be of God, and not of us,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.7. and having this hope and truſt we uſe great boldneſs and plainneſs of ſpeech, and are not aſhamed of that worthy Name, by which we have been called, nor of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, <hi>for it is the Power of God unto all thoſe that Believe;</hi> and this Myſtery (viz. <hi>Chriſt in us the hope of Glory,</hi> Col. 1.26, 27) hid
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172162:26"/>from Ages and Generations) hath he open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and revealed in us, bleſſed, honored and glorified by the ſweet and precious Name and Love of our God for ever, that hath opened the myſteries of his Kingdom, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed them unto Babes, Sucklings, and to the little and lowly in Spirit, and yet hath hid them from the Wiſe and Prudent of the Earth, this is the Lords doing, and is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous in our Eyes, bleſſed, yea everlaſtingly bleſſed be his holy Living, eternal Name, Love, Life and Power, who alone is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all Glory, Rule, and Dominion for evermore.</p>
                  <p>And having this Teſtimony, and for this Teſtimonies ſake, and for our love and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs thereunto, we ſuffer, and are brought into bonds by the chief Prieſts and Rulers of this Generation; for as it was in the Apoſtles dayes, ſo it is now, <hi>They that will live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus muſt ſuffer perſecution;</hi> and as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>In the World you ſhall have tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but in me you ſhall have Peace; and if you love Me the world will hate you; and even ſo perſecuted they the Prophets that went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us:</hi> this perſecuting ſpirit (getting a place and room in the Woman, as I ſaid before)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172162:26"/>broke forth in <hi>Cain,</hi> the third Perſon in the Earth, and he ſlew <hi>Abel</hi> his only Brother, and here the Enmity between the Seeds appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (which I mentioned in the beginning) and this envious Perſecuting ſpirit hath had a place and deſcent through all the Generations of Man-kind to this very Day, as the Scriptures are full, how they that ſerved and feared the Lord did ſuffer Perſecutions, Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Tribulations, Reproaches, ſpoiling of Goods, Buffettings, Impriſonments, yea, even to the Death, and all for following the Lord in the Regeneration, and for ſerving and obeying Him in heart and ſpirit, and for departing and ſeparating themſelves from the Ways, Worſhips, Cuſtoms, Traditions, and beggerly rudiments of the World; and as they perſecuted the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt that went before us, even ſo do they perſecute us, and yet they will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs they know God, but their Works deny Him; for I was no ſooner turned from Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Light; nor from Satans Power to God; nor from ſin to righteouſneſs; nor from the luſts and pleaſures of the Fleſh to ſerve the Living God; nor no ſooner come to deny my ſelf, and take up the Croſs of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172162:27"/>Chriſt, and follow him, through Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Reproachings, Revilings, Mockings, Faſtings, Temptings, or what other Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſoever, or through Death it ſelf unto Life; yea, no ſooner I ſay was I given up to follow him, but perſecution aroſe for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ſake, notwithſtanding my long Travel and Pilgrimage in the Wilderneſs, (neither conſidering the Faintings, the Hungrings, the Thirſtings, the Jeopardies, Perils, the many deſperate Dangers, the dark Diſconſolate days, the long and weariſom Nights my poor Soul ſuſtained, with many a ſigh and heavy groan; with many a dolefull lamentation, with much brokenneſs of Heart, and contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Spirit when Rivers as it were run down from mine Eyes, when my Heart failed me for fear in the day of my ſpiritual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, from <hi>Egyt</hi> to <hi>Canaan</hi>) I ſay never conſidering the afflictions I bad gone through the enmity in Gods enemies without aroſe againſt me, to repoach, revile, and perſecute me, and (as I ſaid before, having withdrawn and ſeparated my ſelf from them, with their Way and Worſhip) I was hated, envied and threatned by them, but eſpecially by one of <hi>Englands</hi> chief Prieſts, named <hi>Lewis Weſt,</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:172162:27"/>a Man whoſe Life and Gonverſation doth more fully declare him to all that knows him; part whereof I may ſet down in this following Treatiſe, and ſhall leave it to the view, judgment and conſideration of all ſober juditious Men, that knows any thing of the Way and Worſhip of God; but eſpecially to thoſe my Neighbours and Country-men that hath known both him and me according to the fleſh; (though he be a Man in eſteem, honour and repute amongſt Men, and the Children of this World, and hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to his ſeveral Titles and degrees of Honour and Preferment, being reckoned one of their chief and learnedſt orthodox Divines; being (as his Wife once ſaid to me) contemning me as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udatious, and for my puerility and illiteratneſs, far inferior to argue, or diſpute matters of Conſcience with him) brought up at his Book and School from his Child-hood; and I being but a Child, as ſhe ſaid, and indeed ſprung of mean Parentage and low Degree, according to the fleſh; and in my minority Educated a little at School but the moſt part about Husbandry, Tilling, or Hearding, or the like, bring an inferiour weak Child in compariſon of Thouſands;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172162:28"/>but what I now am is by the Grace and ſweet Love of God, for which I have cauſe to bleſs and magnifie his Name for ever) and let ſuch I ſay as hath known both him and me, and not only ſuch, but all that have any feeling or ſenſe of the Way and Work of God judge of us, and between us, in every thing, either before or hereafter inſerted or recited; being for my own part, (according to the principle of Light and Truth I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs) willing to recommend my ſelf to every Mans Conſcience in the ſight of God, and alſo to give a reaſon to any Man that ſhall in Truth and Soberneſs, demand a reaſon of me of the Faith and Hope that is in me (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the manifeſtation of the Grace of God received.)</p>
                  <p>Now I ſay, the ſaid <hi>L. W.</hi> was no ſooner ſetled in his place, and I ſet to follow the Lord, but he began to menace and threaten me, together with other Profeſſors, to bring us under Conformity; and by and by ſhewed his auſterity, by which he made many Profeſſors (and others inclining to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation) bow and conform, who came in by degrees, and yielded Conformity at one time or other, in one thing or other,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172162:28"/>which ſtrengthened his Lordly ſpirit in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity, (who ſhould have been Miniſter and Servant to all) thereupon perſwading him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that a little more rigor, a little more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity, one twiſt more i'th rod, one cord more i'th whip would ſubject all his Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and make them Conform; ſometimes he would have drawn me with ſoft words, pretending great kindneſs to me, or any of my Mothers Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for our Parents ſake, the ſmalneſs wherof may appear by and by; for he having no occaſion at all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, ſave touching the Law of my God, (being that which was matter of Conſcience and weight to me) yet it ſeems occaſion muſt be had, and ſmall ones muſt be taken where great ones are not; and therefore he took it againſt me, becauſe for Conſcience ſake, I could not pay him Tythes.</p>
                  <p>A thing never challenged nor paid (for ought I know) by any Goſpel Miniſter, nor any other under a Goſpel Diſpenſation, what ever any Man may pretend; ſo <hi>he that flattereth, and ſmootheth deceitfully, crying Peace, Peace to the Wicked,</hi> becauſe I cannot now run with them to their exceſs, nor cannot return to their vomi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> again, but
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172162:29"/>eſpecially becauſe I could not <hi>put into his mouth,</hi> as <hi>Micah</hi> ſaid, <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.5. <hi>he now forthwith prepares open War againſt me;</hi> and thus he begins for my firſt years denyal of Tythes to him, he preſents me to the Jury, at a Temporal Court, held at his own Houſe in the manner of little <hi>Salkeld</hi> by the Dean and Chapter (ſo called) of <hi>Carlile,</hi> he himſelf being one of the Lords of the Court; ſo being called by the Jury, I told them that for Conſcience ſake I could pay him none, often ſaying to them that that Court had nothing to do to determine matters of that nature, the Eccleſiaſtical Courts being provided for that purpoſe, unto whom ſuch things more properly belonged, yet the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors ſlighted me and ſaid I was a fool, it was better for me to have them determined there, &amp;c. So being willing to do the Prieſt a pleaſure, they proceeded to caſt it for him, and gave a Precept againſt me of One pound one ſhilling, or there abouts, for which the Prebends Bailiffs took a Cow from me wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h Three pound three ſhillings, or upwards, I having but one other; the Prieſt called me to him, required me to pay him, I ſaid no, I could pay him none; then he beckned
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172162:29"/>to one of his Fellows another Prebend, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then preſent, to reaſon and expoſtulate with me, endeavouring to perſwade me to pay him, and in our diſpute he pleaded the Civil Law; a third Prieſt ſtanding by, by way of Interlocution, Promptingly ſaid to the Ear of the other, <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> Sir, <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> to whom I anſwered, either of you prove Tythes <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> here before all this People, and I will pay them, which thing they ſtayed not to do; for immediately the aforeſaid <hi>L. W.</hi> taking one of them by the arm, drew them away, and they all three went to an Alehouse, leaving me to the Court, with whom I reaſoned a while, clearing my Conſcience, (which I valued more worth then a Cow) and then left them: The Jury meeting at other times, I ſtill warned them not to meddle with it, being it apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to another Court; nevertheleſs they proceeded as above; but mark what befel about the very time the Jury delivered in their Verdict, the Fore-man had a Barn burned by a ſudden hand from the Lord, as was believed, amounting to a conſiderable dammage; which thing I often pondered in my ſpirit, though few looked on it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172162:30"/>then a common accident. This being done, from that time forward he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to take my Tythes in kind, as they fell due, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> his Collectors taking Hay and Corn at their pleaſure, ſometime going in at the wrong end of the Dale, contrary to the order of Tything, ſo taking the beſt of the Grain; other ſometimes taking three or four Stooks, or a Cart load together off at one end; and if I carried away any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tythed, they were ſure to pleaſe themſelves in the next Dale of mine where they came: Thus they continued, not ſhaming to bear and dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g away by force what they could ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend; [mark] even as the Prieſts (<hi>viz. Eli</hi>'s Sons) and their Servants did in <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, who were Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> and with their fleſh-hooks dragged out of the Pan, Pot, or Caldron either boyled or raw; and if any denied to give them, they took it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by force, read 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. from verſe 12 to 17. but mark their end, for the Lord was grieved with them, and ſaid, <hi>he would cut them off that there ſhould not be an old Man left in</hi> El's <hi>houſe,</hi> and verſe the 35, 36. <hi>I will raiſe up a Prieſt ſaith the Lord, that ſhall do according to all that is in mine heart; and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172162:30"/>it ſhall come to paſs that every one that is left in thine houſe</hi> (ſpeaking to <hi>Eli) ſhall come crouching to him for pieces of Silver, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of Bread:</hi> Mark the end of theſe Prieſts (Sons of <hi>Belial</hi>) who ſerved themſelves with the fat, and kept Servants as vile as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, who violently pulled and reaved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by force from the People, even as the tything polluted Prieſts and their Servants doth now in our days; are they not pulling, rending and reaving throughout this Nation of <hi>England,</hi> ſo barbarouſly and inhumanely, that they have made their name to ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k, and they are become contemptible and baſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all People, read <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. to verſe 9 and will not their end be like thoſe Sons of <hi>Belial:</hi> and alſo what becomes of the Poſterity of many of the Prieſts that are gone? are they not already in many p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ces crouching for pieces of ſilver, and morſels of bread, yea, even to ſuch as their Fathers perſecuted? ſearch and ſee if it be not ſo. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed; this not anſwering his deſire and end, more miſchief reſting in his heart againſt me, he cited me to the Biſhops Court but for what I know little, ſave that he himſelf ſaid, for all manner of Tythes ſince he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:172162:31"/>Incumbent in that place, (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what was done as aforeſaid) his Libel I never got, they commonly being Scrools of Lyes; ſo the Court proceeded to Excomunication, whereupon he procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Writ, called <hi>Excommunicate Capiendo,</hi> and thereby caſt me into Priſon about the latter end of the ſeventh Month 1663. where I have continued theſe four years, during all which time he never did ſo much as give me a viſit in my Priſon-houſe, nor never laboured to convince me, or regain me either by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, information or inſtruction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as is provided and enjoyed in the Articles to be enquired of in their Viſitation; read Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle the 10th, concerning Miniſters duty to Popiſh Recuſants, and other Sectaries; nay, he would never ſo much as allow me a fair ſober Diſcourſe to reaſon the caſe or matter in difference; but when I have met with him, (having ſometime gone to his houſe) is ſoon as ever my judgment differed from his, or that I either oppoſed, or queſtioned any thing he ſaid, or held out, forth-with he broke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to paſſion and fury, ſometime buffetting me with his fiſt, (as he hath often done both to his own hearers and others) other
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:172162:31"/>times calling me rogue and raſcal, with ſuch like vilifying tearms, in great fury Threatening he would humble me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſtill all this not anſwering his ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirit, and covetous ends, he yet devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth more miſchief, and preſently he caſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to compaſs my little parcel of Land, (as <hi>Ahab</hi> did <hi>Naboth</hi>'s) yea, worſe then <hi>Ahab,</hi> for he never profered me the rate in money, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.1, 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I read <hi>Ahab</hi> being ſad and dejected becauſe of <hi>Naboth's</hi> anſwer, <hi>Jezebel</hi> his Wife could ſoon cure that malady ſaying to <hi>Ahab, what, art not thou King? Ariſe and be merry, and Ile give thee the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard;</hi> ſo he ſoon deviſed a way to kill and take poſſeſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And indeed whether <hi>L. W</hi>'s Wife hath not been a deviſer and abetter againſt me, it is queſtioned by ſome, but I leave it to the Lord and themſelves: and he goes on in Law untill the Sheriff returned I could not be found; (although I was in his Cuſtody, and that the Prieſt <hi>L. W.</hi> knew well enough) upon which falſe return a Writ of Outlawry came forth againſt me, and then they knew where to find me; for thereupon
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:172162:32"/>the Sheriff's Clark gave another Mittimus to the Goaler for me. And untill that time I never had the leaſt notice neither from him, or any one of the Kings Officers (ſave only that his Wife did once ſay I laid for contempt, and that her Husband would take another courſe for his Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and the Jayler keeping me more ſtrict then my Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, I required a reaſon of him, he ſaid he had received another Mittimus for me; I asked him for what cauſe, he ſaid he knew not but it was at <hi>L W</hi>'s. Suit; I deſired a ſight of it if he pleaſed, he ſaid yes, if I would give him thirty pence; I ſaid, it were but reaſonable that I knew upon what account I was ſo dealt with; but no account could I have untill I bought a Coppy thereof of the Sheriffs Clark, yet being (as a Child) very ignorant in matters of Law, (having never been concerned in matters of Law, nor never had occaſion at any Court with any perſon whatſoever, ſave this with him) I let it go on in ſingleneſs of heart, reſolving to leave the iſſue to the Lord, knowing he was all-ſufficient, and chuſing rather patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſuffer, then to involve my ſelf into ſuch dubious unſeen troubles, and vaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:172162:32"/>as of the Law doth produce, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially being ſo uncapable of things of that nature; and thus it continued in ſuſpence (I ſtill waiting to ſee the effect) untill about a year after he ſtirred again, and ſought through ſmooth words ſubtilly to have enticed ſome of my Relations, to have given him a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition for me, telling them one while Ten pounds, another while Twelve or Sixteen pounds would do it, pretending to ſhew them all the favour imaginable, if they would do any thing; and when his blandilocutions could not prevail, then he ſought to terrifie them with threats, ſaying, he had a Writ ready, and the Sheriff would come and take poſſeſſion, and all I had would be Confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> alſo the People and Neighbours adjacent, with great exclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on preſſing them to compound; ſaying it was pitty it ſhould be forfeit, which put them to a point, not knowing what to do, ſome of them gave me an account once and again with tears, and great grief and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I (as often before) deſired, and alſo diſcharged them not to meddle in it; it was my own, and I knew not that it could go for a better Teſtimony; I had nothing but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172162:33"/>what I had received of the Lord, the loſs was like to be ſolely mine; ſo let him and me alone, for what he could inflict I was to bear, and that he could go no further then the Lord permitted, and what he intended for evil the Lord turned to good, and I hoped to be preſerved and provided for; upon which they were diſſwaded, and would not be induced by him: So by the aforeſaid Writ he called a Jury, and by compulſions ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned my Brother, and others that farmed my Land, to give an eſtimate of the Annual value of it, and alſo what Goods and Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels I was poſſeſſed of about two years before (<hi>viz.</hi> the time when he began that Suit) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to make all Confiſcate from that day forward; ſo the Jurors gave in their Survey at Six pound <hi>per annum,</hi> &amp;c. in the year 1666 Then after he had done all this, what through the Exclamation of my Relations and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, for the ſatisfying of them, and what through the advice of others my Friends) I procured a Reverſal, reſolving to joyn Suit, and try with him; (and never more I did, neither to this day, nor before, in matters of Law proceedings in my own defence) and how the Lord prevented or confounded
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:172162:33"/>him in his proceeding I know not, but to this day his expectation hath periſhed, and it is between three or four years ſince he begun; and indeed I can truly ſay, it was freely offered, and not it only, but Liberty and Life alſo (if it had been required) into the Will of the Lord, feeling and enjoying his Peace and Preſence I am ſatisfied, and can ſay, it is enough, and in the uprightneſs of my Heart, I deſire I may honour him with life, liberty and ſubſtance while this Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of clay is undemoliſhed, for he alone is worthy of all Glory and Thanksgiving from me for evermore; <hi>For he brings to nought the underſtanding of the Prudent, and turns the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Wiſe men backward, and confounds, the Wiſeſt</hi> Ahithophels, <hi>ſo that their vain hope periſheth, and their Expectation is cut off.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now all this he hath wickedly done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and that for no juſt cauſe as in the ſight of the Lord, nor no cauſe pretended, ſave ſome ſmall Tythes, as Hens, Eaſter-Reckonings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which was no doubt very inconſiderate in compariſon of what he hath done; for I have been much perſwaded that when he begun with me, he could no
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:172162:34"/>way reckon Five ſhillings, for his Collectors took in kind that which was moſt material, as Corn and Hay, as I have before related; and for Wooll, and Lamb, I had none, and for other Goods I had but a few; it may be a Cow or two, but ſeldom, if ever three, which things could amount to no great value, ſuppoſe it were for two or three years; an account whereof I have often required of him, I have alſo written to him for an account; alſo my Relations have deſired an account of him, but to this day none could I have from him; alſo I have written to him, that we might fairly and ſoberly Diſcourſe of the Title of Tythes profering if I were convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that they were Lawfull, to pay them without all that to do, and withall warned him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ceaſe from his wicked proceedings, being perſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ded they ſhould not go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed by the Lord; a true Tranſcription whereof hereafter follows, as they were ſent him in ſeveral Papers, at ſeveral times, which I have inſerted for the Readers better ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <p>
                           <hi>LEwis.</hi> I am informed there is a deſign in thy Heart to deprive me of mine
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:172162:34"/>inheritance left me by my Father, Is this the fruit of thy Miniſtry? and in this doſt thou do as thou wouldſt be don unto? Hath Satan filled thine heart, and rooted Covetouſneſs ſo deep in thee? Take heed to thy ways, ſearch and ſee what ſpirit thou art of, and what ſpirit it is that ſuggeſteth this in thee: enter into conſideration with thy ſelf, and commune with thy own heart, whether thou wouldſt be done unto ſo, yea, or nay; or whether it be thy place to covet thy Neighbours Goods, or Inheritance? me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks thou ſhouldſt not be ignorant what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of that Woman <hi>Jeſabel,</hi> for coveting <hi>Naboth's</hi> Vinyard, and what the reward of Covetuouſneſs is, the Scriptures are full; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the words of the Wiſe Man, that ſaid, <hi>lay not in wait. O wicked Man, againſt the dwelling of the Righteous, ſpoil not his reſting place; enter not into the Fields of the Fatherleſs</hi> &amp;c. and whatſoever is written, is written for our Learning; thou haſt often repeated that Command that ſaith <hi>Covet not thy Neighbours Goods, nor any thing that is thy Neighbours;</hi> and is thy heart now going af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy Covetouſneſs? Weigh theſe things with thy practiſe; Why ſhouldſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:172162:35"/>thy own Soul? thou that holdeſt Scripture for thy Rule, will it juſtifie thee in this thing? Or where haſt thou any ſuch Rule in it amongſt all the Converſations of the Saints? And do not think but thou muſt be brought before the Tribunal of God, there to give an account of all thy deeds done in thy Body, and there thy perſon will have no more reſpect then mine, (though now it may) all thy Pomp, thy Dignity and Riches will ſtand thee in no ſtead, neither juſtifie thee in his ſight, who hath ſaid, <hi>The wicked ſhall not go unpuniſhed;</hi> thou haſt deprived me of my juſt Liberty already, and if that cannot content or ſatisfie thee, ſurely no more will mine Eſtate; for the more thou obeyeſt that envious and covetous ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the more it will draw thee on, untill thy Soul be ſhut up in the Grave, out of which there is no redemption. So I deſire thee, have reſpect to thy Souls everlaſting health, for theſe, and ſuch like as thou art often found in, are not the fruits of a Goſpel Miniſter, for Chriſt and his Apoſtles never taught any ſuch Doctrine; and truly, whilſt thou art of this ſpirit and converſation, thy Miniſtry will not profit to wards God, nor thou canſt never
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:172162:35"/>turn many unto Righteouſneſs (its true, thou mayſt make ſome Proſelytes, but I think few Converts) it appears thou came not to ſeek nor gather us but ours, ſo that thy end is thy own, and therefore accurſed; ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thou repent thou ſhalt certainly bear the indignation of the Almighty, for little or nothing haſt thou Miniſtred unto me either in Doctrine or Practice but that which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of Death, and ſuch Miniſtration de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves no maintenance: So I deſire thee, as one that reſpects thy Souls everlaſting welfare, and in love thereunto I ſend this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, and not in any reſpect to my own intereſt, as the Lord whom I ſerve knoweth, in whoſe preſence I am, but that thou mayſt ceaſe to bring ſo deep guilt and weight upon thy Soul, but rather repent of thy wicked purpoſes, and ſeek unto the Lord,, if perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture the thoughts of thine heart may be forgiven thee; for according to outward appearance one would think thine Eſtate were ſufficient to ſatisfie thee, that thou ſhouldeſt not reap where thou ſowedſt not and covet my penny that haſt ſo many pounds; remember the Parable of <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>David.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:172162:36"/>
                        <p>But thou may object and ſay, there is a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, thou haſt a proper right and due unto it; To this I anſwer, (as I have formerly done) if thou or any of thy Function will appoint the time and place where I, or ſome other of my Companions in bonds may meet with you, and according to Scripture, ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and the Spirit of Truth, convince me or us that ſuch things is juſt and due, and properly belong to your Miniſtration, or that Chriſt and his Apoſtles did ordain conſtitute or allow any ſuch Miniſtry or Maintenance after he had offered himſelf a perfect Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, having thereby aboliſhed all Types, and the Law that made nothing perfect: I ſay, if thou, or any of you can, or will convince me or us of the lawfulneſs of paying Tythes, we ſhould neither ſuffer Impriſonment, loſs of Eſtate or Goods, nor the Execution of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Law to paſs upon us for denyal of Tythes, but rather pay them as conſcientiouſly as any one whatſoever: And this were but the place and duty of your Function, and indeed if it were not matter of conſcience to me, I could not have ſuffered ſuch detriment, loſs and impriſonment in the patience and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent as I have done by thee, and I am yet
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:172162:36"/>reſolved to ſuffer more before I offend Gods Witneſs in my Conſcience.</p>
                        <p>And further I demand of thee what the ſum or value is that thou claimeſt of me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reckoned up together, for I have been deprived of my juſt Liberty a full year and upwards, which is a penalty beyond my of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, or any pretence of offence that thou haſt ſhewed me; So that I think thou need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not a proceeded to have damnified me any further: So ſeeing thou yet intendeſt to add weight and oppreſſion to the afflicted and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, little enough, if thou give me a true account of my ſuppoſed tranſgreſſion, which I expect thou wilt forthwith do by this Bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, either in word or writing, without any further deferring; for ſure thou haſt not gone about to impoſe all this upon me that thou haſt done, and yet intends to do by adding affliction to my bonds, but thou canſt and will give a reaſon in every particular where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; which I expect of thee without any further evaſion, or otherwiſe I may conclude thou canſt not: So that I ſay again in tender love to thy Souls eternal Peace, do I deſire thee to ponder well theſe things,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:172162:37"/>and receive the Advice of thy Friend here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for I know there is a Witneſs in thy Conſcience that will receive me, from which thou canſt not flee, nor hide thy ſelf Day nor Night, to it I appeal; and know thou, that its not that I am weary of Sufferings, or am ſo married to the World that I cannot part with it; for though the Devil may have power to Diſpoſſeſs me of an Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Inheritance, as he hath had power to caſt into Priſon; yet will I wait upon the Lord, knowing he is able to ſubdue Satan under his Feet, and thou could have had no power againſt me if it had not been given thee; ſo if thou willt not be adviſed for thy good, do what thou haſt power to do, as for me I have ſo much Faith as to Truſt in the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and Patience to endure all theſe things, knowing the Captain of my Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was made perfect through Sufferings, who will be Glorified in the Sufferings of his Saints, whom my Soul honours and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies above all: So be Exhorted and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in time, leſt this ſtand as a Witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee in the Day of the Lord's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, for this was in my heart from the Lord to warn thee of, ſo I ſhall be clear of thy Blood.</p>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:172162:37"/>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Carlile,</hi> the place of my outward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace, <date>the 14th of the 9th Month, 1664.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>By one that deſires from my heart the welfare of thee and thine, and to be found in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of love to Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Tho. Carleton.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>This ſecond I ſent to him after I was Outlawed.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>L. Weſt,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>HEar and underſtand, let thy patience ſhew forth it ſelf a little to hear, read and receive home this herein inſerted directed to thee; how long will it be ere thou ceaſe to add oppreſſion to the oppreſſed? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haſt thou Outlawed me, when in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Hadſt thou no way to accompliſh thy deſign, and obtain thy covetous deſire and end, but by Treachery and Deceit, and by ſtealing Law againſt the Innocent? Oh, how eager hath thy deſire been after the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of the Righteous, and that without
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:172162:38"/>any juſt cauſe; for which thou haſt often refuſed to give a reaſon or ſhew the cauſe! Thou knoweſt on the day of my Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I asked thee what thou couldſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, before many Witneſſes; alſo I writ to thee for an account, and my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations deſired an account of thee, but none yet wouldſt, (or rather couldſt) thou truly and juſtly give: Oh! be aſhamed, be aſhamed, and bluſh that ever thou ſhould profeſs a Prieſts Function, and deal ſo Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly as thou haſt done: was thy cauſe ſo evil, and thy plea ſo bad, that thou muſt ſteal Law to obtain thy greedy deſire? Is thy love (ſo much profeſſed) to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Children at an end? and is envy, wrath, and malice crept in inſtead thereof? Oh! the Heathen ſhall condemn thee for this; yea, the Earth ſhall open her mouth, and the very Beaſts of the Field, and Fouls of the Air ſhall abhor and be aſtoniſhed to hear and ſee thy proceedings herein: The Tribe of the Prieſthood will be aſhamed of thee, and all ſuch Sons of <hi>Levi;</hi> well did <hi>Jacob</hi> ſay, <hi>Inſtruments of Cruelty was in their hands;</hi> yea, I may ſay Cruelty in the higheſt degree, pride, tyranny and oppreſſion
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:172162:38"/>is their way and path; well ſpeak the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, that which is now come to paſs, yea, ſeen and felt, <hi>Micha</hi> 3.5, 11. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.18, 19, 22. and <hi>chap.</hi> 22.25, 26, &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.11. Oh, the oppreſſion of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of <hi>England,</hi> the Earth can ſcarce bear them; and among them all canſt thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a preſident for Covetouſneſs, Cruelty and Oppreſſion? ſurely thou knoweſt not what ſpirit thou art of; but thy fruits will diſcover thee by and by; if a Man ſhould tell of thy dealings to thy Function (how thou haſt beat me with the fiſt of Wickedneſs; perſecuted with all thy might; ſworn, or cauſed to ſwear, deceitfully; and how illegal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou haſt done, and that for filthy lucre ſake, to obtain the gain of oppreſſion) would they tollerate thee, and not be aſhamed? Oh, bluſh to hear of thy corrupt Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! thy own hand ſhall witneſs againſt thee, and thine own heart ſhall condemn thee for theſe things; thou haſt not only dealt Treacherouſly with me, but with the Kings Officers alſo, by cauſing them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, <hi>I could not be found,</hi> when thou hadſt me in Priſon, and they had me in Cuſtody; ſurely thy Maſter will deceive thee, and thy
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:172162:39"/>nakedneſs, treachery and deceit is, and will be laid open, and made more publick then thy Proclamation was, that I might either render my Body or be Outlawed, which thing was done in obſcurity and deceit; but I muſt be more publick and plain with thee, it may be to rip up thy skirts, that thy nakedneſs may appear, thy filth and putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, though as a chief Prieſt, yet one of the Whores Children; for the light mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts thee ſo to be, and all thy crooked deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſerpentine paths; and by the Children of Light thou art ſeen, and ſhalt be made apparent to them that is yet under the yoke of oppreſſion; thy Name ſhall rot, and the memorial of thy Seed ſhall ſtink in thy Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations to come; a Teſtimony I have to bear againſt the workers of Iniquity, and for that end the Lord hath called me forth, and brought me not only to believe, but alſo to ſuffer for his Name, which Name I have as a Rock, a Shield, and Helmet of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this day of great Tryal; and in the Strength of the Lord am I reſolved to hold forth my Teſtimony, valuing all with it as droſs and dung, and doth believe, that through it I ſhall undergo all, and be able
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:172162:39"/>to make War in Righteouſneſs and by his Power ſhall tread upon the neck of the Scorpion and Adder, and on the crown of the head of thee, and all the Oppreſſors of the Lords Seed, who at this day is made ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of your Cruelty; yea by the Power of the Living God we both do, and ſhall tread you as chaff in the Streets: So take heed how thou proceedeſt leaſt Gods witneſs in thy own heart break thy reſt; for the firſt Prieſt that impriſoned for Tythes in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> was made a ſpectacie of his wrath, and he is the ſame God to day, and can ſave; ſo take heed betime leaſt the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God fall heavy upon thee, and labour not to incur the wrath and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Almighty upon thy Soul; for thy deceit, violence, ſpoyling, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting is and will be a token of perdition, when my innocent ſuffering is and will be a token of Salvation, and that in Chriſt Jeſus. So be warned I adviſe thee once more, and repent and amend ſpeedily, leſt the plagues and arrows of the Almighty fall heavy upon thee; for this I am bold to tell thee in the Name of the Lord, that the Lords wrath is kindled againſt ſuch, which will not ceaſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:172162:40"/>nor quench till the workers of Iniquity be cut off, that have added affliction to the afflicted, and uſurpingly exerciſed lordſhip over the Heritage of God; for your treachery, deceit and folly hath and is appearing to all Men, and Gods controverſie againſt you is begun; for your end is deſtruction, whoſe God is your gain, and your belly, whoſe mind is on earthly things; yea, the Stone of your Wall, and the Beam of your Timber, the very materials of <hi>Babel's</hi> Building ſhall cry out againſt the Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and the Stone you have rejected is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Head; (<hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt Jeſus the Light) and if thy patience can read it, and apply it, ſo do, if not, how willt thou bear and anſwer the Lord when theſe things fall upon thee.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Carlile</hi> 
                              <date>the 13th of the 3d Month, 1665.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <salute>From a Sufferer for Truth and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</salute>
                           <signed>Tho. Carleton.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Theſe Queries following I propounded to him, occaſioned by ſome Diſcourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, about their Sacrament and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, which he ſeemed to charge upon me as the ſole cauſe of my impriſonment;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:172162:40"/>having the like confounded Architectors of <hi>Babel,</hi> either loſt the original cauſe, elſe find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the weakneſs and inconſideratneſs of it, was aſhamed, and ſo let it fall: For I ſaid to him that I never thought Nonconformity to their Church and Sacrament had been the cauſe, but rather Tythes, as my Mittimus ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified; he anſwered, no, no, it was it, and nothing but it, (meaning Nonconformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.)</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>L. Weſt,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>PErceiving thou blameſt me for want of Conformity to the Church Ordinances and Sacraments, as if that were the ſole cauſe of my impriſonment, and thou pretending to be a Miniſter in the Church, and to the Church, give me a full and poſitive anſwer to theſe following Queries, according to Scripture, ſound Doctrine, and the ſpirit of Truth, that ſo my judgment may be rightly informed, and if I have been erroneous and ſchiſmatical, I am willing to reform when I am thereof convinced.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. What is the qualification of a Miniſter of Chriſt; what is his Gifts and Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and how, and from whom are they obtained?</p>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:172162:41"/>
                        <p n="2">2. How is a Miniſter of Chriſt to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led &amp; ſent, what is their Ordination; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy Call, Ordination or Miniſtry be from him; to whom waſt thou ſent, and to what end; or whether there be not ſome that run unſent, and never profit the People? accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.32.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. What doſt thou Miniſter from in thy ſelf, or what doſt thou Miniſter to in the People, or wherein doth thy gift and miniſtration con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>t?</p>
                        <p n="4">4. What is the Gifts and Parts of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt, what is the gifts and parts of a Miniſter of Antichriſt, or how do they differ one from another?</p>
                        <p n="5">5. Whether is a Miniſter to be Servant to, and in the Church, or to exerciſe lordſhip over the Church and Heritage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the manner of the Gentiles is?</p>
                        <p n="6">6. Whether is covetouſneſs, pride, wrath, malice, envy, ſwearing, lying, drunkenneſs, fornication, oppreſſion, robbery, theft, idle and corrupt communication, and ſuch like, of the Spirit of Chriſt or Antichriſt?</p>
                        <p n="7">7. Whether they that do ſuch things do believe in God, and have Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, or can be either a Miniſter or Member in his
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:172162:41"/>Church and Body, having not obtained Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, Redemption, and Salvation from thoſe things?</p>
                        <p n="8">8. What is the Church of Chriſt, or how many Churches is there, whereof doth it conſit, whereon doth it ſtand, where, and by whom is the Foundation thereof laid, and how is it preſerved Holy and without Spot, or whether is it ſubject to corruption and change yea or nay?</p>
                        <p n="9">9. What are the Ordinances of the Church, what are the Precepts, Rules and Canons therein to be obſerved; and to whom doth the Rule and Government there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of belong?</p>
                        <p n="10">10. Whether doth theſe Ordinances of the Church belong unto all Men, or whether is all Men under the Rule and Government thereof, or what is the qualification of thoſe that have a right therein, and the priviledge of thoſe that are Governed thereby?</p>
                        <p n="11">11. How many Ordinances are in the Church, when and by whom are they inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to what end, and for what time?</p>
                        <p n="12">12. What is Baptiſm, who is the Baptiſer, with what, and to what are Men Babtized?</p>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:172162:42"/>
                        <p n="13">13. How many Baptiſms are there, and how do they differ one from another?</p>
                        <p n="14">14. How are they Baptized that are Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into the death of Chriſt, and are Buried with him in Baptiſm; or how is the Baptizing with Fire and the Holy Ghoſt?</p>
                        <p n="15">15. Whether doth dipping and ſprinkling in water (<hi>England</hi>'s preſent Church Form in Baptiſm) make one a Member of Chriſt, or whether is any unclean thing a Member of Chriſt, yea, or nay?</p>
                        <p n="16">16. Whether they that were Baptized, (and ingrafted as a Member in the Church) if they perform what was therein promiſed, <hi>(viz)</hi> forſake the Devil and all his works, the pomps and vanities of this wicked World, and all the ſinful Luſts of the fleſh, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith and keep Gods holy Will and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and walk in the ſame, whether they muſt not be excomunicated, and caſt out of your Church, and into Priſon, and ſuffer loſs both in body and eſtate, yea, or nay, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>John</hi> 16.2.</p>
                        <p n="17">17. What was thoſe Ordinances and Traditions that <hi>Paul</hi> forbad the <hi>Colloſſians</hi> to touch, taſte, or handle, which (though
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:172162:42"/>commanded by Men) was to periſh with uſing, which Ordinances Chriſt blotted out, and nailed to his Croſs, as being againſt ſuch as he had quickned and raiſed by his Spirit.</p>
                        <p n="18">18. What was thoſe Meats and Drinks, thoſe Holy-dayes, New-moons, and Sabboth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, which was but ſhadows of good things to come: or is not the Churches yet under thoſe Ordinances, Traditions and Shadows, and knows not the Light of the glorious Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel revealed which Chriſt commanded to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in?</p>
                        <p n="19">19. What was the Philoſophy, Traditions and Rudiments of the World which had like to have ſpoiled ſome, and which thoſe that were dead with Chriſt were not to be ſubject to; but if Pope and Turk ſhould have power to ſet up their Traditions &amp; Rudiments, would you not be ſubject, and Preach them up for Doctrine?</p>
                        <p n="20">20. What is the Sacrament of the Lords Supper which thou would have me receive; how is it diſtributed and received, or what is the qualifications of the worthy Receivers, and if I Eat and Drink the thing ſignified <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Body and Blood Spiritually, and ſo difiſt from the Sign, muſt I not be caſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:172162:43"/>out of your Church, and into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</p>
                        <p n="21">21. What is his Body of Chriſt, and what is the Blood, whether is his Body Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual or Carnal, or how is the Lords Body to be diſcerned?</p>
                        <p n="22">22. Whether is the Body one, or how many Bodies hath He, or how do they Eat and Drink his Blood that Eternal Life abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in?</p>
                        <p n="23">23. How did they eat the ſame Spiritual Meat and Drink, the ſame Spiritual Drink, which were Baptized under <hi>Moſes;</hi> for they drank of that Rock which followed them, and that Rock was Chriſt?</p>
                        <p n="24">24. What is the difference between the Cup of the Lord, and the Cup of Devils, and the Table of the Lord, and the Table of Devils?</p>
                        <p n="25">25. Whether are they worthy Receivers purified from their Sins, and ſanctified through His Blood, ſeeing His Body was broken, and His Blood ſhed for the remiſſion of ſins?</p>
                        <p n="26">26. Whether they that are yet in their Sins do not eat and drink their own condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, not diſcerning the Lords Body?</p>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:172162:43"/>
                        <p n="27">27. Who is the Head of your Church and Body, (or who is King, Prieſt and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) whether Chriſt, King, Pope, or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; or how many Heads is there?</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>12 Month, 1667.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Send thy Anſwer to me at my Priſon-houſe in</hi> Carlile.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>T. C.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </postscript>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Another ſent after, about the 4th Month, 1667.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>L. W.</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I Having all along a deſire to be edified in the True Way and Worſhip of the Living God, and an inclination from my childhood, to follow after that which is good, righteous, and unreprovable in the ſight of the Lord, and to keep my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence undefiled, and my judgment clear and uncorrupted, as the Lord God of Heaven knows, from whom nothing can be hid: and ſeeing the ground of the Controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thee and me is matters of Faith or Worſhip, and ſo matters of Conſcience to me, and ſuch as I cannot eaſily renounce, nor dare not turn from, unleſs my judgment were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:172162:44"/>perſwaded; I therefore ſent ſome Propoſitions to thee, to that effect, an anſwer whereof I expected from thee before this time which thing I thought but requiſite, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſiſtant with thy Office and Profeſſion, being that which the Miniſters of Chriſt was always ready to do, being willing to render a reaſon of their Faith and Hope to any that ſhould demand it; and alſo to exhort, inform, and inſtruct in the Doctrine and Principles of Truth, with all meekneſs, gentleneſs and long-ſuffering; which thing if thou refuſe to do, let me know upon what grounds, for I have not ſtraitned thee for time, but thou mighteſt have done it with deliberation; ſo I deſire a ſober anſwer of thee of all and every particular propounded, or elſe a reaſon why thou wilt not, and it may ſuffice for the preſent.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>T. C.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Now having as briefly as poſſible given a True and Impartial Relation of all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, ſtates and proceedings on both ſides that is of moſt importance and concernment, and the ground and cauſe of all, as things hath paſſed and been carried on between us,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:172162:44"/>plainly and honeſtly, ſo far as I know, and do remember; I ſhall leave all, both his and mine, cauſes and proceedings, with all that hath been done, to the witneſs of God in all Hearts and Conſciences, that gives a true ſenſe and underſtanding of the nature and property of every word and work; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly let the ſober, moderate and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byaſſed Reader or Hearer judge of us, and between us, and eſpecially ſuch as have known us both after the fleſh, and the Lives and Converſations of us both among them <hi>(ziz.)</hi> the Pariſhioners of <hi>Addingam,</hi> and others in the Towns and Pariſhes adjacent, amongſt whom we have lived, and with whom we have had to do, many of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing privy to the moſt part of thoſe things, and ſo may the better bear witneſs to the Truth or Falſhood of them, being (as I have ſaid elſewhere) willing to recommend my ſelf to every Mans Conſcience in the ſight of God; and as I own and acknowledge the Light for my Leader, Guide and Salvation, ſo I am willing that all my deeds ſhould be brought to the Light, and that which I do or have done that is not juſtifiable in the Light let it be condemned by Light, and I aſhamed,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:172162:45"/>and this is to do as I would be done unto; alſo theſe my Papers that I have ſent to him, they are now made publick, and ſo are no longer his and mine only, but other Mens to judge and conſider of.</p>
                  <p>In my firſt I deſire (as I would often have willingly embraced) that he, or any other of his Function and Profeſſion would give me or us a ſober moderate viſit or meeting, at their own time and place, allowing us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for perſon, that there we might diſpute the differences in Religion between them and us, in a ſober moderate ſpirit, which to us is of great price; and if in the Spirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he or they could convince us, that we are ſchiſmatical and erroneous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (as they have frequently affirmed, and preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind our backs) whether in denying of Tythes, or in any other thing whatſoever; I can ſay it for my ſelf, and believe it for many others, that if in our Conſciences we were convinced thereof, we would reform our Judgments, and pay Tythes, and ſubmit in any other thing whatſoever, as really and conſcientiouſly as any People in the Nation, without either ſuing at Courts, ſpoyling of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:172162:45"/>goods, excommunications, cominations, impriſonments, or the execution of any Law whatſoever; and if this be not very equal and reaſonable, let all ſober People judge, and whether it be not the part and place of Men profeſſing that Function, and to be Miniſters of Chriſt, and Overſeers in the Church, that Spiritual Men might War and overcome with Spiritual Weapons, and by the Armor of Light, and the Power and Demonſtration of the Spirit of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus? that as the ſaid <hi>L. W.</hi> hath oft Preached, it may be known, to whom the Lord hath given the Urim and the Thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim; but theſe they uſe but in words on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but inſtead of dealing ſo with us, they'l turn us over to a Conſiſtory, Spiritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l or Eccleſiaſtical Court, (ſo called) which, as I may truly ſay is as Carnal and Earthly a corrupt Court at this day, as any in the World I know of, and to the Secular Powers, and Civil Magiſtrate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and when we are brought before them, and anſwers to what is Charged againſt us, pleading mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Conſcience, the Doctrine of Chriſt or His Apoſtles, or the priviledge of the Church in a Goſpel Diſpenſation; then
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:172162:46"/>they cry hold your peace, we have no thing to do with that, Diſpute it with your Miniſters, you ſhall not Preach here, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And all we can get of their Miniſters is, <hi>Rogue and Raſcal, Erroneous and Schiſmatical Fellow, or Audacious Saucy youth, I'll hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you, we'll take a Courſe with ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractary Fanatick as you are ere long,</hi> &amp;c. So having the Sword by their thigh, and the Law by their ſide, thus are we preyed upon by every one of them; and if any one do plead himſelf free by their Law, then (as ſome of them hath ſaid) they know what to do, they have another ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t to catch us with, which they know will hold, and that is, tender us an Oath, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we will not ſwear like themſelves, then either fine or impriſon, or baniſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and having got us into Priſons for Tythes, or ſuch things, there they let us lie as dead Men out of mind, never owning nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding us in any thing from year to year, unleſs to envy and ſtraiten our Liberty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by ſtirring up and provoking the Goalers againſt us, who being willing to do the Prieſts and Magiſtrates a favour, hath often ſhown their ſeverity to the hazard of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:172162:46"/>lives of the Innocent in their Cuſtody, (whom they have called ſometime their ſheep) and yet preyed upon us, not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us the Liberty they allowed to Fellons and Murderers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet ſtill the Lord was with us, and wonderfully preſerved us to his praiſe, when Men roſe up againſt us to have ſwallowed us up with open mouth, bleſſed be His Name for evermore.</p>
                  <p>And alſo whether it were not requiſite that he gave me a true and particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of every of his demands and claims whatſoever, or of any other difference (if any had been) betwixt us, before he had thus far proceeded to have damnified me, having done what in him lay, to deprive me of all, ſave only my life, which I have yet for a prey? And alſo whether it had not been his place and duty, pretending to be a Teacher and Inſtructer of others<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Paſtor, or Elder in the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reputed a Learned Orthodoxical Divine? (and ſometime profeſſing himſelf my ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Father) but ſuch meaſure a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I have had from him are no ſpiritual inſtructions to me I ſay, if ſo, whether he ought not to have anſwered my Queries, and alſo my other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:172162:47"/>ſent to him; (which he never would do to this day) thereby to have informed and cleared my judgment and underſtanding, being things appertaining to Faith and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Profeſſion and Worſhip of Chriſtianity, and ſo matters of Conſcience to me, let all ſober wiſe Men judge?</p>
                  <p>Alſo I ſhall appeal unto all ſober and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Men and Women, and refer my ſelf to the witneſs of God, and the illuminated underſtanding in all, whether ever any of the Holy Men of God did ſo with any perſon in the Church, or out of the Church, Believer or Infidel, as he hath done with me, yea, or nay; or whether ever you read of any of the Apoſtles or Miniſters of Chriſt in Ages paſt, that denied to give a Reaſon of their Faith and Hope in Chriſt Jeſus; and to Inſtruct, Exhort, Inform, Teach, Reprove, Rebuke, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as he hath done? or whether you read of any Miniſters of Chriſt that ſued at Law for the maintenance of their Bellies, ſpoyled and Perſecuted, Excomuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated out of their Church into Priſon, ſought Mens Liberty, Heritage &amp; Eſtate, and yet can ſhew no fair nor juſt cauſe, as he hath done, yea, or nay? Whether ever any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:172162:47"/>of Chriſt did ſwear, lye, and beat with the fiſt of wickedneſs, as he hath done, yea, or nay? or whether ever any Miniſters of Chriſt, was ſo inclined to drunkenneſs, and to frequent Ale-houſes, that they needed to be reſtrained by a Fine, as his wife hath done with him, yea or nay? All which, (with ſeveral ſuch like deeds, which I ſhall now omit) I need not go far to prove, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own practice doth notoriouſly evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and teſtifie the ſame, ſufficiently known to many that knows both him and me and by what is before related.</p>
                  <p>Now conſidering the many Diſputes, Contentions, Strifes, ſuing at Law, ſpoiling of goods, caſting into Priſons, and the great unparalell'd ſufferings that have been occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned in this Nation in theſe late years about Tythes, and the great objections and excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations made againſt us for denying them, (about which I have a ſhare, being deeply concerned and involved therein) together, for the quietneſs and peace of my ſpirit, upon which this thing hath long reſted, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xcites me to caſt in my mite, and lay down my reaſons and grounds whereupon I have denied them, and ſuffered for the non-payment thereof?
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:172162:48"/>tho weakeſt and unfiteſt of many thouſands for ſuch a work? yet, according to what I have received, and am perſwaded of, I ſhall lay down in truth and ſimplicity; and that chiefly for the ſatisfaction of ſuch as deſire to be ſatisfied, and for the ſtopping the many objections and maledictions of others made in ſecret behind my back by ſome of my Neighbours, eſpecially the people called <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependants</hi> in that part, who moſt of any hath condemned me for ſuffering ſo much for ſuch ſmall trivial matters, as they ſay, being as it ſeems a ſmall ſcruple in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and ſuch a more as they can eaſily ſwallow now; though in the beginning riſe and growth of their Religion, their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was wholly againſt Tythes in a Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel day; yea, ſome of them preaching in great zeal againſt them, Condemning the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of them, ſaying, <hi>They were clear contrary to the maintenance of a Goſpel Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry?</hi> and yet when they ſaw that Tythes were like to be the only wages, mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and reward of their preaching; (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing generally eſtabliſhed by the Laws and Cannons of <hi>England</hi> for that end) rather then they would want that ſweet morſel,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:172162:48"/>and goodly Garment, and the Fleſhly eaſe that came thereby, and ſuffer any thing for the denying of the ſame, they could ſoon (through their Chriſtian Prudence or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy) cure that Malady; and for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter digeſtion of that Diet, make to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a ſtomach Pill, or two, to Cure that Crudity; and ſo rather Suppreſs, Extirpat, Hide or let fall one of their Principles, then either want that delightſome livelyhood, or beloved Benefice, or yet either ſuffer any thing either in Liberty or Eſtate for the holding that Principle throughout.</p>
                  <p>So for the Conſiderations aforeſaid, I ſhall endeavour to anſwer the general Objections Principly made againſt me and my Brethren in this caſe, and what I hold and believe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1ſt <hi>Objection,</hi> is, <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Returning from <hi>Chedarlaomer</hi> from Reſcuing his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew <hi>Lot, Melchiſedeck</hi> met him, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, and bleſſed the Lord in his behalf, and brought forth Bread and Wine and ſet before him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to him <hi>Abraham</hi> gave a Tenth of the ſpoyls, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.18 <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer,</hi> To this I ſay, I never find it a preſident or rule for me; ſuppoſe he gave a
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:172162:49"/>Tenth, it was a voluntary gift, he was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commanded by God, nor compelled by Man, and if he had not given, I think he had not ſinned, and that which he did give was but a Tenth of the Spoils, taken at the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and ſo no rule for me, being no Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier at any ſuch Slaughter, and ſo not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of any ſuch Spoils; ſo if it be bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to any, (as I think to none) it is to Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and not to Plowmen: and what if he in gratification of his Love) in meeting him, and ſetting Bread and Wine before him) had given him one half of the Spoils, this had been no binding Rule to Poſterity.</p>
                  <p n="2">2d. <hi>Objection,</hi> is, <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Vow when he went to <hi>Padan-aram: If God</hi> ſaid he, <hi>will be with me, and will keep me in this way that I go, and will give me Bread to eat, and Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to put on, ſo that I come again to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe in Peace; then ſhall the Lord be my God and this ſtone my Pillow, which I have ſet for a Pillar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall be Gods Houſe; and of all that thou giveſt me, I will ſurely give a Tenth unto thee,</hi> Gen. 28.20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Here <hi>Jacob</hi> being gone from his Fathers Houſe; <hi>for,</hi> its ſaid, <hi>he lighted on a certain place</hi> (it ſeems between <hi>Beerſheba</hi>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:172162:49"/>and <hi>Haran,</hi> I ſuppoſe it was either in the Fields, or Deſart) <hi>on the South ſide of</hi> Luz, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 18.13. however I ſuppoſe <hi>Jacob</hi> was in a deſolate diſconſolate condition, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.3. <hi>for,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>he took of the ſtones of the place, and laid them for his Pillow, and lay down to ſleep,</hi> Gen. 28.11. Now the Lord appeared to him, (in a Viſion) as He hath oft done to his Servants in ſuch diſconſolate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions which makes His appearance more Glorious ſaying, <hi>I am the Lord God of</hi> Abraham, <hi>and of</hi> Iſaac <hi>thy Father, the Land whereon thou lieſt, to thee will I give it, and to thy ſeed after thee; and thy ſeed ſhall be as the duſt of the Earth, and ſhall ſpread to the Eaſt, Weſt, North and South; and in thy ſeed ſhall all the Families of the Earth he bleſſed: And behold, I am with thee, and will keep thee in all places, and will bring thee again into this Land, I will not leave thee untill I have done as I have ſpoken. And he awaked, and ſaid, ſurely the Lord is in this place, and I knew it not; and he was afraid, ſaying, how dreadfull is this place, it is none other but the Houſe of God, this is the Gate of Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. [mark] the Lords appearance in an hour of great diſtreſs is very comfortable, and alſo fearfull; this
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:172162:50"/>is true fear indeed, here is fear mixed with love; here <hi>Jacob</hi> lays hold forth with upon the Love and Promiſe of the Lord, and ſaid, <hi>If the Lord will do ſo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then ſhall He be my God, and this ſtone my pillow, which I have ſet up for a pillar, ſhall be Gods Houſe, and of all that he giveth me, I will ſurely give a Tenth unto him.</hi> [mark] I ſay, <hi>Jacob</hi> being poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with fear, and overcome with love, he vows and promiſes unto the Lord again; this was a voluntary act in <hi>Jacob,</hi> he obliged himſelf to the Lord after the Lord had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to bleſs him, and he performed his promiſe; for after twenty years he purged his Houſe of Idols, and built an Altar unto the Lord at <hi>Bethel,</hi> Gen. 35.6. which he called <hi>Elbeth-el,</hi> (viz.) <hi>The God of Bethel:</hi> But who did he give his Tenth unto, or when did he give it, that is yet diſputable? but ſuppoſe it had been to the Prieſthood, (which ſome hold was annexed to the firſt-born of Families) what, will that argue for me to do ſo? <hi>Jacob</hi> vowed but for himſelf, not for his poſterity after him, and it was voluntary, (being filled with the Lords appearance in a day of diſtreſs) <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.3. and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God, neither compelled by Man,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:172162:50"/>and ſo not binding to any ſave <hi>Jacob</hi> alone; only this may be obſerved, if any one have vowed as <hi>Jacob</hi> did, let ſuch perform alſo: alſo, it was but once in <hi>Abraham,</hi> and once in <hi>Jacob,</hi> and that in caſes extraordinary; and who, or what is he that can plead for annual payment of Tythes of every of a Mans encreaſe from theſe two places; what, ſuppoſe I being in diſtreſs (as I have often been, and few of Gods Servants are exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) ſhould vow a vow unto the Lord, that if he will preſerve me this one time, or deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me from this great danger, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then will I give him one half of all that I enjoy, or have received of him; would this my vow (being performed) be binding to my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and their Children after them from Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to Generation for ever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object,</hi> 3. Now in <hi>Exodus</hi> 23.19. it is ſaid, <hi>The firſt of the Firſt-fruits of the Land thou ſhalt bring into the Houſe of the Lord thy God.</hi> This is the firſt expreſs command, but here is no certain dividual part expreſſed, only the firſt of the Firſt-fruits, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.26.</p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.10. <hi>Moſes</hi> inſtituting the Feaſt of Firſt fruits; <hi>When ye come</hi>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:172162:51"/>(ſaith he) <hi>into the Land which I will give you, ye ſhall bring a ſheaf of the Firſt-fruits of your Harveſt unto the Prieſt, and he ſhall ſhake it before the Lord,</hi> verſe 14. <hi>This ſhall be a Law for ever in your Generations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, that which is more expreſs is <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.30.32, 33. <hi>All the Tythe of the Land, both of the ſeed of the Ground, and of the Trees is the Lords; and every tythe of Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock and Sheep, and all that goeth under the rod, the Tenth ſhall be holy unto the Lord;</hi> this is a more poſitive command then any before.</p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.20. it is ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall offer a Cake of the firſt of your Dough for an Heave-offering; as the Heave-offering of the Barn ye ſhall lift it up, and give it to the Lord in your Generations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>Moſes</hi> being the Son of a <hi>Levite, Exod.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>Aaron</hi> was his Brother, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.14. the Lord bid <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeparate <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons for the Prieſts Office, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.1. and appoints him to make them holy Garments, <hi>The Ephod and the curious Girdle,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Aaron</hi> was to wear the Breaſt-plate of Judgment upon his Heart, and upon it the names of the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:172162:51"/>the Breſt-plate of Judgment, <hi>Moſes</hi> was to put the <hi>Urim</hi> and the <hi>Thummim,</hi> which he was to bear upon his Heart when he went in before the Lord, <hi>&amp;c. Exod.</hi> 28. through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
                  <p>So the Prieſthood being ſetled to <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons, as a Statute, and an Ordinance for ever, throughout their Generations, he was to take unto him his Brethren the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> the Family of his Father they were to be joyned with him, and to miniſter unto him, and were to take the Charge of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary of the Tabernacle, and of the Altar; only he and his ſons was to execute the Prieſts Office in all things, <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.2. to verſe 7. then all the Heave-offerings, and the holy things that the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> offered to the Lord, was to be <hi>Aarons</hi> and his Sons for ever, by a perpetual Covenant of Salt, as in verſe 19.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons was to have no Inheritance in the Land, neither any part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> for the Lord was their part and inheritance for ever, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.1, 2. And to the Children of <hi>Levi,</hi> the Lord gave the Tenth in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and for their ſervice in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:172162:52"/>of the Congregation, and they were to have no Inheritance among the Children of <hi>Iſrael, Numb.</hi> 18.20, 21, 23, 24. for the Tythe which the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> offered was to be the <hi>Levites</hi> Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and out of them they were to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract a Tenth, which they were to offer as an Heave-offering unto the Lord, which was to be given unto <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons, verſe, 26.28. only when they were come into the Land of <hi>Canaan, Joſhua</hi> by the appointment of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſet forth Forty eight Cities, with their Suburbs, which the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> gave of their Inheritance at the Command of the Lord, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 21.1, 2. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Then again, I read <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.28, 29. beſide the Tythe they were to bring year by year unto the Lord, at the end of every three years they were to bring forth all the Tythe of their Increaſe, and lay it up within their Gates, and thither ſhould the <hi>Levites</hi> come (becauſe they had no Inheritance among them) and the Strangers, the Fatherleſs and the Widows, and ſhould Eat and be filled, that the Lord might bleſs <hi>Iſrael</hi> in all the works of their hands, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.12, 13, &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:172162:52"/>
                  <p>Again, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.3, 4. They which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Sacrifice, whether Bullock or Sheep, <hi>ſhall give unto the Prieſts the right ſhoulder, and the two Cheeks, and the Maw; and the Firſt-fruits of the Corn, the Wine and Oyl, and the firſt of the Fleece of the ſheep,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Then again, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> when he came he ſaw the Houſe of God was forſaken, and the Portion of the <hi>Levites</hi> had not been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but every one was fled to his own Land, he reproved the Rulers, and ſet the <hi>Levites</hi> in their places, and cauſed all <hi>Judah</hi> to bring their Tythe of Corn, and Wine, and Oyl into the Treaſuries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and appointed the Wards of the Prieſts, and of the <hi>Levites</hi> every one in his Office, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.10, 11, 12, 30, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Alſo King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> appointed the Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Prieſts and Levites by their turns, every Man according to his Office; (hence it is ſaid <hi>Zacharias</hi> was of the Courſe of <hi>Abia,</hi> and executed the Prieſts Office before God as his turn came, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.5.8.) and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the People to bring in part for the Prieſts and Levites, that they might be Encouraged in the Law of the Lord; So the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> brought in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:172162:53"/>of Firſt-fruits, Corn, Wine, Oyl and Hony, and of the increaſe of the Field, and the Tythes of Bullocks, Sheep, and of the holy and conſecrated things; the Tythe of all things in abundance: yea, ſo much, as they eat and were ſatisfied, and there was many heaps laid up in ſtore; and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> commanded them to build Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and in them they laid up all their Tythe and their Firſt-fruits, and their dedicated things, and ſet Overſeers over them, to whome they committed the charg of them, who deſtributed with fidelity to their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren great and ſmall by courſe, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.2, 4, 5, 6. to verſ. 14. &amp;c. And in <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 10. they were all ſworn, and ſealed to fidelity both Prieſts and Levites, Porters, Singers, Nethinims, and all the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to keep the Law, and the Ordinances of it, and to bring in all the Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruits, the Tythe, and the dedicated things, Corn, Wine and Oyl, &amp;c. into the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and Treaſures, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Then, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſetting forth the glory of the Temple, and meaſuring it with the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring Reed, he ſhews who ſhall be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſervice of the Temple, and who
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:172162:53"/>not; he alſo divided the Land into four Portions, one for the Prieſts, one for the Levites, one for the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and one for the Princes, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 44. and chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters 45, 46. alſo he ſets forth the Offerings, of the Princes, and their Ordinances, as Meat-offerings, Drink-offerings, Burnt-offerings, Sin-offersings, Treſpaſs-offerings, and Peace-offerings, &amp;c. alſo the Sacrifices of their New-moons, their Sabbaths and ſolemn Feaſts, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Alſo <hi>Amos</hi> coming to cry againſt the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry in <hi>Jeroboam's</hi> time, and againſt the Princes and Prophets of <hi>Bethel,</hi> he calls their Princes Kine, they oppreſſed the Poor and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the needy, and multiplyed Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion in <hi>Gilgal,</hi> and ſaid, bring &amp; let us Drink, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet they would go to <hi>Bethel,</hi> and bring their Sacrifices in the Morning, and their Tythes after three years; they could offer Thankſgiving, and proclaim Free-Offerings, and this they liked then, (as the Prieſts of our Age loves Free-offerings, and give ye now) ſo they might live in their ſins, but the Lord ſwore by his Holineſs, he would take them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with Thorns, and their Poſterity with Fiſh-hooks, and he gave them cleanneſs
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:172162:54"/>of Teeth, and ſcarceneſs of Bread; He with-held the Rain in its ſeaſon, and he ſent Blaſting, and Mildew and Peſtilence, and Sword amongſt them.</p>
                  <p>Then again, the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> cries out againſt the Prieſts, how they diſpiſed the Name of the Lord; they ſaid the Table of the Lord was not to be regarded; and ſaid, it was polluted, and ſnuffed at it; when as it was they that polluted it, by offering un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Bread, the Blind, the Lame, the Torn and the Sick for Sacrifice. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Go offer it to your Princes ſaith the Lord, and ſee if they will accept it from you; you have fed your ſelves, and ſerved your ſelves, and not the Lord: For who among you,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>will ſhut a door, or kindle a fire on mine Altar for naught,</hi> verſe 10. <hi>Curſed be the Deceiver that hath in his Flock a Male, and ſacrificeth a corrupt thing.</hi> And chap. 2. <hi>O ye Prieſts</hi> (ſaith <hi>Malachi) this Commandment is for you ye have broke the Covenant of</hi> Levi, <hi>even my Covenant of Life and Peace; ye have been par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial in the Law; if you will not hear and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to give glory to my Name, I will corrupt your ſeed, and caſt dung upon you faces, and will curſe your Bleſſings,</hi> chap. 2.2.4, 5, &amp;c. <hi>for
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:172162:54"/>the Prieſts lips ſhould preſerve knowledge, and they ſhould ſeek the Law at his mouth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but ye are gone out of the way, ye have broken Covenant, and cauſed many to fall, &amp;c.</hi> And in chap. 3. he ſaith, <hi>Behold the Lord whom ye ſeek ſhall ſuddenly come to his Temple; but who may abide the day of his coming, for he ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to try and fine as ſilver; yea, he will fine and purifie the Sons of</hi> Levi: [mark] it is the Sons of <hi>Levi, that they may bring Offerings of Righteouſneſs; and he will come near (them) to Judgment, and will be a ſwift witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Adulterer, falſe ſwearer, and thoſe that keep back the Hirelings wages, that vex the Widow and the Fatherles, and oppreſs the Poor and Stranger, and fear not me ſaith the Lord; for from the days of your Fathers</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ye are gone away from mine Ordinances and have not kept them Will a Man rob God,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>yet ye have robbed me in Tyths, and Offerings, ye are curſed with a Curſe: Bring all the Tythe into the ſtore-houſe, that there may be meat in my Houſe, and prove me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; and ſee if I will not open you the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of Heaven, and pour you out a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But your words have been ſtout againſt me, ſaith the Lord; ye have ſaid,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:172162:55"/>It is in vain to ſerve God; and what profit is there in keeping his Commandments and in walking humbly before him? And therefore ye count the proud happy; and ſets up them that work wickedneſs; and thoſe that tempt God are delivered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the next place which ſome account as formidable as all the reſt is, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.42. Chriſts own words, ſaying: <hi>Wo unto you Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, ye Tythe Mint and Rue, and all manner of Herbs, and neglect and paſs over Judgment, and the love of God; theſe things ye ought to have done, and not to have left the other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done.</hi> Theſe are the main grounds (being under the Law of the firſt Covenant) upon which the Ordinations, Titles, Claims and Propriety of Tythes do, or ever did ariſe or ſpring; and upon which all the Diſputes, Acts Decrees, Laws, and Tryals at Law, Differences and Sufferings, of what kind ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, do originally ariſe and deſcend, by which the reader may obſerve the riſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Tythes, and the end thereof, and the obſervation of them from <hi>Moſes,</hi> or the <hi>Levitical</hi> Law downwards till Chriſt <hi>the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs ſake, to all them that believe,</hi> Rom. 10.4.</p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:172162:55"/>
                  <p>I ſhall now proceed to give my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whereupon I deny the Payment of Tythes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, The Reader may take notice of the Inſtitution of Tythes and by whom, Here is <hi>Moſes</hi> the Servant and Prophet of the Lord, who was faithfull in all his Houſe, and was a Witneſs through Faith of thoſe things which ſhould afterward come to paſs, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.3, 4. this was he whom the Lord chuſed and ſent into <hi>Egyt</hi> for a Prophet, Prince and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to the Children of <hi>Iſrael, Exod.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.34, 35. and having brought them to <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> the Lord ſpake unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Tell the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>You have ſeen what I did to the</hi> Egyptians, <hi>and how I carried you on Eagles Wings, and brought you to me: Now if you will hear my Voice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and keep my Covenant, then ye ſhall be my chief Treaſure above all People, though all the Earth be mine, and ye ſhall be to me a Kingdom of Prieſts, and an holy Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Then <hi>Moſes</hi> propoſed to them what the Lord had ſaid to him: and the People anſwered unanimouſly, <hi>All that the Lord hath Commanded we will do:</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> reported their words unto the Lord, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.3, 4.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:172162:56"/>
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So the Lord calling <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> only up into the Mount ſaid, <hi>I am the Lord thy God that have brought thee out of</hi> Egypt &amp;c. <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides me?</hi> and he delivered to them his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and his Law by the diſpenſation of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo he commanded them not to make unto themſelves gods of ſilver or gold, verſe 23. Then he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Moſes</hi> to make an Altar of Earth or Stone, whereon to offer the burnt-offerings and peace-offerings, &amp;c. <hi>And ſee</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that a Tool be not lifted up upon it,</hi> verſe 24.25. Then he delivered to him the Temporal or Civil Laws, <hi>Exod.</hi> chap. 21, 22, 23. &amp;c. So <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote all the Laws, and erected them an Altar under the Mount and Twelve pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, according to the Twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſent of the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> who offered Burnt-offerings, Beaves and Peace-offerings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and with half of the Blood he ſprinkled the Altar, and the reſt he put in Baſins: And he read the Laws, and all the words of the Lord to the People; who ſaid, <hi>All that the Lord hath ſaid we will do and be obedient:</hi> So <hi>Moſes</hi> ſprinkled all the People with the Blood; and ſaid, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Blood of the Covenant which the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:172162:56"/>Lord hath made with you touching all theſe things,</hi> Chap. 24. Then the Lord called <hi>Moſes</hi> up into the Mount, ſaying <hi>I will give thee Tables of Stone and a Law, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments which I have written, that thou mayſt Teach them to the People:</hi> And <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> took his Miniſter <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and went up; and <hi>Moſes</hi> was in the Mount forty Days and forty Nights; and God ſpake unto <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſpeak unto the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that they ſhould offer unto the Lord an offering of Gold, Silver, Braſs, Purple, Scarlet, and fine Linnen, Oyl and Spices, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Stones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that they ſhould make the Lord a Sanctuary, that he might dwell amongſt them; and that it ſhould be according to the expreſs Pattern ſhewed to him: and alſo that he ſhould make an Ark, in which the Teſtimonies of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant ſhould be placed; deſcribing the faſhion of the Tabernacle, and the Order, Place and Faſhion of all the appurtenances thereunto belonging; every thing was to be made, placed and erected according to the expreſs Patern ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wn to him in the Mount, chapters. 25, 26. Mark what I ſay, <hi>Moſes</hi> having read the Law, and the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:172162:57"/>Book of the Covenant in the audience of the People, they ſaid, <hi>All that the Lord hath ſaid will we do, and be obedient,</hi> chap. 24.7, 8. Then he took the Blood of the Covenant, having with the one half ſprinkled the Altar, with the other half he ſprinkled the People, and the Covenant was confirmed; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all things were by the Law purged with blood; <hi>and without ſhedding of Blood is no Remiſſion, Hebr.</hi> 9.22. [mark] here is the eſtabliſhment of the firſt Covenant, <hi>which ſtood in meats and drinks, and divers waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and carnal Ordinances, which was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed untill the time of Reformation,</hi> Hebr. 9.9, 10. [mark here again] <hi>which was but a Figure for the time then preſent, and could never make the Comers thereunto perfect, as pertaining to the Conſcience: But Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come an High Prieſt of good things to come,</hi> [mark] <hi>by a greater and more perfect Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, that is not made with hands, nor not of this building.</hi> I ſay alſo, Chriſt Jeſus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come (who was the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs ſake, to all that believe, and the Subſtance of all Shadows, Antitypes and Figures) he hath brought in a more excellent Miniſtry, being a Mediator of a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:172162:57"/>better Covenant, eſtabliſhed upon better Promiſes; wherefore, coming into the World, he ſaith, <hi>Sacrifices, Offerings and Burnt-Offerings for ſin, thou wouldeſt not,</hi> (which are offered by the Law) <hi>but a Body thou haſt prepared, (as it is written) Lo I come to do thy Will O God; by the which Will, we are ſanctified,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; [mark] <hi>He taketh away the firſt, that he might eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the Second;</hi> Now if the Firſt Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant had been faultleſs, there ſhould no place have been for the Second, but finding fault with them under the Firſt Covenant; (and why? becauſe it was not poſſible that the blood of Bulls and Goats ſhould take away ſins; for in thoſe Sacrifices there was (yea, and is) a remembrance of ſins every year; ſo that the Commers thereunto is not made perfect ſo finding fault with them, he ſaith, <hi>Behold the days come, that I will make a new Covenant with the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and with the Houſe of</hi> Judah, <hi>not according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that I made with their Fathers when I took them by the hand, and led them out of</hi> Egypt; <hi>(for becauſe they abode not in my Covenant, I regarded them not ſaith the Lord) But this is the Covenant that I will
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:172162:58"/>make with them after thoſe days, I will put my Law in their Hearts, and write it in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts; and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my People,</hi> Jer. 31.33. Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k. 37.26. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hebr. 8.8, 9, 10. and 10.16. <hi>They ſhall not need to Teach every Man his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or every Man his Brother, ſaying Know the Lord for they ſhall all know me, even from the leaſt to the greateſt of them; and their ſins and their iniquities will I remember no more:</hi> [mark] Their ſins and their iniquities will I remember no more; here ſuffer me to enlarge a little by the way: Now where Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin is, there needs no more Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for ſin; and for this end was Chriſt made manifeſt to take away all ſin, and in him was no ſin; howbeit the Children of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who are ſtrangers to the Covenant of Promiſe, being never yet come to the <hi>Light,</hi> nor to the <hi>Second Covenant,</hi> the <hi>New and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Way;</hi> they I ſay, that have not received this, they ſay there is no Redemption from under ſin; there is none ſay they, can be ſet free from iniquity while on this ſide the grave; there is not an upright Man upon the Earth ſay they, that doth good, and ſinneth not; there is none Righteous, no not one: a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:172162:58"/>ſtrange Doctrine in a Goſpel Day: this Generation uſed to bleſs the Name of the Lord for this glorious Day, and Golden Age, and time (ſaid ſome) wherein his Goſpel was ſo purely Taught and Preached; [mark this confuſion] is the Goſpel purely Taught them when they are yet in their ſins; but it may be they have not received the Goſpel in Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Purity, but in name and word only, for the <hi>Goſpel is the Power of God,</hi> Rom. 1.16. or Chriſt Jeſus <hi>the Light of the World the Power of God and the Wiſdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.24. <hi>who was manifeſted to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſin;</hi> but theſe will pretend to be Goſpel Men and Chriſtians, who ſay none can be purified from ſin, and thereby fruſtrate the end of the Lord and make void his coming, who came <hi>to ſave his People from their ſins, and he is able to ſave to the utmoſt them that come unto God by him:</hi> but may it not be ſaid, they come not unto God by him, and they enter not in at the Door, but climbs up ſome other way that holds ſin for Tearm of Life, which the Devil is Author and Lord of, then whoſe Servants are they, let wiſe Men judge; a ſmookey Tenent, a Principle of Darkneſs aſſended out of the Bottomleſs
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:172162:59"/>Pit; ſure no Chriſtians, what ere they may profeſs: What, hath Chriſt ſuffered in vain? What, hath the ſhedding of his Blood no more effect? What, is he not able per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to ſave thoſe to come unto God by him? Is he not able to ſave his People from their ſins? Is he not able to redeem from death? Is his Hand ſhortned? Or his Power weakned? Is he not the ſame he was in the Apoſtles dayes? Is not his power the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever? [mark] Was he not given for Salvation to the Ends of the Earth? Was he not ſent to redeem thoſe that were under the Law? Was he not ſent to ſave his People from their ſins? Was he not ordained a Light to lighten the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> and the Glory of the People of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael?</hi> Yea, <hi>a Light to lighten thoſe that ſit in Darkneſs and the Regions of the ſhadow of Death, and to guide their feet in the Way of Peace:</hi> Was he not manifeſted to take away our ſins? and was not his Blood ſhed for the Remiſſion of ſins? the Apoſtle ſaid, yes: and if it be not ſo that our ſins be done away, nor we not ſanctified, purified and cleanſed through his Blood, nor do not wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Remiſſion nor forgiveneſs through his
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:172162:59"/>Sufferings and Death, and our Conſciences purged from dead works, and our ſins done away in him: I ſay, if none have this benefit by him, then is our Faith vain, and we are ſtill in our ſins, and both the Apoſtles and we are found falſe Witneſſes of him, but neither they nor we are falſe Witneſſes, for we know, (and they knew before us) <hi>That Life and Salvation is manifeſted, and we have ſeen it, and that which we have ſeen and heard we do declare, that ye might have Fellowſhip with us</hi> [mark] that ye might alſo obtain Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Redemption with us. <hi>And this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is the Meſſage that we have heard of him, and received from him, and declare unto you, that God is Light, and in him is no Darkneſs at all, and if we ſay that we have fellowſhip with him, and walk in darkneſs, we lye: But if we walke in the Light, as he is in the Light, then have we fellowſhip with him, and one with another, and the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth from all Sin, &amp;c.</hi> (mark) ye Sons and Daughters of Darkneſs, that ſay none can be cleanſed from all Sin; but no marvel if Infidels ſay ſo, that never owns the Light, that never came to the Blood of Sprinkling, that never
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:172162:60"/>came to the Blood (the Life) of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that cleanſeth and purifieth from all ſin, but are ſtumbling and groping in darkneſs immagining in their dark minds that all is like themſelves, and theſe will profeſs they know God but they are Lyars, (1 <hi>John</hi> 2.4.) for they neither keep nor believe that any can keep his Commandments; but they ſeeing but in part, believes that a Man can but be in part purified, and in part ſanctified, but not throughout: Now I would ask them one Queſtion, wherefore none can be ſanctified throughout? Is not that which ſanctifies in part able to ſanctifie throughout? Is not the Blood of Chriſt able and ſufficient to cleanſe and purifie from all ſin? Was he not able perfectly to ſave thoſe that come unto God by him? Yes ſurely he was, elſe he had been an imperfect Sacrifice; but the cauſe is, either they will not come to him for Life and Salvation (or elſe when they do come, they abide not with him, nor continue not in obedience, to preſs forward to the high Calling that is in Chriſt Jeſus; they ſit down ſhort of the prize; they go not on unto perfection, they faint, and are weary before the work be compleated and finiſhed,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:172162:60"/>like fooliſh Builders, and then content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their own vain immaginations, and pleads inability, weakneſs and failing, which (ſay they) is inſident to all Men, thinking all like themſelves; but they meaſuring all by themſelves, and comparing themſelves with themſelves, <hi>(viz.)</hi> with their own immagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, are not wiſe, as ſaid the Apoſtle; but <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>As many as received him, to them he gave power to become the Sons of God, even to them that believe in his Name,</hi> John 1.12. <hi>and if Sons, then Heirs, and Joynt-heirs with Chriſt;</hi> now Heirs doth inherit, but no unclean thing doth inherit; therefore Sons and Heirs muſt needs be ſanctified through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and muſt needs be born again of the Holy clean Seed that inherits; and the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Ye are the Off-ſpring of God,</hi> and the Off-ſpring of God muſt needs be Holy; for as the Root is, ſo are the Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and as the Tree is, ſo is the Fruit. But I ſhall return to my former Subject a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain (viz.) the Second Covenant, the Light or Law written in the Heart, which we have received, and therefore are not looking up to the Mount that might not be touched, and that burned with Fire,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:172162:61"/>nor at Blackneſs, and Darkneſs, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, nor at Figurative and Shadowy things, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.1. and 12.18, 22. &amp;c. but we are <hi>come to</hi> Mount-Sion, <hi>the City of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, to the New and Heavenly</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>&amp;c. and to Jeſus the Mediator of the New Covenant, and to the unchangeable Prieſthood, that endureth for ever, for the Law maketh Men High-Prieſts that have infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that continueth not by reaſon of Death, but the word of the Oath which was ſince the Law, maketh the Son High-Prieſt, who is Conſecrated for ever, and therefore he is the ſurety of a better Teſtament, and ſuch a High-Prieſt becomes us, and ſuch a one have we need of, who is holy, harmleſs, undefiled ſeparate from Sinners:</hi> Yea, this was his Work, I ſay ſtill, and the end of his coming to ſeparate and ſav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his People from their ſins, and this is Chriſt Jeſus an High-Prieſt of our Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, a Prieſt for ever after the Order of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedeck,</hi> who is worthy of more Glory then <hi>Moſes,</hi> inaſmuch as he that buildeth the Houſe is worthy of more Glory then the Houſe, now Chriſt is a Son over his own Houſe, which Houſe are we, if we hold faſt our confidence and hope to the end, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:172162:61"/>he is able to ſave to the uttermoſt thoſe that come unto God by him, ſeeing he ever liveth to make interceſſion for them; but this they ſtill doubt of, and cannot believe; who are yet wading in the frothy unſtable Waters, and ſtumbling in the dark, being toſſed with every windy vaniſhing Doctrine, and is not come to the breakings of the Day, to the Light, the Son I mean; for its the Sun and Light that makes Day, and makes all things manifeſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.13. <hi>John</hi> 12.36. I ſay they cannot believe that Doctrine, that any ſhould be ſaved to the uttermoſt; and no marvel, for they are Strangers to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Promiſe, the Light and to the vertues and effects of the Light, which until I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and obeyed, I was as doubtful as they, and did object againſt it as incredible; but I was of them the Apoſtle foreſaw, that <hi>ſpoke evil of things they knew not;</hi> for I had not then known nor tryed the Light, though it was in me, yet I loved darkneſs rather; even ſo do they now, who ſpakes againſt Light, and the ſufficiency of it, they ſpeak evil of that they know not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in that thing they corrupt themſelves.</p>
                  <p>But to proceed, I ſay Chriſt Jeſus is
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:172162:62"/>come, the <hi>New and Living Way,</hi> who is King, Prieſt and Prophet; ſo the Covenant is changed, the Prieſt-hood is changed; ſo there muſt of neceſſity be a change of the Law alſo, and then Tythes and Oblations muſt needs ceaſe, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.12. For verily they that were of the Sons of <hi>Levi,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Office of the Prieſthood had a Commandment to take Tythes of the People; but it is evident, that after the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> there ariſeth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prieſthood who is made not by the Law of a carnal Commandment, as the Sons of <hi>Levi</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> was, nor Conſecrated by a carnal nominal Biſhop, (as Prieſts are now) but he was made and ordained by the Power of an endleſs Life; and this is no other then the Son of God, who is Conſecrated for evermore; and ſaith the Apoſtle (with this aſſertion) <hi>There is verily a diſanulling of the Commandment going before, becauſe of the weakneſs and unprofitableneſs thereof:</hi> (mark) here is a diſanulling of the Commandment, what Commandment? The Law of the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Commandment by which the Prieſts (the offspring of <hi>Levi</hi>) received their Office, and the Commandment by which they took
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:172162:62"/>Tythes of the People, read <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; ſo the Prieſthood being no more of <hi>Levi,</hi> nor the Sons of <hi>Aaron,</hi> then there is no more Law, nor no more Tythes after the Firſt Covenant; for the New Covenant is eſtabliſhed, the New and Living Way is made known, and the unchangeable Prieſthood being brought in, the Firſt Covenant and Prieſthood muſt needs give place, the Law muſt needs be abrogated, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment diſanulled, and the firſt Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle and Sanctuary muſt needs be turned out, and then all the Rites and Ceremonies, and all the Appurtenances and Ordinances of that Prieſthood, Tabernacle and Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary muſt needs be turned out alſo; then no more room for Tythes, (being an Appur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance or Ordinance of that Covenant) when Chriſt the Spiritual, Eternal, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable High Prieſt is come, (and we ſay he is) a greater and more perfect Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle; for the Firſt that ſtood in meats and drinks, and divers waſhings, and carnal Ordinances, was but impoſed untill the time of Reformation, being Figures for the time then preſent, [mark] and but ſhadows of good things to come, <hi>Hebr,</hi> 9.10. and 10.1.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:172162:63"/>and 8.5. Now, when doth the time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation enter, that you may ſhake off the firſt Prieſthood, Tabernacle and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Is it not now high time for People to amend, repent and reform? Is it not time for Men to work out their Salvation? Is it not time to make their calling and election ſure? Is it not time to turn from Darkneſs to Light, and from Satans power to God? Is it not time to ſeek the Kingdom of God, and the Righteoſneſs thereof? If ſo, then is not the time of Reformation come? Is not the Spiritual appearance of the Son of God come? Is not the Comforter that leads into all Truth come? Is not the ſound of the Everlaſting Goſpel come? Is not the time in which the true Worſhippers ſhall Worſhip the Father in Spirit and Truth come? Is not the Light that was given for Salvation to the ends of the Earth come? Is not the Light that gives the knowledge of the Glory of God come? Is not he that convinces the World of Sin, of Righteouſneſs, and of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment come? Is not he that is the Way, Truth and Life come? Is not he that ſaves his People from their Sins come? And is it not now a time of Reformation? Is it not
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:172162:63"/>now time to die unto Sin, and awake unto Righteouſneſs? Is it not time to put on the New Man, which renews into the Image of God, and brings into Righteouſneſs and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs? elſe in vain hath the many and large Profeſſions of <hi>England</hi> been; and to what purpoſe hath it carried the name ſo long of a holy and reformed Nation, if the time of Reformation be not come? Indeed there is little more amongſt many of the Tollerated Churches in <hi>England</hi> but Profeſſion only; amongſt all the Lo here's, and Lo there's; amongſt all the many Diviſions, Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Sects and Separations; amongſt all the Gatherings, Societies or Aſſembles, how few hath the Womb of Reformation really brought forth? and how many hath proved Abortives? yea, how many is Strangled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'ch Womb? Oh! he wiſt well what he ſaid, who ſaid, <hi>Strait is the Gate, and narrow is the Way that leadeth unto Life, and few there be that find it:</hi> yea, may I ſay, few there be that ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, and therefore muſt needs be few that find it. Oh! who can but lament, yea, mourn and ſorrow in ſecret to ſee the preſent ſad and miſerable Eſtate of <hi>England,</hi> who was formerly accounted as a Nurſery of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:172162:64"/>and Godlineſs; and how is it now grown over with Weeds, Briers and Thiſtles? Oh, who doth not ſee how wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs is eſtabliſhed, and ſin increaſeth as a flood; how the Workers of Iniquity are ſet up and the proud called happy? Oh, how doth Idolatry grow and flouriſh, and all manner of abomination abound? yea, they work wickedneſs greedily, making haſte to do evil, and are skilfull to tranſgreſs; yea, they improve both wits, life, time and eſtates in the luſts and pleaſures o'th Fleſh; they commit lewdneſs with heart and hand, their feet run to evil, and they are not at all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, neither do they bluſh; they ſport themſelves with their abominations, and the fear of God is not before their eyes. Oh, the unparallell'd abominations that ſwims in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is undeclarable! Oh, how doth the veſſels of the Whore flote upon her Waters! ſurely, ſurely, the juſt God will be avenged on her, and will recompence her for all her abominations, and notorious evils; he will bring down the pride of her ſtout hearted, and humble the heady High-mindedneſs of her High ones, and lay low the lofty looks of her Lordly leaders, and ſeverly puniſh the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:172162:64"/>pride of her Princes; Yea, his anger is already kindled, and his wrath ſhall ballance her wickedneſs, and who ſhall withſtand his Power, or who can divert his Decree: in that day the wickedneſs of the wicked ſhall be upon him, for neither Rock nor Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſhall ſave them, they'l find no cover from the Storm, nor no hiding place from the Tempeſt, though they now flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with their own imaginations, and heal themſelves with ſmooth words, and fortifie themſelves with the arm of Fleſh, ſitting like a Queen that ſhall ſee no ſorrow, making merry over the Witneſs which lies ſlain in their Streets; yea, they hate to be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; <hi>The Judges judge for Reward, the Prophets divine for Money, the Prieſts preach for Hire, and hare rule by their means, and the People love to have it ſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I remember <hi>Malachi</hi> complaining, cryed out, <hi>O ye Prieſts this Commandment is for you, and if you will not hear, neither lay it to heart, I will bring a Curſe upon you, and I will Curſe your Bleſſings; for ye have departed out of the Way, ye have cauſed many to ſtumble; therefore have I made you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible and baſe before all the People,</hi> Mal.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:172162:65"/>2.1, 2, 8, 9. And is not this the State of the Prieſthood of <hi>England,</hi> who is ready enough to cry, Bring ye all the Tythes into the Store Houſe, (<hi>viz.</hi> into their Kitchins, Purſe and Pocket) and pay them (ſay they) duely, and truly, liberally, and with a chearful Heart for God loves a chearful giver; and then ſay they, God will remove his Judgments from amongſt you, and thoſe (let them be as vile as they will) that will pay them liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally (and that with the better) and is ready to put into their mouths, and labour, and give it to them; to ſuch they will cry <hi>Peace, peace,</hi> and ſay ſuch a one is a very honeſt Man, and they will befriend him in any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of concernment before Magiſtrates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but he that ceaſeth to put into their mouths, (let him be as honeſt as he will) againſt him they <hi>prepare War,</hi> and cry, <hi>Bring ye all the Tythes,</hi> &amp;c. when as it was they that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lichi</hi> complained of, <hi>that robbed God in Tythes and Offerings,</hi> Mal. 2.1. and 1.6. it was they that <hi>deſpiſed his Name;</hi> it was they that <hi>offered polluted Bread, and the blind, and lame and ſick for Sacrifice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>will ſhut a door for naught, or will kindle a fire on mine Altar for naught,</hi>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:172162:65"/>verſe 10, and are they not ſo now, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them will ſhut a Door for naught? which of them hath any thing to Preach, if the People have nothing to give? nay, they cannot relie of the Peoples gift, but they muſt know what Revenew belongs unto the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combent, or Miniſter of that place, and how it doth ariſe; and it muſt be confirmed to them either by the Biſhop, Magiſtrates, or Donators, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thus they Bargain, yea, they are as expert Merchants as ever <hi>Babylon</hi> bred, obſerving their time for Trading; and when they have enjoyed a Benefit Ten, Twenty or Thirty years, if another fall vacant of a greater Revenue, Stipend or Value, then they beſtir themſelves, with all diligence, by writing, running, riding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (yea, ſome will not let to ride Poſt to and again) to the Donators, Biſhops, or ſuch as can impower and inveſt them in ſuch a place; and having obtained it, then they will be gone; there ſay they, a Man may live comfortably, this is a poor ſorry mean place having this or the other inconvenience: And thus they ſhew themſelves unto all; for it appears their Comfort is Fleſhly eaſe, and their End is great Benefices, and their
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:172162:66"/>gain is filthy lucre, their god (they chiefly ſerve) is their Belly, and what will be their reward? hence they fulfil the old proverb, <hi>No penny, No pater Noſter;</hi> nay not ſo much as a Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, or Farwel Sermon; Benefit taken away they are ſtruck dumb.</p>
                  <p>And they are ſo far ſhort of the Prieſts in <hi>Malachi</hi>'s dayes, that they will kindle no fire at all; they will keep no Store-Houſe at all, neither for the poor Widow, Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, Orphant or Stranger; (theſe muſt beg in the Country) Tythes is confirmed to us, ſay they, for our maintenance and liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood by the Law of God and Man, that ſo we may be leſs cumbred in the World, and may devote and give up our ſelves more to the Service and Worſhip of God, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Church: And thus they claim Tythes to be theirs, and yet (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) they will keep no Store-Houſe to maintain the Poor out of, as they did under the Law; nor they'l kindle no fire on the Altar, neither will they Sacrifice or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any thing unto the Lord out of their Tythes and Firſt-fruits; they'l neither Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice Bull nor Goat, Lamb nor Dove, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cake nor fine Flower, nor Bread
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:172162:66"/>leavened nor unleavened, neither Meat offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nor Drink-offering, Sin-offering, Peace-offering nor Treſpaſs-offering, nor any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Oblation according to the Levitical Law, and yet they muſt have Tythes paid them as they were then; all that Law ſay they, is aboliſhed ſince Chriſt came in the Fleſh, ſave that ſweet morſel of Tythes which is ſo pleaſant to their pallat, like <hi>Achan</hi>'s wedge of Gold, and Babyloniſh Garment, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.21. which they covet as much as he did, and would ſave alive, as <hi>Saul</hi> did the King of the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> and the beſt of the ſpoyl as Sheep, Oxen and Fatlings, &amp;c. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.9. even ſo they would have Tythes kept up above all the reſt of the Ordinances, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Services of the firſt Tabernacle, and that ſhadowy Diſpenſation, Tythes is the ſweeteſt of all, many of the reſt would be trouble and coſt to them, and diminiſh their Revenue: So theſe they confeſs to be aboliſhed, and why not Tythes ſay I? Of what inſtitution was Tythes? Or for what term more then the reſt? that they muſt not be aboliſhed with the reſt? I know no cauſe but the reaſons aforeſaid crept in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their Anceſtor, or Mother the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:172162:67"/>Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in the Night of Apoſtacy.</p>
                  <p>Then again, there is that in <hi>Luke</hi> 11.42. where Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Wo unto you Scribes and Phariſees, &amp;c.</hi> from which they infer that Chriſt allowed the payment of Tythes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel; indeed ſo ſay I that Chriſt there allowed the payment of Tythes, (the <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſees</hi> being as under the Law) but not under the Goſpel, its true he condems them for the neglect of weightier matters, as Judgment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may not I accordingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem both Prieſt and People now; he ſaid they Strained at a Gnat, and ſwallowed a Camel; may not I ſay ſo now to them that makes ſo much ado about Tythes, and neglects things of greater weight, as departing from Iniquity as Swearing, Lying, Coveting, Stealing, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing, Defrauding, Cozening, Drinking, Cheating, Adultery, Fornication, and many more things of greater weight, walking in diſobedience to what God hath manifeſted by his Light in their Conſciences; doing that which they ought not, and leaving undone what they ought, they are (at beſt) but like the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> Sticking at the outſide things, as Tythes, Ordinances of the Church, ſo called, Conformity, and the like Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:172162:67"/>required by Men, but never ſhew ſo much zeal and diligence to keep their Conſciences clear, and to obſerve what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of them by the Lord; they'll pretend a great zeal for the Church and Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but when appears ſo much zeal for God? and the keeping of his Commandments, and of loving him with all their Heart. But to come more poſitively to the point of his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of Tythes in this place, I ſay, I grant it for they were then under the Law, and the Law was but a fulfilling, <hi>For he came not to deſtroy the Law, but to fulfill it,</hi> which he did obſerve in the dayes of his Fleſh, untill he had offered up himſelf a perfect and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Sacrifice, then he ſaid, <hi>It is finiſhed;</hi> then came in the Second Covenant, and took place of the Firſt, (it being diſanulled) the Second was Eſtabliſhed when his Blood was ſhed, by which Salvation was obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>For without ſhedding of Blood there is no Remiſſion:</hi> So may not we as juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Condemn then the Tything Prieſts, and other fiery Zelots in our Age, who is ſo Exact for their Tythes, as if Salvation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended in that particular, and is very neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in ſeeking after Righteouſneſs, Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Reformation of Life; but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:172162:68"/>if any ſeek after God, or the knowledge of his Way and Truth, then they cry out of ſuch with open mouth, as Fanatick, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, Seducers, Erroneous perſons, who ſeek to be Wiſer then their Forefathers; What is become of them, ſay they, that the Way and Worſhip that ſerved them can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſerve you, but you muſt have a new Way of your own, contrary to Church and State? I now remember ſome of the ſame Spirit ſaid to the Apoſtles, <hi>They were ſetters up of ſtrange Gods, bringers in of new Doctrine, turners of the World upſide down; away with them they Taught the People againſt the Law and the Cuſtoms of the Place and People, they were not worthy to live;</hi> ſo that I ſee by experience, <hi>They that live after the Fleſh perſecute thoſe that live after the Spirit</hi> in every Age; but I ſhall not here inſiſt, but as I have ſaid before (to that of <hi>Luke</hi>) he ſpoke to them that was yet under the Judaical Laws, (but ſo am not I) and was a fulfilling them, as appears elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where by his ſaying to <hi>John</hi> about Baptiſm, <hi>Suffer it to be ſo now, for ſo it becomes us to fulfil all Righteouſneſs;</hi> ſo he was but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating that Diſpenſation; but when he came to ſuffer, and was lifted up upon the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:172162:68"/>Croſs, he ſaid, <hi>Its finiſhed;</hi> then he put an end to all the Ordinances of the Firſt Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and brought in the Second, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Prieſthood, which ſtands for ever after the Order of <hi>Melchiſedeck.</hi> Thus much for Tythes as they were due un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, and no where elſe; and as they were an Ordinance amongſt the Jews only in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and no People elſe; for its ſaid, <hi>He gave his Statutes and his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to Iſrael,</hi> to every Nation he did not ſo; but I am no <hi>Jew,</hi> therefore not under that Law, but rather of the Stock of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> (as is believed) and Tything among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> I never yet read of; and Chriſt the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs ſake (and the Heart and Life of what the Law figured out) being come, neither <hi>Jews</hi> nor <hi>Gentiles</hi> ought to be any longer under Shadows and Figures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But again, when their claiming of Tythes by vertue of the Moſaical Laws is overtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and will not hold plea <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> (as they ſay) then they betake them to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is, <hi>Jure humano,</hi> or <hi>The Civil Laws of this Nation,</hi> by which Laws ſay they, Tythes is eſtabliſhed and ſetled to them (ſay
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:172162:69"/>the Prieſts) by vertue of their Place and Office as a moſt competent Livelyhood for them and their Families: In anſwer where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I ſay, that the radix and grand Original property of this Title and Claim did and doth ſtill ariſe from the Moſaical or Levitical Law, (which is diſanulled and done away in Chriſt, as is before proved) and hence they are accounted a Spiritual propriety, and therefore a (pretended) Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Law and Court is kept and appointed (by Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Authority, within their ſeveral juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diſtinct from their Civil Laws) only for the tryal and recovery of Tythes, and ſuch other matters as they account Spiritual; and this Levitical Inſtitution is the ſole Baſis and Foundation upon which their Civil Law de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, and the Foundation being taken away the Structure or Building falls; ſo that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſanull'd in Chriſt, the Civil Law hath no more power, ſo that the Title of Tythes is loſt. Now again, every Law is or ought to be grounded upon Equity, and ſound Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and Righteouſneſs, and for ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious and pious honeſt end and purpoſe, as the Preamble to all Laws do hold forth, which is the Key that opens the myſtery,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:172162:69"/>ground, intent and end of every Law and Statute whatſoever; ſo that of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th about Tythes, doth not inſtitute, enact or ordain, ſettle or impoſe them as a Temporal Civil Injunction, but they are there called Spiritual gifts belonging to holy Church, and becauſe many doth deny the payment, &amp;c. ſo this Act doth but enjoyn the payment of them, as a ſuppoſed due and right formerly belonging to holy Church; and therefore doth but (at the utmoſt) repair, ſtrengthen and preſerve that which was like to decay, but doth not ſet up any new ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, property or title; ſo the reaſons of this Law being taken away (which is, that they are a ſuppoſed due) this Act is nulled.</p>
                  <p>Theſe before mentioned being the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly main Grounds and Reaſons whereupon Tythes are claimed and payed, which I hope is ſatisfactorily anſwered; indeed, ſome more frivilous Objections are made; (as, what will not many ſay to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves when they are in an exigent? yea, brawl, menace, perhaps beat with wicked fiſt, revile or ſcoff, and it may be ſet an Officer on one, and hale him before a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:172162:70"/>&amp;c.) I ſay many more they make to little purpoſe, as that in <hi>Luke</hi> 18. where the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee</hi> payed Tythes of all he poſſeſſed, which hath little in it, unleſs they would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned (with him) as a <hi>Phariſee</hi> with their outſide holineſs: others ſay, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzle the mouth of the Ox that treadeth out the Corn;</hi> I ſay ſo too; if they be Oxen let them be unmuzled, and live of what they tread out, which is ſo little that they never durſt rely upon it yet, but they are more idle then ſuch Oxen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this is like their plowing in hope, and ſowing in hope, which for the moſt part fails before they ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plow or ſow; for in which of the Prieſts did ever the hope endure untill he reaped the Fruit of his plowing or ſowing? but rather firſt he muſt know what Stipend there is, what Tythes or Gleab-lands, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Revenue belongs to the Incombent, and how it doth ariſe; this you may ſay is too true: Again ſay they, <hi>He that gathers a Flock let him eat of the milk of the Flock;</hi> (indeed ſo ſay I) but they either get no flock gathered, or elſe their Flock is barren, and gives no milk, or otherwiſe the milk they give doth not ſatisfie, which makes them pull,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:172162:70"/>tug and draw ſo hard for milk, meat and maintenance from others pertaining to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Flock which they never gathered, as daily experience teacheth to their ſhame, and to the ſhame of all that are gathered by them: Again, (ſay they) <hi>If we have ſown unto you Spiritual things, is it a great matter if we reap your carnal things?</hi> I ſay its no great matter, but rather the part and duty of a Chriſtian; but to whom have they ſown Spirituals? I am ſure not to me, for <hi>L. W.</hi> hath Miniſtred nothing to me, but that which is Earthly, and ſavours of Death, (as I have elſewhere ſaid) which deſerves not my Carnals, nor any other maintenance from me, not that I am ſtrait-handed, or ſo knit and joyned to the things the Lord hath endued me with, but I can deſtribute them freely to ſuch as ſow Spirituals, and Miniſters freely from the mouth of the Lord, or to any other in neceſſity; but <hi>L. W.</hi> (as is well known) hath no ſuch neceſſity, for all his eager pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit after my Carnals theſe Three or Four Years laſt paſt; but he hath coveted an evil covetouſneſs, to ſet his neſt on high, but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hath not delivered his Soul from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of evil, but hath conſulted confuſion to his ſhame.</p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:172162:71"/>
                  <p>So Still I ſay the grand Title ſtood in the Moſaical Inſtitutions, all which pointed at Chriſt, and Chriſt being come, they fall flat, and to them a period is ſet; for its Evident for ſome hundreds of years after Chriſt, there was neither Claim nor payment of Tythes, nor no ſetling or confining of Miniſters to ſuch and ſuch Pariſhes or Places, but they that received freely, preached freely, and went from one Country to another, and from one People to another, as they were drawn by the Spirit of the Lord; and in thoſe dayes there was no ſetled nor forced maintenance belonged unto them, but they who received Spirituals, and were brought into the Faith and Fellowſhip of the Saints they adminiſtred of their Temporals freely without any injunction, (as many hath done in <hi>England</hi> theſe late years) and the Lord having opened the Hearts of many (as <hi>Lydia</hi>) they called them into their Houſe, being open, to diſtribute to their Neceſſities; ſo that they that ſet forth without money or ſcrip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wanted nothing: yea, I believe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Lords Miniſters and Servants (called Quakers) hath Travelled (in theſe late years) many Hundred of miles, from
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:172162:71"/>one People and Nation to another, having been perſecuted, and beat, and haled to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and out of Priſon, here and there amongſt a ſtrange Nation and People which they knew not, who when they ſet forth could not aſſure themſelves of one Nights lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or one meals Meat, and yet they were in every place ſufficiently provided for, and had no want, they only caſt their care upon the Lord, and lived upon the Goſpel, being Preachers of it, and by the Faith of the Son of God, as did the primitive Chriſtians in the Apoſtles dayes, and ſome Hundred of years after, untill the power of Chriſtianity was loſt, and the Apoſtacy crept in, and then they fell into Forms and Immitations, <hi>Rome</hi> being the leading Church ſetled Biſhops, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars and Prieſts, and erected Monaſteries, Abbeys and Religious Houſes, and placed them there, and brought in the old Rites and Cuſtoms of the Jews again, (under a colour of Zeal and Piety) perſwading the People to give gifts to pious uſes; ſo enjoyning them to one thing after another, until their Traditions were received as Canonical, and amongſt the reſt brought in this of Tythes again, which for a long time
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:172162:72"/>was payed at the Owners pleaſure, either to the Poor, or to the aforeſaid Monaſteries and Religious Houſes for pretended Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual uſes; and when they ſaw that the greater part deſtributed their Tythes to the Poor, Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third did reſtrain the Peoples freedoms, <hi>Anno</hi> 1180. And Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> ordained that Tythes ſhould not be deſtributed to the Poor, but to the Mother Church, <hi>Anno</hi> 1274. And Pope <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the Fourth ordained the payment of Tythes upon penalty of Excomunication by a Council at <hi>Trent,</hi> about the year 1560. And thus they crept in again, (as they fell from the Power of Godlineſs) then they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to build again that which was before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and ſo brought in theſe old Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances again, in immitation of the Moſaical Law, and ſo came to force and compel a maintenance (for a Prieſthood and Miniſtry which was not of <hi>Levi</hi>'s Linnage) which was never uſed nor known amongſt the Chriſtians in the purity of the Goſpel; but being lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle acquainted or read in the State of the Church as it did deſcend from the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times downwards to this Day, I ſhall be more ſparing in things thereunto pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:172162:72"/>and for the further ſatisfaction therein, (and how <hi>Rome,</hi> and other Churches, fell from their Primitive purity, and how they brought in Tythes and the Relicks of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſm again) and every external extant Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance or Tradition now allowed and eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed throughout all <hi>Europe</hi>) I refer the Reader to <hi>A. Pearſon</hi>'s Book, called, <hi>The great Caſe of Tything,</hi> and alſo to <hi>Francis Howgil</hi>'s Books, the one called, <hi>The Glory of the True Church Diſcovered in its Purity,</hi> where he proves Tythes no Goſpel Ordinance; the other called, <hi>The Great Caſe of Tything once more Revived &amp;c.</hi> where the State of the Church in the Primitive times, and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from year to year, and the bringing in of all the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Stuff, and Superſtitious Traſh is ſufficiently treated of, and may be ſatisfactory to any ſober Reader that deſires to be inſtructed.</p>
                  <p>Now it appears clear, that that Law by which Tythes was payable and due under the Firſt Covenant was only Eſtabliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews,</hi> (as I ſaid before) and that in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> being a peculiar People, to whom he gave his Laws and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:172162:73"/>his Statutes for ever, as its ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19. and its believed we are not of the <hi>Jews</hi> Genealogy, neither of the Offspring of any of the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> according to the Fleſh; and therefore (if Tythes were yet an Ordinance in force) as to the contrary is ſufficiently proved ought not to be paid by us by vertue of that Law and Covenant, we being of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Stock by Nature, (is authentical) and ſo hath nothing to do with the Ordinances of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> according to the Fleſh, who was the natural Branches unto whom pertained the Law, and the Covenant, and the Oracles of God, and they fell through unbelief, and by their fall we came to be ingrafted, and we <hi>ſtand by Faith, which is the Gift of God, a Myſtery held in a pure Conſcience,</hi> and not by the Obſervation of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Firſt Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: So let the blind Prieſts and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors lay their hands upon their mouths, and be aſhamed of their groſs abſurdity, and ſtupid Sences being mudled and jumbled in obſcurity with their many Arts and Sciences, multiplicity of Tongues, and divided Langu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, one pleading one thing, and another
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:172162:73"/>pleading another, until they become like Froth upon the Waters, which while not touched appears material and ſubſtantial, but if once handled waſteth and vaniſheth away; ſo doth their windy deformed Doctrine, and typical Tenents, who hath long Preached and talked of a Covenant of Grace, which is ſtill a Myſtery, or as a Book Sealed to them while they are ſtuddying and muſing in their Greek and Latin Libraries, not at all percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Vail, or the Wall of Partition that ſtands between them and the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace unbroken down and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
                  <p>One other Objection is in my mind, which is this, ſpeaking of <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> who recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Tenth of the Spoils from <hi>Abraham,</hi> its ſaid, <hi>Levi, who received Tythes payed Tythes in Abraham;</hi> and further he ſaith, <hi>Here men that die receive Tythes; but there he received them of whom it is Witneſſed that he liveth;</hi> now what objection can be made from theſe words, <hi>Here Men that die receive Tythes, but there, &amp;c?</hi> the words hath Relation to two times or places, or as <hi>here</hi> or <hi>there?</hi> as <hi>here</hi> in this time, and <hi>there</hi> in that time; for the Law being 430 Years after
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:172162:74"/>
                     <hi>Abraham,</hi> or after the Promiſe was made to <hi>Abraham, Galat.</hi> 3.17. muſt needs be nearer to the Apoſtle, or to the days of the Apoſtle, then the day that <hi>Abraham</hi> gave the Tenth of the ſpoyl to <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> by ſo many years; ſo that he might well ſay <hi>here</hi> when he ſpoke of the Sons of <hi>Levi,</hi> and <hi>there</hi> when he ſpoke of <hi>Melchiſedeck;</hi> but if any ſay it hath Relation to the very Age and Day when the Apoſtle ſpoke it, (which is diſputable) yet I may ſay now as he ſaid then, Here Men that die receive Tythes, (yea ſuch as are dead while they live) and not only receive Tythes, but perſecute, impriſon, and in a manner rob for Tythes ſuch as doth not give contrary to Law or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, but I allow not ſuch: I may ſay here Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> Swear, Lye, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet, Oppreſs and Perſecute exceedingly for Tythes, and yet pretend to be Goſpel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; but I ſay again, I allow not ſuch neither believe they are Goſpel Miniſters; ſo this makes little (in my judgment) for Tythes under the Goſpel: Then again, <hi>There he received Tythes</hi> (viz. <hi>Melchiſedeck) of whom it is witneſſed that he liveth;</hi> and Chriſt is ſaid <hi>to be a Prieſt for ever after the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:172162:74"/>Order of</hi> Melchiſedeck; Now if any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from hence that Tythes or Firſt-fruits belongs to Chriſt, as being, or coming in <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi>'s Order; I ſay, rather it hath reference to his immutability and unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs, then taking of Tythes; for its ſaid, <hi>He was without deſcent, without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or end of dayes;</hi> and if it related to Tythes; firſt, I ſay to that, it was but the Tenths of the Spoyls, and not of all his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and Increaſe, clean and unclean, as they are now claimed: And ſecondly, I hope you'l grant Chriſt a Spiritual Prieſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any will give, it muſt be the Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruits and Tenths of things Spiritual, and not Carnal, elſe there is no agreement nor coherence; <hi>For Sacrifice and Offerings he would not,</hi> for he being Spiritual accepts nothing but what is Spiritual, and proceeds from the meaſure of his own Spirit and Truth in every one; and herein let as many offer and give unto the Lord as will, and as much, and as often as they will, I allow of it, if it be a Spiritual Offering indeed.</p>
                  <p>Thus much in Defence of my Innocent Sufferings, being thus far convinced in my
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:172162:75"/>Judgment, and perſwaded in my Heart and Conſcience, I dare not allow nor yield to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing ſo noxious to my Conſcience, and contrary to the Goſpel Diſpenſation and the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as is before proved) in the firſt place Figurative, impoſed for the time then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, until the time of Reformation: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, being only an Ordinance among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and ſuch as were under the Law, and not to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> nor ſuch as are under the Goſpel. Thirdly, being claimed as Spiritual by Divine Inſtitution, when as the extent and ſcope of the Inſtitution is finiſhed and ended, and is therefore now no more Spiritual then the reſt of the nine parts. And laſtly, being generally Dedicated, Payed and Received for the uſe and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of an Antichriſtian, dark Man-made Miniſtry, who only ſeeks ours, and not us; for which the Wiſeſt and Learnedſt of them can neither produce Precept nor Preſident from Chriſt, or any other his Apoſtles, Miniſters and Servants in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tive purity of the Church, being an old Ordinance of <hi>Moſes</hi> renovated in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Apoſtacy, and Traditionally diſperſed by
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:172162:75"/>Papiſtical Authority over all the <hi>Europian</hi> Nations, as doth fully and largely appear in thoſe pithy and ponderous works of the before recited Authors <hi>A. P.</hi> and <hi>F. H.</hi> this Title of Tythes having ſuch a pleaſant delightſom reliſh, it hath been ſtill retained amongſt all the Reformed Rulers in Church and State, who hath ſo largely profeſſed to caſt off the Papiſtical Yoke.</p>
                  <p>Now I ſhall proceed to ſay ſomething to thoſe my Neighbours and Pariſhioners, amongſt whom I have had my converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in times paſt, and a ſociety when I wrought the will of the Fleſh, who have known my manner of Life from a Child; I ſay to ſuch, what have I done? what have I thought? what have I acted or ſpoken that hath deſerved any ſuch meaſure as I have received from <hi>L. W?</hi> or what evil have I done? or what occaſion have I given to any Mans perſon, good name or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate at any time? eſpecially ſince I aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongſt the People called Quakers, let him, you, or any of you, or any other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon come forth, that can juſtly charge any thing againſt me, wherein I have dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:172162:76"/>any one the value of a penny, and have denied to give ſatisfaction, or have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered violence to any ones Dog, and I ſhall willingly (upon due proof) make acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement and ſatisfaction to the utmoſt of my power; for bleſſed be the Lord my Righteouſneſs and Redeemer, there is no thing upon my Conſcience and Spirit, but what is between the Lord and my own Soul in matter of my Teſtimony; yea, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly magnified be the Righteous Lord my preſerver, to whoſe praiſe I deſire to ſpeak it, that though <hi>L. W.</hi> and many others have ſought occaſion, and have waited for my halting or falling, they have not yet ſeen it, nor got no occaſion againſt me (ſave about the Law and Worſhip of my God, or the holding forth my Teſtimony and Exerciſe of my Conſcience towards him, for which I have been reviled, mocked and reproached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you; yea, the Children in the Streets have played upon me with their Tongues; this I ſpeak to their (or their Parents) ſhame, but was as joy and rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to my Soul, being for Righteouſneſs ſake, the Bleſſing of the Lord was with me, and mine Enemies knew it not, nor
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:172162:76"/>they that dwelt in Darkneſs ſaw it not.</p>
                  <p>This further I have to propound to you, whether ye can allow of it? or that it would be juſtifiable in the Law of Equity and true Judgment, that my Servant ſhould Sue you at Law, make ſpoil, and carry away your goods, and caſt your perſons into Priſon, and after all ſeek to make your Eſtates forfeit and confiſcate, and all for the wages and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of the Service he hath done for me? which of you would approve of ſuch work; or of me in keeping ſuch a Servant? would you not rather ſay to me, if I have hired a Servant and employed him, pay him and maintain him alſo; why doth he trouble you? What have you to do to pay him for my work, ſeeing he is my Servant? Is not this the caſe between me and you? Is not <hi>L. W.</hi> your Miniſter, and alſo your Servant? And by what Law or Reaſon ought I to pay him for doing your ſervice? Hath ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you or he a Preſident in all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of any ſuch unequal deeds? Did ye ever Read of any of the Churches, or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God in Ages paſt that uſed ſuch things? I trow not; If I had deſtributed
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:172162:77"/>voluntarily it had been one thing, but being ſued and compelled thereunto, therefore I complain; may not I ſay to you, why do you hire more ſervants then you can pay? Or why do you keep more then you are able to maintain? Elſe, why am I thus perſecuted for his maintenance? May not I ſpeak this to your ſhame? being ſo many (as I may ſay) for one Servant, you are either hard Maſters, and very penurious and ſtrait-handed to your Servants, or elſe your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants are very <hi>laviſh, proud profane</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal,</hi> and hath <hi>much maintaining:</hi> Did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any Miniſter of ours (called a <hi>Quaker</hi>) come among you to ſue and caſt into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for their maintenance and livelihood? or what would you ſay if they ſhould? I believe you would condemn both us and them; and indeed we ſhould be greatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, if they ſhould; for my part, I had rather Adminiſter to the laſt mite, then any ſuch cauſe of aſpertion ſhould be given againſt us, and alſo teſtifie againſt them as no Miniſters of Chriſt that Preaches for any ſuch ends; if they be Goſpel Miniſters, let their Goſpel maintain them, or let them la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with their hands; though many have
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:172162:77"/>ſaid, we are a diſorderly and unmannerly People; but I affirm we have better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and manners amongſt us then you have; for your Servants are become your Maſters, and Lords it over you, and both in that, and many other things, diſorder and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is come over you, as they that built <hi>Babel</hi> of old.</p>
                  <p>I remember well what <hi>Malachi</hi> ſaith, complaining of the Prieſts, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to verſe 9. <hi>I will ſend a Curſe upon you, I'll Curſe your Bleſſings; yea,</hi> I <hi>have Curſed them already: Behold, I'll corrupt your Seed, and ſpread dung upon your Faces, and ye ſhall know that I have ſent this Commandment unto you, that my Covenant might be with</hi> Levi, <hi>my Covenant was with him of Life and Peace, the Law of Truth was in his mouth; for the Prieſts lips ſhould preſerve knowledge; but ye are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted out of the Way, ye have cauſed many to ſtumble at the Law; ye have corrupted the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of</hi> Levi, (ſaith he) <hi>therefore have I made you contemptible and baſe before all the People.</hi> [mark, now] Is not this the caſe and condition of the preſent Prieſthood and Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> thoſe neutraliſts, that are neither Miniſters of the Law nor
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:172162:78"/>Goſpel? hath not the Lord made them contemptible and baſe before all the People; yea, where ſhall a Man come and have any Diſcourſe about them, but the moſt part, if not all, doth generally conclude they are Covetous, vile, proud and profane Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Oppreſſors, Drunkards, Men-pleaſers, Time-ſervers, Turn-coats, Heady and High-minded, <hi>lovers of Pleaſures and filthy lucre more then of God, having a Form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but denying the Power; but their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall be,</hi> (and is) <hi>made manifeſt, it ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed no further,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle.</p>
                  <p>May not I ſay the Merchants of this laſt Age hath exceeded all that ever went before them, they can trade on thoſe dayes called their Sabboths, or Lords-dayes, and prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit all others from either trading or labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their lawful and honeſt vocations (but if they'l Play, Drink, Revel, Swear, and be Profane, there they may have liberty enough) on thoſe Dayes? Alſo, whether any have need of their Merchandice or not, or will come and Trade with them or not, or will take any of their Commodities from them or not; yet they have a Law, and by that Law compel them to pay, and that
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:172162:78"/>even their own Rates what they demand; and if any refuſe, then they'l menace and thunder out their Comminations, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comunications, and ſome they'l caſt in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, it may be till Death, and yet cloke themſelves over with the name of Goſpel Miniſters, and plead innocency, and ſay its the Law that requires it, and binds Men to be ſubject to Eccleſiaſtical Canons and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; now, wherein doth their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency appear, unleſs in putting a white Coat above a black one, a Popiſh dreſs; and if the Figure be true, they are but outſide <hi>Phariſees,</hi> appearing white and clean with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and that in Apparel only: Yea, I may ſay they are as wiſe expert Marriners (in that <hi>Babiloniſh</hi> Wiſdom) as ever Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficked or Sailed upon the Waters of the Great Whore, they can Sail with any Wind that blows within the Circuit of <hi>Babylons</hi> Coaſts; but that Propheſie comes to be fulfilled upon them, <hi>Evil Men and Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ſhall wax worſe and worſe deceiving, and being deceived, &amp;c.</hi> But bleſſed be the Lord the Day is dawned that declares them, and the Light that makes them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, with their all Abominations, and the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:172162:79"/>Son is appeared that will diſperſe them as the Morning miſt, ſo that their skirts ſhall be uncovered, and their nakedneſs ſhall be laid open, and their viſage ſhall be no more Vailed, for the Judgment of the Great Whore is come and coming, wherein all her Merchants ſhall weep and mourn, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no Man buyeth their Merchandice any more.</p>
                  <p>So this Mite of my Teſtimony I have caſt in, being but a Mite indeed in compariſon of the many weighty, praiſe-worthy works, given forth by many of the dear and faithful Servants of God upon this very Subject in this very Age, from the breakings forth of the Glorious Light in them revealed and made known; And for the clearing my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in the ſight of the Lord, I refer this to publick view, and give this Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to my Countrymen and Acquaintance, or any others that yet ſee not the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and the Prieſts in this very point; and partly for ſatisfying or ſilencing of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, eſpecially the People of the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants,</hi> or Congregational Church at <hi>Melmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> (ſo called) who though (as I have ſaid before) they once made the non payment
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:172162:79"/>of Tythes an Article of their Judgment; yet have of late (ſince I became a ſufferer for them) whiſperingly or clandeſtinely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned me in ſecret more then many (if not all) others that have leſs profeſſion, and ſeem more profane, rendring me fool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh and unwiſe to ſuffer ſo much, and ſo long for ſuch a trivial, external, tempory matter, as they call it; but to me it was and is no ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll matter being to the Contrary perſwaded in my Conſcience, and knowing by good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and aſſured Teſtimonies, that I muſt ſtand or fall by obedience or diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the manifeſtation of the Lords precious Gift and Light in my own Soul and Conſcience; I therefore value not the Judgment of any Man, or People, (being from the Light, the Line of True Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Rule of Life to me) and to be accounted a Fool is no new nor ſtrange thing, for a Fool I am to their Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as was the good and precious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God in Ages paſt, <hi>For the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God is fooliſhneſs with Men;</hi> and caſting things upon me behind my back, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes them not, it were more Chriſtianly for them to Admoniſh, or Inſtruct me face
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:172162:80"/>to face, and to give me their Advice and Reaſons in matters of this nature, which if I found to be more weighty, ſound, and agreeable to the Witneſs of God in my Conſcience, I ſhould be very ready, willing and glad to receive them, and be informed by them; I am neither ſo far remote, nor ſo much a ſtranger to them, (though my Principle may) but this way they chuſe not, but makes War and fights as Men that beat the Air hiddenly, or a far off, ſlighting and contemning my Principle, and me for its ſake, above moſt of People, as though I had been Poyſonous and Infectious where I came, prohibiting ſome of their Society, (and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſo called) to have any Fellowſhip or Converſe with me, or to receive either Books or Papers from me, or come where I was; and one of their leading Teachers (<hi>G. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholſon</hi> by Name) denied to make good their own Principles and Tenents, held forth in their own Defence againſt us; and alſo to make good ſeveral contumelious aſpertions caſt upon us (in my Hearing) by him and others; and alſo denied to give an account of his Faith and Hope in Chriſt J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſus, ſaying, <hi>It was in vain, &amp;c.</hi> with
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:172162:80"/>ſeveral ſuch like matters which I ſhall now omit; and yet theſe People will be Slighting and Villifying us in ſecret; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we have much more cauſe to have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteemed them and their Principles, having more knowledge of both them and it, when we were amongſt them, then ever they had of us or ours; and in villifying our Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, they ſpeak evil of things they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, being a Treaſure whoſe worth and value they never knew, the myſtery whereof is hid and ſealed from that ſtate and nature they live in; we have known theirs, but they never knew ours; yea, for my own part I can truly ſay in the Light and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, that I had more love and affection in my Heart for thoſe people, then any other Profeſſion that was from the Light; yea, many a time I could have mourned in ſecret, and been willing to have undergone great hardſhip that they might have been won and gained to the Lord; yea, I could as it were, have plucked them out of the fire many a time; other times my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hath been weighed and burthened, yea, filled with indignation againſt ſome of them that were Elders, Teachers and Leaders
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:172162:81"/>that cauſed the reſt to Err, who like the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old, have <hi>Shut the Kingdom of God,</hi> as it were; but I am ſure they have drawn backward and hindred the work of the Lord, both in themſelves and others; for <hi>they would neither enter themſelves, nor ſuffer thoſe that would,</hi> but have made War againſt the Light in themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and I teſtifie they are Strangers to the Covenant of Promiſe, Chriſt Jeſus the Light, the New and Living Way, who is the Light of the World, <hi>John</hi> 8.12. <hi>Who is in the World, and the World knows him not, and lighteth every Man that comes into the World,</hi> John 1.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, unto whom <hi>John</hi> came to bear Witneſs, and yet how few will believe? how few doth receive <hi>John</hi>'s Teſtimony, though he was ſent from God to bear Witneſs of the Light? and all hold <hi>John</hi> as a Prophet; alſo, how few do receive Chriſts own Exhortation, who ſaid, <hi>While you have the Light believe in the Light, that you may be Children of the Light,</hi> John 12.36. no marvel if they receive not ours? may it not well be ſaid unto them, <hi>Behold ye Diſpiſers and wonder, I will work a Work in your day, which though
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:172162:81"/>a Man declare it unto you, yet will you in no wiſe believe,</hi> Acts 13.41. [mark] ye Deſpiſers that Deſpiſe the Light, account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it as a thing of nought, (calling it Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, or Diabolical, or an unholy thing) eſteeming it too mean a Meat for your ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed up Stomachs, and cannot yet be digeſted by you; what better Teſtimony would you have? Would you have one ariſe from the Dead? here's <hi>John</hi> a Man ſent from God, and here's Chriſt Jeſus which roſe from the Dead, which Death could not bold; alſo we have the Teſtimony of the Spirit of Truth, <hi>and having received this Teſtimony, we have the Witneſs in our ſelves, and can ſet to our Seals that God is True,</hi> John 3.35, and that there is no other way to the Father, but by Chriſt Jeſus the Light, which is the Life and Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant, though many ſet it at nought, and will not ſtoop to ſo ſmall a thing, yet all the Powers of Darkneſs cannot comprehend it, it will break thorow them all to your condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that are diſobedient; and for proof thereof I appeal to every of your Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the ſight of God, and let the Light therein, <hi>which abideth in you, which is
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:172162:82"/>Truth and no Lye,</hi> John 2.27. let it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare for me whether any of you can hide you from it; <hi>If you take the Wings of the Morning</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> ſaid) <hi>and fly into the uttermoſt parts of the Earth, it will find you out;</hi> do what you will it will declare the nature of your deeds; when you do evil at home or abroad, never ſo ſecretly, when no man ſees, it will condemn you, and when you do well it will juſtifie, and you will feel peace and joy in that Work; it will tell you all that ever you did, as the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſaid, <hi>Is not this the Chriſt, come and ſee;</hi> then they came and ſaw and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved alſo, not becauſe of her words, but by what they heard from him themſelves, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>they knew indeed that this is the very Chriſt,</hi> John 4.42. So be intreated (as a Man would intreat his Friend whom he loveth) to come with the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> and ſee wether it be not ſo as we have ſaid; ſhe was but one, and that a Woman, yet they came forth with her to ſee if it was he, and it was he, and they believed; but we are many Witneſſes, and Teſtifie what we have heard, and ſeen, and handled of him: So once more (I ſay) be intreated to come and ſee;
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:172162:82"/>not to come forth after us, and follow us, as he ſaid, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.21, 23. but to turn in your minds (I mean) to the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in your own Hearts, <hi>for the Kingdom of Heaven is within you,</hi> and there hearken to him that is the Light of the World; (mark, the World is ſet in Mans Heart, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.11.) and when you have heard and obeyed, (for that is believing indeed) I queſtion not but you will be ready to ſay with the <hi>Samaritans, That ye know that he is indeed the very Chriſt.</hi> So put not off by delays, but while the Lord calls do you anſwer, and while he ſeeks be you gathered, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24.26. yea, <hi>while the Light and Love of God is with you believe in it, receive it, and walk in it; for Darkneſs comes when no Man ſhall walk or work,</hi> John 22, 35, 36. <hi>And the Light of the wicked ſhall be put out, and the ſpark of his fire ſhall be quenched,</hi> Job. 18.5, 6. <hi>Then ſhall his Wrath and Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry increaſe, which will torment the Conſcience for ever, where they ſhall feel the Worm that dies not, and the Fire that never goes out; then Sorrow, Mourning and bitter Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall fall upon them; then may they cry to the Mountains fall on us, and to the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:172162:83"/>Hills to cover us;</hi> even they (I mean) that ſlighteth their day of Viſitation, and hate to be reformed; <hi>For behold the Days come that ſhall burn as an Oven, wherein all the proud, and all that do wickedly ſhall be as ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; the Day that cometh ſhall burn them up, and ſhall leave them neither Root nor Branch; but to them that fear my Name, ſaith the Lord, ſhall the Son of Righteouſneſs ariſe with heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Wings, and they ſhall go forth and grow as Calves in the ſtall; and they ſhall tread down the Wicked; yea, the Wicked ſhall be as Aſhes under the ſoles of their feet, in that Day when I ſhall do this ſaith the Lord;</hi> he that can believe it, let him.</p>
                  <p>This is my Teſtimony given forth in the ſame Love wherewith the Lord my God hath loved me, not deſiring to Eat my Morſel alone, nor yet to conceal the loving kindneſs of the Lord, (which is held forth freely unto all) of which I am made a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker, according to the meaſure of that Grace and Love received in Chriſt Jeſus, who would not that any ſhould periſh, but that all Men might come to the knowledge of the Truth and be ſaved; who was the Firſt-fruits of Righteouſneſs, leaving us an Example to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:172162:83"/>follow his ſteps: So deſiring that all might come to partake of the ſame Grace with us, and walk in the ſame Light with us, where there is no occaſion of Stumbling; and come to drink of the ſame Living Water with us, which whoſoever drinketh thereof ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thirſt again, but is ſatisfied for ever, this none knows ſave they that drink thereof, and they are but a few.</p>
                  <p>Having for the Reaſons aforeſaid, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this to publick view, its now other Mens (as well as mine) to judge of, and no doubt may be by ſome oppoſed, as well as by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers approved; I therefore deſire the diſcreet Reader (having ſoberly and piouſly pondred this ſhort Treatiſe, in the fear of the Lord (not raſhly to aſperſe either me or it behind my back, thereby to make my Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple or Teſtimony odious in the Eyes of ſuch as are weak and unſtable in Judgment, but rather (having any thing to object againſt the Truth of any particular herein) to make known their Objections to me, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by word or writing, and I ſhall be very willing to be Chriſtianly informed, or elſe to give a Chriſtian information, and ſober Reply for their ſatisfaction, and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:172162:84"/>for the clearing and vindicating of every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular herein, according to that Talent of knowledge that is given me to improve; and this I hope will be eaſily granted by ſuch as is willing to do unto me as they would have me (or others) to do unto them, which is according to both Law and Prophets.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given forth about</hi> 
                        <date> the 6th <hi>Month,</hi> 1667.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Tho. Carleton.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:172162:84"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:172162:85"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:172162:85"/>
                  <p>To the CALLED OF GOD, And true Profeſſors of the LIGHT &amp; SPIRIT of Jeſus Chriſt, in theſe Northern Nations.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:172162:86"/>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:172162:86"/>
                  <head>To the Called of GOD, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>OH, my well-beloved Friends, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Siſters, in that Spiritual Heavenly Relation, that ſtands in the power of an endleſs Life, do I tenderly Greet you all, and in the ſenſible Feeling thereof, do I at this time with much tenderneſs and fear, communicate theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Exhortations unto you.</p>
                  <p>Upon the Second day of the Tenth Month at Even, after I was returned from
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:172162:87"/>waiting upon, and ſerving the Lord, amongſt the aſſembly of his People, as my body I lay down upon my Bed, expecting to take its natural reſt, my Soul alſo was inclined to take its ſweet repoſe in God, and in my contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, the care of the Churches, and the concerns of the Flock of God, came weightily upon me, ſo that my natural Sleep was wiped away from mine Eyes, and in my Meditation with my God, theſe things fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing roſe freſh in me, and the delivering of them to you, came greatly upon me, ſo that I felt a real neceſſity upon my Soul to ariſe and write: And a cry run through me, and the Mourning of my Spirit, and the Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Soul was very great, for the diviſion of <hi>Reuben,</hi> oh for the diviſion of <hi>Reuben</hi> there was great ſearchings of Heart, oh many a Sigh, oh many a Groan, oh, many a Lamentation is made by many a tender Heart, and many a broken Spirit, for the diviſion of <hi>Reuben,</hi> which at this Day were great and many, ſo that it came upon me in the Dread and Fear of the Eternal God, to Warn all the Churches, all the Called of God, all the Profeſſors of his Name, High, and Low, Rich and Poor, Man and Woman,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:172162:87"/>to beware of Divſion, even the Diviſion of <hi>Reuben</hi> the Firſt-born, therefore take heed, take heed all you that were Firſt-born, or Firſt begotten to God, who were as the Firſt-fruits of the Spirit in this laſt Age, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation; Oh let all be Adviſed I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly intreat you, and in the Counſel of God, do I hereby Warn you all, to beware and avoid Diviſion, for that Houſe that is Devid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it ſelf, and againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand, oh let me adviſe and warn you (in the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and brokenneſs of my mourning Soul) as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did his Brethren of old, ſee that you fall not out by the way, oh feel, feel the melting compaſſionate Spirit of <hi>Joſeph</hi> whoſe Bowels broke towards his Brethren, and he wept upon their Neck, oh that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Spirit of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> he ſought no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge when they were fallen into his Hand, and there ſheaves came bowing to his ſheave; and the eleven ſtars did obeiſance unto him, he was not lifted up, nor exalted with Pride, though Lord of all <hi>Egypt,</hi> as he ſaid but was full of Compaſſion and wept over them when they were ſmitten and terrified with Guilt, only innocent <hi>Benjamin</hi> wept upon his Neck: Oh ſee his care to his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:172162:88"/>fall not out by the way; And as our faithful Father <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid to his Nephew <hi>Lot,</hi> let there be no ſtrife between us for we are Brethren, and the <hi>Canaanite</hi> and the <hi>Perizite</hi> they dwell in the Land, they will ſee it and behold it, and this will agravate the Sin and the Lord will greatly be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by it. Oh ſee the Care and Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Spirit of faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> how he ſought to preſerve Peace and Love, and even as it were ſubmitted to his Nephew <hi>Lot,</hi> the whole Land is before thee, take thy choice, and let not us ſtrive for we are Brethren, ſo here was no ſuperiority nor exalted Spirit in <hi>Abraham;</hi> but he works by Love, Oh my dear Friends be you all warned and take heed of Diviſion; for we are now upon our Travel, and upon our Return out of <hi>Egypt</hi> as <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren were, and the Lord hath given us Favour in the ſight of <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Princes, and hath given a large ſupply to the Souls of us, and our families who was ſorely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with Famine yet in all this there is no cauſe of Diviſion, let no ones Heart be exalted or lifted up becauſe of Gods Love to them; <hi>We are now Returning to
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:172162:88"/>the premiſed Land the Land of Reſt and Peace,</hi> Therefore let us return in Peace, and dwell in Love together, for Love is of God, and he that dwells in Love, dwells in God; and this Love thinks no Evil its no maintainer of Strife, nor no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getter of Diviſion, And take the Advice of the Apoſtle, mark them that cauſe Diviſion, and avoid them, and from whence comes War and Strife, and from whence comes all Diviſion, do they not riſe from fleſhly ſelf-ſeeking Luſts that War againſt the Soul; And is not the accuſer of the Brethren con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, would not he accuſe us one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſet us at variance one with another, and provoke to ſell, and betray one another into the hands of the <hi>Medianites,</hi> to be Bondſlaves in <hi>Egypt</hi> again.</p>
                  <p>And what is the matter the accuſer works upon, <hi>is it ſome party coloured Coat the Father is pleaſed to beſtow upon one more then another, or upon ſome dream of Exaltation, or being Prefered one above another, or is it about ſome Trifle, Jangling, or queſtions of Words, thus the Enemy laboured of old and wrought Diviſion, and thus he would Work now if he be not watched againſt,</hi>
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:172162:89"/>Oh therefore all take heed, and labour to keep near the Lord every Man for himſelf, and every Woman for her ſelf; labour to keep out that Spirit that would provoke to ſtrife, and to contention, oh let it enter into none, nor (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entered) keep poſſeſſion in any for where Strife is there is Confuſion and every Evil work, ſo if any thing would ariſe at any time that tends to Strief, or would rend, and make Diviſion; in the Bowels of the love of God; I deſire all to watch againſt it, ſhut it out, cruſh that Cockatrice timely; kindle no ſuch fire, nor blow up that Flame with words, but in the meek ſpirit of Jeſus quench it, and rather give place to wrath, for a ſoft mild anſwer turns it away; always remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Why do you not rather ſuffer wrong, and ſuffer your ſelves to be defrauded, and ſet them to judge that are leaſt in the Church, that a ſpeedy end may be put to it:</hi> And as Chriſt himſelf ſaid, <hi>he that would be Chief let him become Servant, and as I have waſhed your Feet, even ſo waſh you one anothers Feet:</hi> Here was a bleſſed Example of Humility laid down, and the lording of the Gentiles reproved. And truly Friends, they that ſtand ſingle in the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:172162:89"/>light and counſel of God, whoſe Eye is impartial may clearly See, and diſtinguiſh in all matters of Debate and Controverſie, what ſpirit Rules, for if the Lambs ſpirit be there, there is Innocency, there is Tenderneſs, there is Humility, there is broken Hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that ſpirit that is from above is Gentle, Meek, and Lowly, eaſie to be entreated; it is not ſtubborn, proud nor ſelf willed, it hates not Reproof as Fools, but it loves the Reprover as a wiſe Man; ſo they that are of this ſpirit they are of <hi>Abraham's</hi> Seed, and of <hi>Abraham's</hi> Faith, let there be no ſtrife between us for we are Brethren, they will readily comply, and follow after Peace, knowing that the Lords Honour, and the Honour of his Truth is concerned; ſo let the fruits of the Lambs ſpirit appear in all, let the Lambs nature come up, and rule in all, that the Lamb and his followers may have the Victory; ſo ſhut out all Pride, all Stubbornneſs, all Ambition, all ſelf Exaltation, and Worldly glory, let that ſpirit and nature, bow down at the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool of the Lamb, and come bending unto him as <hi>Joſeph's</hi> Brethren to <hi>Joſeph;</hi> Oh how then would his Bowels break, and weep
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:172162:90"/>over its neck, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> over his Brethren, and the Father over his prodigal, oh how willing is he to receive ſuch, and love them freely; therefore all keep near the Lord and wait to feel univerſal Love in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Spirit of Jeſus, that it may fill all, poſſeſs all, and mutually flow through all, that your firſt love may be ſtrengthened, even the love of your eſpouſals, whereby you were firſt eſpouſed to God, and united one unto another, this will renew you again, oh the comlineſs, and the beauty of this firſt love, how precious and ſweet it was; many of us may yet remember, how it drew our Souls to God, and one unto another, oh what a Heavenly harmony, what a Heavenly oneneſs this love, this firſt love did beget, how it wrought all into concord, and unity as one Body, one Heart and one Spirit, to hold the ſame Teſtimony and ſpeak the ſame Thing, in the one pure Language, out of the many Languages, and out of all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion the root and ſpring of it; oh the amiableneſs of that firſt love, the love that thinks no evil, how precious and ſweet a thing it is to behold, and to ſee Brethren dwell together in it, it truly preaches for
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:172162:90"/>God, and is one infallible ſigne of a Diſciple of Jeſus Chriſt as by himſelf lay'd down, by this ſhall all Men know that you are my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples becauſe ye love one another, for love is of God: <hi>So if any have turned aſide, if any one be hurt, if any one be wounded, here is their balm, retire to their Primitive purity, to their firſt Zeal, to their firſt fervent deſire, to their firſt love and tenderneſs, that which is ſtronger then Death which many waters cannot quench, nor floods waſh away;</hi> Oh that all would be ſtirred up to wait upon the Lord, to feel the renewings of it, that in ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of Spirit we may ſerve one another, and provoke one another to love and good works, and in that dwell together, and watch againſt Diviſion and the author and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of it, and the God of Peace and Love will be with us, and he will delight to dwell amongſt us, and he will cauſe his that abide in his Love to revive as the Corn and to bloſſom as the Roſe, and their comlineſs will appear again as the morning Sun upon the Mountains; ſo every particular retire, retire to your firſt Love, to your firſt Integrity to your firſt Zeal for God, let not that be loſt as the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> did; leaſt the
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:172162:91"/>Lord the Juſt and Righteous God, remove the Candleſtick out of its place; ſo all do your firſt Works, and keep your firſt Teſtimonies unviolated, in Doctrine, Life and Practice, for this Preaches much for God.</p>
                  <p>And truly Friends this is a ſearching Day, though a Day of outward eaſe, yet a Day of inward trouble to many, a ſifting trying Day, the Day of Satans transformings, who goes ſubtilly about to deceive, and with his Tail would ſweep down a third part of the Stars and cauſe them to fall to the Earth; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my dear Friends keep low and humble before the Lord, within the Sanctuary of God, and lay timely hold upon the hornes of the Altar thereof, for the Day of ſifting is begun, and the Day of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowing is at hand, wherein our God will ſift the Nations, and winnow the People, he will fan them, yea he will fan them, and thorowly purge them, he will take away the chaff from the wheat, and purge away the droſs from the ſilver in his refining Fire, and who ſhall ſtand when he appears, who ſhall dwell with devouring Fire, or who ſhall dwell with everlaſting Burnings, only he that walketh Righteouſly, and ſpeaketh Upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:172162:91"/>who abhoreth the gain of oppreſſion, and ſhutteth his eyes from ſeeing Evil.</p>
                  <p>And truly Friends our God is come and comming to execute Juſtice and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Earth, I have ſeen it, yea in the Light of Jeſus, I have beheld the Lord for ſeveral years paſt, how he hath been ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the Sins of the Daughter of his People; and bringing to Light the hidden things of diſhoneſty, yea how hath the Lord ſought out the hidden things of <hi>Eſau;</hi> ſo there is nothing covered but he can reveal it, nor nothing hid that he doth not know, his Eye ſees all, and his Ear hears all, his Juſtice he will Execute upon the head of the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor, and he will wound the hairy ſcalp of the Head of the Evil doer, whether profeſſor or prophane, let none think to eſcape, Wealth nor Wiſdom he will not regard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mountains nor Hills can preſerve or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any of the Workers of In quity in this ſearching Day; <hi>the Righteous God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven will not be bribed, he will not be mocked nor diſſembled with,</hi> though prophane Men <hi>Johanan</hi> like, may diſſemble with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and may for a time appear like <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> Tombs with a fair ſmooth poliſhed
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:172162:92"/>Face in the ſight of Men, and may ſubtilly cover their Sin, and keep their deeds of deceipt and darkneſs hid from the Eye of Man for a time, <hi>and like a painted Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot wipe their mouth, as though they had done no Evil, flattering themſelves with their own crafty Wit, making lyes and falſhood their refuge,</hi> yet the Juſt and Righteous God, who judges Righteouſly he will find out ſuch, he will diſcover their skirts, and uncover all their nakedneſs to their ſhame and utter confuſion:</p>
                  <p>Therefore all take heed of maintaining any thing hiddenly, in the dread of the Lord God I warn you; but mind the Light of Jeſus, and the leadings of it in your own Hearts, and live in that, walk with God in that as <hi>Enoch</hi> did of old; and then you need not fear the Tryal of the Day, though your Deeds be revealed upon the Houſe top, your nakedneſs will not become your ſhame, you will need no deceitfull coverings nor aprons of Fig-leaves, ſo to the Witneſs all retire, it will diſſemble with none, it will truly diſcover your preſent eſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition before God and the nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of every thing you undertake, I know
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:172162:92"/>the experience of it, not a foot can turn aſide out of the narrow way of Life, but (being waited in) it will certainly diſcover; the worth and preciouſneſs of it, let no one ever deſpiſe; Oh my dear Friends em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it take heed of riding over or trampling on its reproofs, or of thinking to ſmother and quench it in your ſelves, no no, its mouth can never be ſtoped, nor its judgment ever perverted, it will be as Ten thouſand Witneſſes, it will one Day be too hard for all that now rejects it, And will put the World the Fleſh and the Devil to ſilence.</p>
                  <p>So let none be puffed up with any thing, truſt not to <hi>Egypts</hi> help nor to the Worlds wiſdom, for they will be as a broken Reed, but all keep low, and mind the narrow Way that leadeth unto Life, the ſelf denying way, 'tis but a few that find it, yea perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture but a few of that few that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes to walk in it; The broad way the way of the World lies very near on every hand, it is ſoon ſtepped into, if once ones Eye be turned aſide, then it appears delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and hath a ſhow of Beauty in it, but it leads to the chambers of Death.</p>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:172162:93"/>
                  <p>And my Friends thoſe things I laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you in my former Epiſtle, I hope I need not here reiterate or make repetition of, but as I was enjoyned by the Lord to deliver them unto you; ſo I would have all Male and Female, to ponder them in your Hearts that all may be clear, and I clear of all, And Friends keep your Hearts clear of the ſpirit of this World, of all the Ways, Faſhions, Pleaſures and Alurements thereof; <hi>ſhake your ſelves from them, live looſe to them, for things may be Lawful to them, and by their Law, that may not be Lawful to us by our Law.</hi> The Law of the ſpirit, <hi>here is our rule, ſo take heed of meaſuring by their Rule, for our Rule being ſpiritual, exceeds all their carnal Rules; and our Righteouſneſs muſt exceed theirs alſo, ſo all minding the Rule, and minding the Line, none needs go out of their Way, for it exceeds all the Lines and Rules of Mans making, ſo come to the juſt meaſure, the meaſure of Truth, for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt meaſures are abomination in the ſight of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:172162:93"/>
                  <p>And all ſhake your ſelves from all the Whoriſh Babiloniſh brats, from all her Cuſtoms, from all her Ways and Worſhips, partake not of them, <hi>come away come away, haſten haſten out from among them,</hi> bid adieu to all her Glories and eſcape for your lives as <hi>Lot</hi> did out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gods deſtroying Angel go forth, for his Wrath is kindling and his Fury is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up into his Face, and who ſhall ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; Oh therefore come, come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, linger not, haſten, haſten, to little <hi>Zoar</hi> the City of our Refuge, which God hath appointed for us, come give up, give up all, in pure obedience follow the Lamb, even the Lamb of God that takes away the ſin, and finiſheth Tranſgreſſion, and breaks the bonds of Death, oh give up, leave all and come away, and wait to feel the Blood of ſprinkling, the Blood of the Lamb to ſprinkle the poſts of your Doors that the deſtroying Angel may not enter, but may paſs over you as he paſſed over his <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old; for I know it from the Lord and can declare it unto you, that God hath a Remnant at this Day, (as he had in that) that are in Covenant with
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:172162:94"/>him; And thoſe are they that hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed Truth in their inward parts; and hath kept their Garments unſpotted of the World, and hath walked with God in the ſimplicity of their Hearts, they are his, he hath Choſen them out of the World, he hath called them by his Name, and eſpouſed them to himſelf, and whoſever toucheth them touches the apple of his Eye, God will take care of them and will be their munitioned Rock, he will paſs by them and ſpare them as a Man ſpareth his onely Son that ſerveth him; oh therefore retire, retire to the Lowly, Meek, and ſelf-denying Spirit of Jeſus, live in the poſſeſſion of it, ſo ſhall you be Heirs of Life and Glory in and through Chriſt Jeſus, and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of the New and Heavenly <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> whoſe Walls is ſalvation and Gate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> praiſe, and though fear may ſurprize the hypocrite, and aſtoniſhment ceaſe upon the Diſobedient and Rebellious, yet you ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>and as Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> that cannot be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the Lord God Almighty will ſtrengthen your ſtakes, ſo that not a ſtake of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> can be removed, nor a Cord of <hi>Zion</hi> ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e broken, the Mouth of the Lord hath ſaid
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:172162:94"/>it. Oh therefore all ſink down, ſink down to the pure Principle of God in the inward Man, the juſt Mans path, the ſhining Light of Jeſus Chriſt, oh let that Guide all, and Order all, and then may we ſay with <hi>David,</hi> thy Word o Lord is a Light unto my feet and a Lanthorn unto my paths indeed, and ſo in the Light feel the Love, the firſt Love renewed, and ſtrengthened again, oh ſtrengthen, ſtrengthen that little that yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, that it may grow warmer and warmer, and not colder and colder; for where ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity abounds there Love grows cold, and undoubtedly in ſuch the Life declines; therefore feel univerſal Love to grow, to fill, to run through all, for Love worketh no ill to his Neighbour, it is the fulfilling of the Law as faith the Apoſtle; ſo if any one Male or Female have declined, have walked diſorderly, have turned aſide from the holy Commandment, from the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of the flock of God, from the holy Order of the holy Life, and Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, it ſtops the Currant of Love both in themſelves and others, oh let ſuch return, return, repent and amend, and bow to the Righteous Judgment of him to whom all
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:172162:95"/>Judgment is committed, and at the Footſtool of Jeſus truly humbled, in true Tenderneſs and Contrition of Spirit, wait to feel the Currant and Streams of Love from God the Father, to flow in, and heal again, and to reſtore again, that ſo the heavenly ſap, vertue and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal love may be felt to ſpring, run and aſcend again through every member or branch, that love and good will in all may grow and increaſe, and the contrary nature may decline, and that root in which enmity, ſelf-love, pride and contention, ſtands, may be dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubdued and ſlain, that all may bow to the Croſs and be ſubject to the Power, the heavenly Power of God, oh feel it, feel it, in your Souls to live, oh let none reſiſt it in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor in others, for whoever reſiſts the Power reſiſts the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, <hi>ſo priſe it, priſe it my dear Friends, retain the ſenſe and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:172162:95"/>of it in your ſelves;</hi> let not that be loſt in any high nor low, rich or poor, old nor young, there is a living Beauty and Comlineſs in it ſtill, it is beyond all profeſſions or preſcribed Forms, or imitations of Mans mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, there can no form nor likneſs be made of it, ſo the nature and work of the Power being poſſeſſed and lived in, it will preſerve all in Love, Unity and Peace and Heavenly fellowſhip, and ſpiritual oneneſs, out of all jars, ſtrifes, diſcords or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions; And the God of Peace and Love will be with us, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to do us good, and will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly cheriſh and maintain his own heavenly Birth and righteous Seed, which by the over ſhadowings of his heavenly eternal Power he hath begotten, and raiſed in all his regenerated ones.</p>
                  <p>So to the pure gift of God, I Recommend you all my dear Friends
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:172162:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>Brethren and Siſters, that in it we may all hold the miſtery of Faith in a pure Conſcience, even that Faith that gives Victory and Dominion over the World, and all that nature, that in it we may live, and by it all may be preſerved, unto the end, That ſo the Lord God Almighty his Living Holy Name, and Eternal Truth may be Feared, Served, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and Obeyed over all, by and through all, for He alone is worthy, yea Everlaſting worthy, God bleſſed for ever and evermore,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Saith the Soul and Spirit of him who is the Lords and yours in the Unity of the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>T. C.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:172162:96"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:172162:97"/>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:172162:97"/>
                  <head>A General EPISTLE: CONTAINING Wholſom Admonition and Advice to Friends in <hi>IRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND,</hi> and elſe-where.</head>
                  <byline>By <hi>Thomas Carleton.</hi>
                  </byline>
                  <p>DEar and well beloved Friends, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Siſters who are in ſome Meaſure gathered by the Arm of God's Power, and have known the bleſſed Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:172162:98"/>of Life and Salvation, to you is the Salutation of my unfeigned Love, and in the Fellowſhip of God's Everlaſting Light do I tenderly greet you all; and for the clearing of my Spirit, of that which for ſome time hath been upon me, do I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate theſe Lines, in the true Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of my Heart, dearly deſiring all that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, To keep low and near the Lord, and wait to feel God's living Power in your Hearts, unto which we were turned or exhorted from the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; for, in the Light of the Lord, I ſee there is a Neceſſity for it: For, unleſs the Senſe of God's living Power be felt, Profeſſion is vain, and Meetings are not made profitable; for the Myſteries of Life and Salvation, and of true <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt not only in any Profeſſion, Name or Notion, of this or that Principle, Article or Creed, formed or received in the Minds of Men or Women, but in a living Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Poſſeſſion of the Power and Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus, the Author and Finiſher of the living ſaving Faith. So my dear Friends, all wait to feel the Operation of that Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in every Heart and Soul, to ſubdue all
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:172162:98"/>to God, and to work all into ſubmiſſion and real obedience to the heavenly Will and Mind of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>who is come a Light into the World, that all men through him might believe;</hi> hear is the unchangeable ſtanding Rule, which every one is to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure themſelves by; and he or ſhe that is meaſured or ſquared by this, are as poliſhed Stones for God's ſpiritual Houſe; and he or ſhe that is not ſquared by this, are not fit to be Members of God's Building: ſo all having the Meaſuring line in your hearts, let Judgment be laid to it, and ſo try all things, words, works, behaviours, and the Intent of all, and from what ground and ſpirit it doth proceed: and this unchangeable everlaſting Rule all keep to it, and Build by it, ſo ſhall you be juſtified with it in the Day of Tryal; ſo all things done by this unchangeable unerring Rule (the Law of the Spirit of Life) this keeps clean and pure, and ſets free of all Mud and Confuſion, Sin and Iniquity, and things that bring death and darkneſs over the Soul and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo cloud the Teſtimony: So let every man and woman (by this ſtanding Rule) examine themſelves, and ſo let them
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:172162:99"/>eat, ſpeak or act, as the Lord ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them; and wherein any one doubteth, and is not clear in what he or ſhe undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, let ſuch forbare, and wait in quietneſs till the Lord clear their way: So all take heed, and keep to the Rule; <hi>for in the Lord's Light we ſee Light, and have Clearneſs, and Freedom, and Peace? but going from the Light, without Rule, without Guide the Vail comes over, Darkneſs gathers in, Confuſion and Trouble, then Peace comes to be loſt.</hi> So you that have known in any meaſure the work of Regeneration, and of the New Birth, through the working of God's Spirit and power in your Hearts, by which ſome unclean ſpirits have been caſt out, keep to the Power ſtill, and beware of letting in the unclean ſpirit again, for if you do, the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-end will be worſe then the beginning. And lean not to the World's Wiſdom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of that ſpirit I adviſe all; for by that wiſdom God is not known; and if once the Senſe and enjoyment of God be loſt, then man and woman is in a woful ſtate, without God in the World; ſo keep out of the world's ſpirit I intreat you all, and live as Fools to it, and all its <hi>wayes, faſhions</hi> &amp; <hi>cuſtoms,</hi> for
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:172162:99"/>in the light of the Lord I ſee a great Snare there at this day and too many that make Profeſſion of Truth are like to be ſplit upon that Rock. So dear Friends, live looſe to the world, and all the glories of it, and ſeek to be wiſe in that which is not of this world, that you may be loved of God; and ſo dwell in that which can bear the <hi>revilings</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches</hi> of this world, and the <hi>contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinners,</hi> as our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath left us an Example: So beware of looking back to <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Glory again. to ſee any <hi>heauty</hi> or <hi>comlineſs</hi> in that dark Land, for, from the Lord I ſee a Temptation attending God's ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael</hi> in this day, as ſurely as ever it attended <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the Fleſh, and many are too prone to deſire the <hi>pleaſures</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> again (<hi>though the beſt of them be</hi> bondage, <hi>as many to their Sorrow have found</hi>) yea, too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there be that cannot bear <hi>tryals</hi> and <hi>reproaches,</hi> and the <hi>way of the Croſs</hi> and <hi>ſelf-denyal,</hi> but think it <hi>long,</hi> and <hi>weariſom,</hi> and <hi>hard,</hi> as they did in the dayes of old, and ſo are too ready to murmur and repine, and luſt in their hearts after this World<hi>'s glory</hi> again, and joyn to its <hi>faſhions</hi> and <hi>cuſtoms</hi>
                     <pb n="174" facs="tcp:172162:100"/>again, and ſo ſet up Idols again, as they did whoſe <hi>Carcaſes fell in tho wilderneſs,</hi> with whom the Lord was diſpleaſed: So beware of letting in that ſpirit of <hi>deſtruſt, unbelief</hi> and <hi>rebellion</hi> againſt God, and his pure Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in your Conſciences, and beware of building that which was once deſtroyed, or licking up that which was once vomited, or entertaining of that which was once caſt out, or owning that which was once denyed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>words,</hi> in <hi>works,</hi> in <hi>behaviour,</hi> in <hi>apparel,</hi> in <hi>doctrine</hi> or <hi>faith:</hi> hath Truth in you condemned for all idle, vain pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, wicked, unfound and unfavoury <hi>words,</hi> and brought you into a Form of needful, true and ſound <hi>words?</hi> keep to it ſtill: hath Truth condemned all idle, proud, prophane, wicked and ungodly <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and all empty, airy, fooliſh, wanton, luſtful, proud, ſelf-willed and Men-pleaſing <hi>behaviours,</hi> and brought you into modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, gravity, plainneſs, reallity and Truth in Life and Converſation? keep to it ſtill: hath Truth condemned for decking and adorning the Body with vain, ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, proud, needleſs, worldly, eye-taking Toyes in Apparel, and led you into plain,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:172162:100"/>profitable, decent, needful things? keep to it ſtill: and faſhion not your ſelves like unto the World, nor learn any of their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, nor of the breeding of that <hi>Egyptian</hi>-Spirit, which keeps the Seed in bondage, and oppreſſed the juſt in the particular and in the general; ſo from the Lord I adviſe you all, and warn you all that are Parents, to watch over your Children, and bring them up in the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord, and beware you breed them not up in the World's manners nor cuſtoms, nor in pride, lightneſs and vanity, nor in things that puff up and lead away their minds from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Croſs of Chriſt Jeſus, but rather breed them up in Humility, Lowlineſs and Self-denial, and in the Fear of the Lord, which is the beginning of true Wiſdom and gate of Virtue; and ſo endeavour to train them up in the right Way to Life, and lay a good Foundation in them while they are young, and then both you and they may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a bleſſing from the Lord which is better then all. So away with all Manners and Breeding, and Education that is out of the Fear of God; for you your ſelves know, the firſt Nature in it ſelf is too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:172162:101"/>to be taken with the Manners and Cuſtoms of the <hi>Egyptian</hi>-Spirit, and to take pleaſure and conceit it ſelf, and be puffed up with, and in thoſe things that lead from God, without nurſing and encouraging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; ſo keep all Low in Meekneſs and Self-denial, that God's Fear may be timely planted in their Hearts, and the Principles of Life and Peace, they may be inſtructed in, as you your ſelves have learned them of the Lord, that ſo the loving-kindneſs and gentle dealings of God towards us, we may tell of them to our Children, and they to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Generation; ſo all learning the way of the Croſs and Self-denyal, that Will that is carnal and earthly will be mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and ſlain, and the Spirit of the World and the Cuſtoms thereof will be Crucified to you all, and you all unto it, and then, how can they that are Crucified to the World live any longer therein? and ſo Spiritual Men and Spiritual Women, Sons and Daughters of the incorruptible Seed, begotten again by the Power and Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus, and ſo dead to the World's Spirit, Ways, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms. Manners, Traditions, Ordinances and Worſhips, all in the Fall and Degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:172162:101"/>from God, and every one Living up to this, being guided by God's Wiſdom, keep their Teſtimony clear and unviolated in the ſight of God and Men.</p>
                  <p>So ſtand true Witneſſes for God and be Faithful or full of Faith in the Lord; believe in Him, love Him above all, and truſt Him with all, Wife and Children, Eſtate and Life; and take heed of giving Offence, or of cauſing Truth to ſuffer in its Eſteem; for God hath glorified it, and will glorifie it; and Wo from the Lord is to them that cauſe Truth to be Evil ſpoken off, that brings a blot upon their Teſtimony, and ſo marreth the Viſage and Countenance of Truth in the particular, or in the general.</p>
                  <p>And dear Friends ſtand living. Witneſſer for God's Truth, and be not cowardly, but valiant, as Soldiers of Chriſt Jeſus, and ſtand up againſt all the Works and Workers of Iniquity, againſt all Hirelings and falſe Shepherds, againſt the grand Oppreſſion of Tythes, with the aboliſhed Ceremonies and Ordinances of the firſt Covenant, and <hi>Jews</hi> outwardly, which Antichriſt and the Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that are gone into the World (having loſt the Power) would innovate and ſet up
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:172162:102"/>again among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> inward, contrary to the Inſtitution of God; and ſtand up againſt all Swearing, and that which leads to Swearing, and againſt Lying or Stealing, and againſt Fighting or Killing (ſince our Kingdom is not of this World) and againſt Fornication, Adultery, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Laſciviouſneſs, Luxury, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Uncleanneſs, the ſins of this World, which are ſo vile they are ſcarce fit to be ſpoken of, or named amongſt the Saints; ſo as becomes Warriours for God, and the everlaſting Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus, ſtand clear of them all, and againſt them all, and then there will be no need of ſhifts and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, and crooked Reaſons in the fallen wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to hide or cover any one with.</p>
                  <p>And my dear Friends, let your Yea be Yea, and your Nay be Nay, and keep to the form of ſound words in all your Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications, Bargains and Dealings one with another, and alſo with them that are without, that ſo you may honour the Lord, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour his Truth, and convince all with whom you have to do, that <hi>Truth and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs lives in you, and you live in it;</hi> this is the glory of all Profeſſion. And be not
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:172162:102"/>forward and raſh in Words and Promiſes; for ſome there are, yea, too many, that make Profeſſion of Truth and true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet know not a bridle for the Tongue, and the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>ſuch Mens Religion was vain;</hi> yea, and too many there are, that are <hi>haſty to promiſe,</hi> and <hi>flow to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form,</hi> and then ſhuffle to excuſe themſelves (as <hi>Eve</hi> did) where no Excuſe can properly bear in the Truth; ſo beware of it, I deſire you all, for this was one expreſs Token the Apoſtle laid down of the <hi>falling away;</hi> therefore be ſlow to promiſe, but careful, quick and forward to perform, when pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and that keeps Truth clear, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers the Expectations of all, and Preaches to all with whom we have to do, and hereby the Saints reached God's Witneſs in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the beginning, ſo keep to it ſtill, and every one ſpeak the Truth from his Heart without <hi>Diſſimulation,</hi> and learn not the ſlighty words and cunning evaſions of the deceitful Spirits of this World, which darken knowledge, thereby to drive Bargains, to accompliſh ſelf-ends and covetous deſigns; for ſuch things (though never ſo fairly gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) are inconſiſtent with the innocency and
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:172162:103"/>naked ſimplicity of our Goſpel, neither is Truth honoured by ſuch deceitful coverings: ſo all Friends, keep clear of ſuch things, and be plain-hearted with all Men; for no <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings</hi> will hide or avail in this bright light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>Day,</hi> but that of God's Eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which will ſtand over all, and Darkneſs cannot comprehend it; but going from the Light and Spirit of God, into the fallen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful wiſdom, then the World comprehends and ſounds, and bottoms all ſuch, and ſo Truth ſuffers in the particular, and in the general; ſo the Law of the Spirit of Life, which we profeſs, is beyond all Laws, and a Rule beyond all Rules, and reaches further to the ordering and guiding of all thoſe that are reſolved and given up to it, in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, then all Laws, Precepts, Canons or Injuctions that are outward whatſoever; ſo the Righteoſneſs that is God's, which Chriſt Jeſus is the Author of, is beyond all, and exceeds all the Righteouſneſs of other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, <hi>Scribes</hi> or <hi>Phariſees;</hi> whereby its plain every Righteoſneſs doth not enter, nor is accepted of God, but only that which exceeds the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> which Chriſt works in all his by the Operation of
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:172162:103"/>his eternal Spirit. So my dear Friends, wait to feel it, and the effectual Works of it brought forth in you all, which to feel is more then words, that your Faith may ſtand in it, and in a living Enjoyment of it; for that Man or Woman that doth not feel it, and the efficacy and vertue of it, they bring from a ſtrange Vine, which Chriſt Jeſus will not own; and all take heed, and keep low in God's Fear. And you my Friends that are Rich in this World, or have much of the Creation of God, do you watch and take heed; for there is a Snare, and that none of the leaſt, which attends that ſtate alſo; and if the Lord hath encreaſed your ſtore, ſet not your Hearts upon them, nor truſt to them; <hi>for he that truſteth to his Riches, ſhall fall,</hi> for as one ſaid, <hi>They are not for ever, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time make themſelves Wings, and fly away:</hi> ſo be not lifted up with them, but eye the Lord, and poſſeſs as though you poſſeſſed not, and labour to be Rich towards God, and Rich in good Works; and remember poor afflicted <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and be ready to do good, and to communicate, as ſaid the Apoſtle, and keep your Hearts ſingle and looſe to thoſe things, and ſo in God's Wiſdom you
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:172162:104"/>will ſee your Way and Service, and the End and Uſe of all. And all you Young Men and Women, that are ſingle and unmarryed, you have an Oportunity to ſerve the Lord? do you keep low, and beware of being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled or brought in Bondage by youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Luſts; for thereby many have loſt a <hi>good condition</hi> with God, and brought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Sorrow and Wo, both in this Life and that which is to come: And above all, take heed of joyning Affinity with ſtrange Nations, and ſuch as know not God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor obey the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; for this was forbidden <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the fleſh, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.3.4. and for their Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience herein, God's anger was kindled againſt them, and they were carryed away captive many; years which made <hi>Ezra,</hi> the Servant of the Lord, rent his Garments, and pluck his Hair off his Head and Beard, and mourn before the Lord, till he and the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> reſolved to put away their Strange Wives, <hi>Ez</hi> 9, 10. chap. And <hi>Eſau</hi> by marrying the Daughters of <hi>Heth,</hi> ſo grieved his Father and Mother, that <hi>Rebecca</hi> complained, <hi>ſhe was weary of her Life,</hi> Gen. 27.46. And <hi>Paul</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:172162:104"/>
                     <hi>not to be unequally yoked together, Believers with Unbelievers, knowing there could be no Union between Light and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nor the Temple of God and Idols, &amp;c.</hi> ſo keep your Hearts ſingle to God, and wait in God's Wiſdom to overcome the Wicked One in your own particulars, and ſeek to be marryed to the Lord firſt, and joyned to the Lord by his eternal Spirit, which brings into Unity, and keeps Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Mind and Spirit unto him: and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Advice of the Apoſtle, who ſaid, <hi>The Unmarried cared for the things of the Lord, how he or ſhe might pleaſe the Lord; but the married for the things of this World, how he or ſhe might pleaſe Wife or Husband:</hi> So all be watchful, and mind your Places and Callings in Chriſt Jeſus: but if any one (in the Fear and Wiſdom of God) do ſee it their way to marry, let ſuch ſeek God's Counſel, and be not haſty, but wait in it, that he or ſhe may enjoy a Wife or a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in the Peace and Love of God, and to be joyned one by his eternal Spirit, and then Meet helps and a Bleſſing one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and then the Marriage is honourable, and the Bed undefiled; ſo all keep clean,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:172162:105"/>and live up to God in all things, in all States and Conditions, in your Places and Callings whereunto God hath called you, that the Lord may take pleaſure to do you good, and to multiply his Bleſſings upon you, that the Iſſues of Life and Peace may abound, and run through all, and reſt upon all your Hearts and Souls as the dew of <hi>Hermon. And the God of Peace and Love preſerve us all in his Peace and Love, and carry us through all by the Arm of his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Power, and guide us all in his heavenly Wiſdom, to the Praiſe, Glory and Renown of his Everlaſting Name, who is God alone, bleſſed forever and for evermore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Written <date>the 13th. of the 7th Month 1676.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Friend &amp; Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Truth,</hi> Tho. Carleton.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:172162:105"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
